<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A divine discoverie of death directing all people to a triumphant resurrection, and euer-lasting saluation.</title>
            <author>Vaughan, Edward, preacher at St. Mary Woolnoth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 236 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 107 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14280</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24596</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105922</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841647</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841647</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6245</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14280)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6245)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1612:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A divine discoverie of death directing all people to a triumphant resurrection, and euer-lasting saluation.</title>
                  <author>Vaughan, Edward, preacher at St. Mary Woolnoth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 197 [i.e. 199], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted [by R. Field] for William Iones [3] and Richard Boyle, dwelling in the Blackfriers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Edward Vaughan.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Pages 94 and 179 repeated in number only.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Resurrection --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6245:1"/>
            <p>A DIVINE DISCOVERIE OF DEATH, Directing all people to a trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant reſurrection, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſaluation.</p>
            <q>
               <p>It is ordained that all men ſhall die.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEB. 9.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Vnum hoc geſtit verit as ne ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norata damnetur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Imprinted for WILLIAM IONES, and RICHARD BOYLE dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Blackefriers. 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6245:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6245:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, MY VERY GOOD LORD, <hi>HENRY</hi> THE EARLE OF HVNTINGTON.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S amongſt all ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary accidents inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the proſperity &amp; aduerſity of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, there is nothing more momentarie then mariage: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo, right honorable, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more anſwerable to the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; condemnation of mankind then death. For as by the one all men come into the world, &amp; by the other all men go out of the world: euen ſo by both, all men without the merits of Ieſus Chriſt, ſhall go
<pb facs="tcp:6245:3"/>into hell fire. Yet for all that, there is nothing more out of the minds of men then death, nor any thing leſſe feared then Gods irefull iudgments which follow after. As may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in euerie profeſſion which is ſtained and polluted with heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh impietie: the like was not in the time of blindneſſe and ignorance; whereby it may be truly ſaid, that the laſt of the three reuolutions ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by ſeales,<note place="margin">Reu. 5.1. &amp; 8.2. &amp;. 17.1.</note> by trumpets, &amp; by viols, related to be the diſhonour of God, and the diſturbance of the Church militant, is now more freſh and more ragingly reuiued, then in any of the two former reuolutions, conſiſting of 600. yeares. Your Lordſhip perhaps will ſay, What is that to me? how can I redreſſe it? I know my Lord, I know, and in truth I muſt acknowledge, that you are an example vnto others, for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent hearing of Gods holy word
<pb facs="tcp:6245:3"/>preached, and for the ſincere recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Sacrament: well may your Honor go on and be ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the zeale of Gods glory, and be recommended before the throne of Gods grace, by the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of ſuch as you did releeue when they were oppreſſed. But the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall cauſe of this my clamor is, to put you in mind of that you know, to wit, ſeeing ſinne is ſo generall &amp; the ſame ſo horribly hainous, that there is nothing elſe to be looked for but death, and not that death onely which is the common viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all men; but alſo the ſecond death, which is the perpetuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the diuell and the damned. And alſo, my Lord, the ſpeciall end of my writing vnto your Honour, is, ſo much as in me lieth, and as du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie binds me, to make you partaker of the fruit of my poore labor, with other my honourable and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:6245:4"/>friends. Nothing doubting but vnder that truth and plaineneſſe wherein I haue ſo faithfully ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured, and ſo heartily deſired the good alſo of ſo many thouſands as to whom it may come; your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſhall ſauour ſo much of ſome thing, as that you will ſay hereafter for your labor in reading of all, you are right glad, and haue therby loſt nothing. Thus briefly and moſt humbly I end, deſiring the Maieſtie of our eternall God, through the mediation of Ieſus Chriſt, to beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie and to adorne you and your honourable Lady with all ſpirituall graces, and that you both may ſee, (like your ſelues) according to your hearts deſire, your childrens children vnto the third and fourth generation. </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From Stretton Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field
<date>the 3. of Iuly, 1612.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt humble in the Lord, <hi>Edw. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aughan.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6245:4"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE LADY THE COVNTESSE of Leiceſter, Douger.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, I know none amongst all the women in the world, vpon my forty yeares reading, neither yet truly reported by any, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this book doth ſo properly appertaine to be carefully read, as to your ſelf. In reſpect ſpecially of Gods mercy wherin he hath made your honor admirably memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for your exceeding wiſedome and abounding graces: which was plainly ſeene in your patient abiding of one ſuch double deadly dayes newes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your noble ſon, &amp; your worthy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable
<pb facs="tcp:6245:5"/>husband, as made al England, France, and Ireland, more aſtoniſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that great inuincible Armado of Spaine, valorouſly floting vnder ſaile vpon our narrow ſeas. And there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo another famous reſpect of Gods mercie, and the kings Maiesties fauor vpon you, for that there is yet aliue a noble Earle of Eſſex, euen out of your owne loynes, who is like to repaire the ruines of his father, to raiſe his and your honourable houſe farre more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed, and lineally to leaue it ſo to be vpholden for euer. Madame, when the foundation of the Temple at Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem was newly laide, the ſound of the people for ioy could not be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the noiſe of the Priests,<note place="margin">Ezra 4.</note> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites, and Ancients for weeping: euen ſo right Honourable, your, and their most louing friends in that dolefull day, could not diſcerne whether the ioy for the Queenes maieſties ſafetie, or the ſorrow for their deceaſſe was the
<pb facs="tcp:6245:5"/>greatest. Although indeed ſome of both ſides, moſt vnconſiderately were partiall in their ioying, and other ſome exceeding in their ſorrowing; yet the maiestie of God did most di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinely and moſt duly traduce the one to temper the other in you, who had the greateſt cauſe of both. Labor you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore good honorable Lady ſo to abound in ioy for them, whoſe ſoules are in heauen, &amp; ſo to abound in ſorrow for your owne ſinnes, that whileſt you are aliue, it may not be diſcerned in which of both you exceed. And labour to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate your ſorrow for the father which is dead, becauſe his heroicall honour, and Christian magnanimitie is yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue in his ſonne. As for the maner of their death, it maketh nothing at all to the matter of their ſaluation, nor for the time of their diſſolution, as you may reade in this booke, by many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible ſentences and warrantable examples of Scripture particularly,
<pb facs="tcp:6245:6"/>after this maner: Firſt, that death hath his prerogatiue and priuiledge in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. Secondly, that death makes this world no world, and men to trade and trauell, to buy and ſell vpon all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties. Thirdly, that the decree concerning the time of death, is inuio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable and vnrepealable. And fourthly, how variable, and how ſundrie wayes death ſeizeth: vpon ſome with the ſtroke of an Angel, vpon ſome with the ſtroke of iustice, vpon ſome with the ſtroke of a friend, and that vnwitting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vnwillingly; vpon ſome with the ſtroke of an enemie, wittingly and willingly. Some godly men do kill and deſtroy themſelues, but vnwittingly and vnwillingly: and ſome vngodly men do kill and deſtroy themſelues wittingly and willingly, euen by their owne act and deed. And now to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, you know that honourable honor resteth not in the dignitie that men &amp; women haue, but in the good works
<pb facs="tcp:6245:6"/>whereby they deſerue: and you know as ſtigmaticall brands are tokens of former felonies, euen ſo procraſtinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> breadeth dangers. Apply your ſelfe therefore good honourable Lady vnto the conueniency of the time, for you know not when death will light on you by many yeares, nor the manner of it by many hundred wayes; that whenſoeuer and howſoeuer it fals, you may haue recourſe to the death of Ieſus Chriſt, to whoſe holy protection I leaue you, &amp;c. Newly from the Printers Preſſe, the <hi>3.</hi> Iuly, <hi>1612.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours moſt humble in the Lord</hi> Edw. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aughan.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6245:7"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVL SIR IOHN HARPER AND SIR PHILIP STANHOP in the countie of Darby Knights:</head>
            <head type="sub">And to the worſhipfull Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Richard Hall</hi> of London, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Humphrey Bonner</hi> of Nottingham, and Maiſter <hi>George Abney</hi> in the ſaid countie of Darby, Eſquiers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y ſingular ſelected frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, hauing publiſhed many and ſundry bookes of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity, and reſolutely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with my ſelf there to ſurceaſſe, knowing this to be the enuious and maligning age, in which few men ſhal be condignely rewarded, neither yet from vniuſt imputations, and impious calumniations freed: yet
<pb facs="tcp:6245:7"/>for all that I was occaſioned, or rather (as I may ſay) violently importuned for my owne better inſtruction and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, being more ſurpriſed with ſorrow then with the loſſe of all the kingdomes of the world, carefully to collect anſwers to diuers queſtions, and obiections which did aſſaile my ſoule, for and as concerning the deceaſſe of ſome ſuch as did moſt nearely concerne me, and exceeding dearely appertaine vnto me. And hauing therewithall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued through Gods mercie, that which of all other things I moſt ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally deſired; I was drawne dutifully and reſpectiuely to conſider that my caſe was, or might be yours, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon caſe of all men. Wherefore I tooke in hand methodically to diſpoſe of all thoſe diſperſed collections into this booke, as your Worſhips may ſee. Wherin I alledge nothing but true ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, &amp; examples of holy Scriptures, and that ſo warrantably, ſo briefely, and ſo plainely, as that I might not ſeeme tedious to the wiſe and learned, nor yet obſcure to the ſimple and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull
<pb facs="tcp:6245:8"/>hearted. Humbly and heartily deſiring you in liew of my labor, and in recompence of my loue, that you wil be pleaſed ſometimes to ſequeſter your ſelues from your publike affaires, yea and ſometimes from your moſt priuate occaſions, for the orderly and through reading thereof. Aſſuring you vpon my poore experience, and vpon the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the beſt learned writers, that there is nothing ſo effectuall in Gods word, except the graces of his holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to make a regenerate man to mourn in mirth, to ſolace in ſorrow, and to apprehend the right vſe of all the meanes, which God hath ordayned for the preſeruation of life, vntill the time of death doth come; as the meditation of mortality, with Scripture anſwers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templatiuely to euery ſuch queſtion and obiection, as may be raiſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning death: together with deuout prayers going before, and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing following after. Or otherwiſe a thouſand to one, death brings with it feare, feare brings an increaſe of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall torments, an increaſe of torments,
<pb facs="tcp:6245:8"/>brings diſtraction of memorie. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards followeth all idle, diſſolute and damnable ſpeech, and ſo from one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect vnto another, an obliuio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt and his kingdome, as the diuell would haue it. Thus I end, hauing timely inough I hope forewarnd you, with my hearty deſires vnto his holy Maieſtie, to comfot you in your affliction and tribulation, that you may be able and readie to comfort others, to the glory of his holy name, and the euerlaſting comfort of your owne ſoules. </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From Stretton Lefield in the countie of Darbie,
<date>this 3. of Iuly 1612.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord <hi>Edw. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aughan.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:6245:9"/>
            <head>The contents.</head>
            <p>In the displaying of this diuine diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of death, is neceſſarily to be obſerued theſe foure generall heads of inſtruction, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by many ſentences and holy exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Scriptures. viz.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>Generalitie</hi> of death, to wit, how inuincibly death reigneth ouer all the generation of mankind, no place exempted, no time priuiledged, nor any perſon vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny occaſion fauoured.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the ſundrie <hi>ſorts, maners,</hi> and <hi>kinds</hi> of death, that is to ſay, how diuerſly and how many wayes death ſeizeth vpon all people, with the ſeuerall reaſons thereof.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the <hi>timelineſſe</hi> of death, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by particulars, the day, the houre, the moment and point of time, in which almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God hath decreed that euerie the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of mankinde ſhall die, ſo that no man by the diligent vſe of the meanes can leng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then his life, nor any man by the negligent vſe of the meanes ſhall ſhorten his life.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the <hi>memorabilitie</hi> of death, that is to ſay the commemoration and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſolemnization which the liuing ought to haue for their dead, with foure principall and Chriſtian respects.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6245:9"/>
            <head>THE GENERA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LITIE OF DEATH.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eath hath dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all mankind, not all together as they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable, but one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another in their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time. To which purpoſe, the iuſt man Iob by the holy influence of Gods diuine Spirit, ſaid, not onely of himſelfe, but alſo of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:<note place="margin">Iob. 30.23.24.</note> Surely I know that thou wilt bring me to death, and to the houſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for all the liuing. Salomon the wiſeſt man then in all the world, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing duly conſidered of mans abode in this life, ſaid:<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 6, 6.</note> Man ſhall be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with darkeneſſe, if he liue an hundred yeares twiſe told; and ſhall not all go into one place? Saint Luke ſpeaking by the ſame ſpirit, ſets downe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6245:10"/>the diuine ſpeech of Saint Paul to the Athenians, among which he doth plainely relate the maner of mans crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this wiſe:<note place="margin">Act. 17.26.</note> God hath made of one bloud all mankind to dwell on the face of the earth. As if he had ſaid, by a vulgar phraſe of ſpeech, Where there is a contagion or an infection, it goes through that familie, becauſe they are of one nature, and of one bloud: euen ſo he meant that all the generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, being of one bloud and of one fleſh, ſhall all taſte of one death. Saint Paul in his exhortation to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians for their enduring affliction, and to liue well,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10.</note> ſaid, We muſt all appeare before the iudgement ſeate of Chriſt: as if he had ſaid, There is no helpe nor hope, we muſt all die. Ioſua a man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding victorious, and full of magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitie and Chriſtian courage, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prepared to die, in his exhortation to his people, points vnto himſelfe, ſaying,<note place="margin">Ioſua. 23.14</note> Behold I enter into the way of all the world: as if he had ſaid, Maruell not my brethren at me, who muſt needs depart this life, the like muſt be your
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6245:10"/>lots &amp; your poſterity. The wiſe woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Tekoha amongſt many other emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ſpeeches which ſhe vſed to Dauid the king, in the behalfe of Abſolon his ſonne; ſaid vnto him, We muſt all die,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 14.14.</note> and we are as water ſpilt on the earth, which cannot be gathered: neither doth God ſpare any perſon. As Dauid ſaid,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 11.25.</note> The ſword deuoures as wel one as another: euen ſo it may be ſaid of all people, that death ſeizeth one manner or other vpon euerie man without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. Furthermore,<note place="margin">Gen. 5.28.</note> the ten holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who liued euery man almoſt his thouſand yet died.<note place="margin">Deut. 2.3. Ioſua. 8.9.10.11.12.</note> We may ſpeake of diuers by examples, as of Moſes &amp; Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua the moſt valiant &amp; moſt victorious warriours that euer were;<note place="margin">Iud. 16.28.29.</note> of Sampſon the <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> man in all the world, and yet they died.<note place="margin">1. King. 11.43. Dan. 4.</note> Of Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who was the wiſeſt man in all the world, and yet he died. Nabucadnezzar was the richeſt man in all the world, and yet he died. Peter and Paul were as <hi>holy</hi> as euer any before or ſince, and yet Peter and Paul died.<note place="margin">Gen. 23.1.2. Heſt. 9.</note> Sarah and Heſter were two <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful</hi> Ladies as euer were, and yet Sarah
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6245:11"/>and Heſter died. To conclude, there was neuer any time, nor place, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that could exempt any man from death. For Sem called Melchizedech was before the flood: he out liued all that knew him;<note place="margin">Gen. 14.14. Heb. 7.1. to 7.</note> and ſo long, that no man knew his kindred: euen when Lot was taken priſoner, and a great grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father of eight degrees in Abrahams time: whence he was ſaid to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out father and without mother, and in part a figure of Chriſt, whoſe Godhead had no mother, and whoſe manhood had no father: without beginning of dayes, or end of life: in reſpect of whom alſo he was ſaid to be king of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, king of peace, and a Prieſt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of the moſt high God; yet for all this Melchizedech died. Iob ſaid, If God ſet his heart vpon man,<note place="margin">Iob. 34.14.</note> and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his ſpirit vnto himſelfe, then man ſhall returne to duſt. As though he had ſaid more plainly; No man in all the world that liueth, but liueth to die whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God will; becauſe mans life conſiſteth of that which is Gods. Salomon ſaith, The deſire of death cannot be ſatisfied,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.8.</note>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:6245:11"/>he gathereth vnto himſelfe all nations, &amp; doth heape vnto himſelfe all people.<note place="margin">Hab. 2.5.</note> Iob ſpeaking to this purpoſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all mankind, and more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of himſelfe, ſaid thus;<note place="margin">Iob. 6.11.</note> What power haue I that I ſhould endure? is my ſtrength the ſtrength of ſtones? or is my fleſh of braſſe? To wit, What did men thinke of me when I was at the beſt? or what could I euer thinke of my ſelfe? was I a man like to liue alwayes? And what man may be named that now is, that euer was, or euer ſhall be ſo ſtrong or ſo enduring, as that he ſhall be able to ſurcharge death? The ſundrie exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and the common experience euen of our owne time hath told vs and doth ſtill forewarne vs of death, which is ſo due to vs, as to them who are gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. The moſt vnlikelieſt do longeſt liue, &amp; the moſt likelieſt do ſooneſt die; which argueth plainly, that there is no ſtability, no certainty nor true token of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance in any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whatſoeuer. Alſo S. Paul ſaid to the Corinthians,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.51.</note> we ſhal not all die. Indeed we ſhall all once die inreſpect of our outward eſtate, ourele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6245:12"/>inclination, and naturall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: but in reſpect of Gods diuine maieſtie, innarrable power, and ſecret will, they which ſhall liue at the laſt day ſhall be changed, they ſhall not be the ſame which formerly they were as men in the world.</p>
            <p>I haue aduiſedly conſidered of ten ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly motiues, or diuine reaſons of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, why all men muſt die.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt reaſon why all men muſt die,</head>
               <p>It is the decree of almightie God, which ordereth all inferior cauſes, and binds the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the obedience of his will. No king can produce ſo ancient a right to his crowne, as euerie man hath out of this moſt ancient decree to chale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge after death the crowne of glorie. Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſaid,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.14.</note> I know that whatſoeuer God hath done, he hath done it for euer: to it can no man adde, and from it can no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diminiſh. Eſai the Prophet, as in the proper perſon of God himſelfe, ſaith, The Lord hath ſworne ſaying,<note place="margin">Eſa. 14.24.</note> ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as I haue purpoſed ſo ſhall it come to paſſe, and as I haue conſulted ſo ſhall it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6245:12"/>ſtand. Againe he ſaith, Seeke ye the booke of the Lord, and reade; none of theſe things ſhal faile, none ſhall want, his mouth hath commanded it.<note place="margin">Mal. 3.6.</note> Malachi ſaid to that purpoſe, I am the Lord that changeth not. The Author to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes ſaith,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.17.18.</note> That God more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly to ſhew the ſtableneſſe of his counſell, bound himſelfe by an oath, wherin it is impoſſible that God ſhould lie; that we might haue ſtrong conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Dan. 6.8.</note> As the lawes of the Medes &amp; Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were vnrepealable: ſo is the decree of almighty God concerning death vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repealable, and in regard of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingnes of it, Ieremy ſaid,<note place="margin">Ier. 17.1.</note> It is written with an iron pen, and with the point of a diamond, and grauen vpon the tables of the heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond reaſon why all men muſt die,</head>
               <p>Is drawne from the vprightneſſe of Gods iuſtice. Sinne being ſo generall in all men, his Maieſtie hath decreed to puniſh it by death in all men, yea in his owne deare children; who although the guilt of ſinne be remoued and taken
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6245:13"/>from them, yet ſinne remaining in their mortall bodies is to be puniſhed with death, and periſhing of that ſubſtance ſo ſubiect to ſinne. Saint Paul ſaid, Death went ouer all men,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> in as much as all men haue ſinned. As by the law eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie husband may put away his wife for alienating her body to another man: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo ſinne by the law doth alienate &amp; put away the ſoule from the body of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueric man.<note place="margin">Iob. 34.11.</note> Elihu ſpake moſt diuinely to this purpoſe, with his friends: God will render vnto man according to his work and cauſe euery man to find according to his way. And as ſinne increaſed from age to age, ſo did the anger of God, as appeared by the ſhortning of their dayes. Though Chriſt hath forgiuen vs, yet ſinne is not out of vs. There is ſtil in man that will keep him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoaring: and a <hi>Quis me</hi> in his mouth, extending la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentably with Saint Paul, from men to Angels, with a violent interrogation enforcing an anſwer, who ſhall deliuer me from the bodie of death?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:6245:13"/>
               <head>The third reaſon why all men muſt die.</head>
               <p>All men muſt die in reſpect of Gods generall purpoſe for the changing and renewing of mankind from one ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance into another, for the tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiating of one body into another, &amp; a tranſmitting of one life into another. This purpoſe of the Father in Chriſt Ieſus, made Iob to ſay,<note place="margin">Iob. 14.14.</note> I wil waite mine appointed time till my changing come. S. Paul relating the verie ſame amongſt many other things of great weight vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Corinthians, ſaid, We ſhal all be changed. And in another place,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, Fleſh &amp; bloud, ſaith he,<note place="margin">35 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.</note> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not inherite the kingdome of heauen: mortality muſt be ſwallowed vp of life.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.4.</note> And in his epiſtle to the Philippians he writes the ſame in effect, being occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned otherwiſe thereunto, and that in theſe words. God ſhall change our vile bodies,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.21.</note> that they may be like vnto his glorious bodie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:6245:14"/>
               <head>The fourth reaſon why all men muſt die is,</head>
               <p>That there may be a performance and a ſeiſure vpon Gods promiſes for the perpetuall good of his Saints after death, which in this life can not be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, and alſo for the ineuitable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the wicked. With the godly,<note place="margin">Eſai. 23.18.</note> ſaith Eſai, ſhall be ioy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſlaying of oxen, kiling of ſheep, eating fleſh, and drinking wine, reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and triumphing. By which words is meant all ſpiritual &amp; heauenly plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of immortal melodies, and vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able alacrities; the father ioying and reioycing in the ſonne, and the ſonne in the father, and both the father and the ſonne in other the Saints, in the Angels, and ſpecially in the Lambe Chriſt Ieſus. The ſame Prophet conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth his ſpeech, as being halfe raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the meditation thereof, in the behalfe of his fellow brethren, who ſaith, Awake thou that ſleepeſt in the duſt;<note place="margin">Eſai 25.9.</note> in that day men ſhall ſay, Lo, this is our God, we haue waited for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6245:14"/>him, he will ſaue vs, we will reioyce and be ioyfull in his ſaluation. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the Lord himſelfe ſpeakes by the ſame Prophet,<note place="margin">Eſa. 26.19.</note> The dead men ſhall liue euer; with my body ſhall they ariſe: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake and ſing ye that dwell in the duſt. Saint Paul ſaid to that effect,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.10.</note> We muſt all appeare before the iudgment ſeate of Chriſt, that euerie man may receiue the things which he hath done in his body. As it was with Chriſt the head, ſo is it with his members: Except the wheate corne die, and fall into the ground, it abideth alone, but if it die, it bringeth much fruite.</p>
               <p>Concerning the ſeiſure of Gods iudgments vpon the wicked according to Gods promiſes, theſe ioyes, theſe preparations, and theſe exultations, are turned vnto weeping and gnaſhing of teeth: Then ſaith Eſai,<note place="margin">Eſa. 23.9.</note> that the noiſe of them that reioyce, endeth, intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the wicked: then their mirth ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, they ſhall not eat and drinke with mirth,<note place="margin">24.8.26.21.</note> and good things ſhall be bitter vnto them, Lo, then the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth out of his place, to viſite the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6245:15"/>of the earth. The earth ſhall diſcloſe her bloud, and ſhall no more hide her ſlaine. Then the Lord hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed to ſtaine the pride of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s glorie, and to bring into contempt all them that be glorious vpon earth. Here the glorie of the wicked endeth, and euen here the glorie of the godly begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth: as by the example of Diues, and Lazarus. And as Abimelech hauing fought againſt the city Sechem fiercely, and exceedingly wrathfull, he ſlue all the people that were therein, left none aliue; and afterwards in ſigne that it ſhould neuer be inhabited, he ſowed ſalt in it: euen ſo is the Lord in his wrath againſt the wicked of the world at that day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fifth reaſon why all men muſt die.</head>
               <p>It is drawne from the matter or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance whereof man was made, to wit, of earth, and therefore ſubiect to peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing: earth cannot continue long out of its ſpheare whence it was exhauſted. Earth how cunningly, and how curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6245:15"/>ſoeuer it be built, (as earth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth,) it will deſcend and preſſe downward according to the nature thereof, vnto the place whence it came, and by little and little, in ſhort time much wil come to nothing. According to the which God ſaid vnto Adam, Thou art duſt,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note> and into duſt thou ſhalt returne. Man is built vpon a bad foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,<note place="margin">Iob. 4.19.</note> therfore Iob ſaid that the ſoules which came from heauen do dwell in houſes of clay, and their foundation is in the duſt, which ſhall be deſtroyd before the moath.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.20.</note> And Salomon ſaid that the ſpirit ſhall returne to God that gaue it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſixth reaſon why all men muſt die.</head>
               <p>It is drawne from the matter or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance whereof the woman was made, or for her immediate conuerſion from one ſubſtance to another, to wit, from earth to fleſh; which being rightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in it ſelfe, is a matter or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance leſſe durable, and more momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanie then the former. For fleſh how
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6245:16"/>fine ſoeuer it be in it ſelfe, and how cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, or coſtly ſo euer it be preſerued: yet if it be not vſed, and taken in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, it will putrifie and become excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding noiſome of it ſelfe, ſpecially the fleſh of a woman: for by how much more excellent, braue, &amp; beautifull ſhe is in the conſtitution of her body then the man, by ſo much the more foule, fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, &amp; ſtinking, her body will become ſhortly after ſhe is diſſolued; following therein, the nature of other pure and purified creatures, which in their time, and right vſe are much to the prayſe of God, and to the comfort of man, but being abuſed, or not vſed as they ought, are the moſt vile, and the moſt venimous things of all others. The fleſh of beaſts, are good for men, and the fleſh of men, good for ſomething, but the fleſh of women when they are dead is good for nothing. Iob there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being borne of a woman, ſaid of him ſelfe, &amp; of all others of that kinde, My fleſh is meate for wormes,<note place="margin">Job 7.5.</note> my fleſh is clothed with wormes and filthineſſe. Man both by father &amp; mother, is a ſtig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6245:16"/>note, a word of diſdaine, or an appellation of anger: therefore Dauid ſaith, What is man, that thou art mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of him? Ye are all but men, the ſons of men. S. Paul ſaid, O wretched man, not, ô wretched Apoſtle, nor, ô wretched Chriſtian, but, ô wretched man; the cauſe of his wretchedneſſe was in him ſelfe, a man miſerable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſeuenth reaſon why all men muſt die.</head>
               <p>It is drawne from the vigour and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rility of mans nature, which being growne vnto the height, declineth, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, and falleth. It weareth, &amp; waneth like the Moone, and like Nabucadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars image,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.31.32.33.</note> which being raiſed from the earth to iron, from iron to braſſe, from braſſe to ſiluer, and from ſiluer to gold, the head and higheſt perfection; then it declined, it returned, and abated from gold to ſiluer, from ſiluer to braſſe, from braſſe to iron, and from iron to earth, euen to that indeede whence firſt it came. When nature is quite
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6245:17"/>decayed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body extinguiſheth, as in the example of that renowned man Dauid,<note place="margin">1 King. 1.1.2.</note> King of gods peculiar people: he was ſo old that he died, when nature was quite worne out of him. This is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo variably to be proued, euen by the nature of naturall things, which hauing their licour, moiſture or iuice dried and worne away, do decay and periſh pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently. To which purpoſe God ſaid by the mouth of the Prophet Eſai, in part touching the deſolation of Iſrael: They ſhall be as an oake,<note place="margin">Eſai. 7.30.</note> whoſe leafe falleth, and as a garden without water. So likewiſe ſaith Iob interrogatiuely, Can a ruſh grow without dirt,<note place="margin">Iob. 8.11.</note> or can graſſe grow without water? As if he had ſaid, Take dirt &amp; water away, then neither the ruſh nor the graſſe but will preſently wither, and come to nothing. Saint Peter likens mankind to the flower of the field,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.24.</note> and to graſſe which being growne to the full height &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turitie, which the licour &amp; iuice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of could poſſibly extend, then preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it returnes, and in very little time is withered, and cleane gone. Salomon li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6245:17"/>man, for his growing and decrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, vnto Lillies and roſes.<note place="margin">Cant. 2.1.</note> As an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chymiſt, hauing viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly exhauſted the ſpirits, and by little and little diſtilled the quinteſſences of minerals, and met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, they are thenceforth good for litle or nothing, but as ſalt hauing left the ſaltneſſe; eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo man hauing his natural vigour, by little, and little, taken or worne away, is but a dead carcaſſe, good for nothing but for to be hid in the earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The eight reaſon why all men muſt die,</head>
               <p>It is drawne from the decree of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God for the diſſolution of the world, and a finall end of all things, a throwing together, and as it were a folding vp of many things into one thing. Eſai ſaid concerning this diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, thus,<note place="margin">Eſai 13.9.</note> The day of the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, cruell with wrath and fierce an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, to lay the land waſte,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.29.</note> the ſtarres ſhall fall from heauen, and the planets ſhall not giue their light, the Sun ſhall be darkned in his going forth, and the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6245:18"/>Moone ſhall not giue her light. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Ezechiel ſaith, O how fearefull, and how terrible that day ſhall be to them which pierced him through! yet then whoſoeuer ſhall call on the name of the Lord ſhall be ſaued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ninth reaſon why all men muſt die.</head>
               <p>It is that there may be a generall victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ouer death and hell. For ſo ſaith S. Paul,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.26.</note> The laſt enemie that ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyd is death. God ſpeakes to that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect by the mouth of his Prophet, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death in the behalfe of the godly: O death,<note place="margin">Hoſe. 13.14.</note> I will be thy death. As though he had ſaid triumphantly, thou that haſt bene the death of all mankind, ô cruell enemie, ô thou vnſatiable deuourer, now I will be thy death, now ſhalt thou be deſtroyed for euer; now thy ſting, and thy ſtrength, ſhall vtterly be taken away.<note place="margin">5.8.6.</note> Againe the ſame Prophet ſaith, he will deſtroy death for euer, and God will wipe all teares and heauineſſe, from all faces;<note place="margin">Luk. 20.36</note> and S. Luke ſaith, they can die no more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:6245:18"/>
               <head>The tenth reaſon why all men muſt die,</head>
               <p>Hath foure ſpeciall reſpects or diuine attributes.</p>
               <p>The firſt whereof is drawne from the celeſtiall kingdome whence our ſoules came, and the terreſtriall taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles and houſes of clay, wherein our ſoules do a while liue or dwell, as ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and ſoiourners. Men are ſaid to be ſtrangers either in reſpect of their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell from one place vnto another, or in reſpect of ſome kingdome where they dwell, being borne elſewhere, not yet free denized nor naturalized. In both which reſpects Dauid ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſa. 39.12. 1 Chro. 19.15. 1 Cor. 5.1.2.</note> that as our fathers were in this world ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, &amp; ſoiourners, ſo Saint Paul to the like purpoſe ſaith, We know that we haue a building giuen vs of God, that is, an houſe not made with hands, but eternall in heauen: as if he had ſaid, our certaine and moſt reſting place is not here on earth, but is in heauen. As he that is in a voyage or iourney neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenteth himſelfe vntill he be at home, and therefore toiles and trauels with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6245:19"/>great carneſtneſſe to end his buſineſſe, that he may returne: euen ſo are we in this tabernacle,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.2.</note> as Saint Paul ſaid, ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and deſiring to be clothed with our houſe, which is from heauen. The faithfull did manifeſtly confeſſe, that they were ſtrangers and pilgrimes on earth,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.13.</note> and that they deſired an heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly countrie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond respect or attribute giuen to the children of God, is</head>
               <p>Drawne from the meere merits of Chriſt, by whom alſo our bodies and ſoules haue intereſt and title to the kingdome of heauen, &amp; that in a more particular and proper manner then in this world, as thus appeareth. Chriſt is called our bridegroome, and we his bride,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.6. Cant. 4.12. Ephe. 1.22. Coll. 1.18.</note> inferring by a neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that where the husband is there muſt be the wife. Againe, where Chriſt is called the head of the Church, it is to be inferred neceſſarily, that where the head is gone before, the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers muſt and ſhall follow after: much like to that which Chriſt ſaid, Wherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the body is,<note place="margin">Luk. 17.37.</note> thither will the Eagles
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6245:19"/>reſort. As an honeſt wife hath alwaies an vnſatiable deſire and longing to be with her husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, no way co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented with his abſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, no not with loue letters, nor with meſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, nor with toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of great price, but with his corporall preſence: euen ſo the true me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of Chriſt, being zelouſly affected &amp; faithfully diſpoſed towards her holy &amp; heauenly husband Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">Cant. 1.1.</note> ſaith, Let him kiſſe me with the kiſſes of his mouth. As if the Church or bride of Chriſt had ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God his and her heauenly father: O let me haue the fruition of his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preſence, let me be alway with him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third respect or attribute giuen vnto the children of God, is</head>
               <p>Drawne from the mortall hatred &amp; malice which the deuill hath againſt vs, exceedingly enuying our ſpirituall, and glorious arriuall into heauen, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore layes many ſnares and infinite al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements, to let &amp; hinder vs from our paſſage; with whome therefore accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will of God, we muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, vnder the conduct of our
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6245:20"/>Lord Generall Chriſt Ieſus. In reſpect of which ſtriuings,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.10. to 18. 2. Timo. 2.3. Phile. 1.2.</note> conflicts and bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telles, we are called ſouldiers and warriors: inferring thereby that when we haue valiantly fought the Lords battels, and faithfully triumphed ouer the diuell, then it followes that we ſhall returne to our owne home with rewards and crownes of euerlaſting glotie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth reſpect or attribute giuen vnto the children of God, is</head>
               <p>Drawne from the affaires wherin God our eternall king hath imployed vs for the performance of certaine religious duties, whereof ſome are pertayning to God, ſome to our brethren, and ſome to our ſelues: the which being done, and duely accompliſhed, then muſt we be gone. In regard whereof, we are called Legates, Ambaſſadors and ſuch like, ſometimes labourers, ſometimes pilgrimes. And in our commiſſion we haue euery man his ſet and limited time of diſpatch,<note place="margin">Iob. 7.1. 1 Pet. 2.1.</note> which being ended, the ancient of dayes, the Angell of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6245:20"/>the couenant will ſend his Angell Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briel, or ſome other,<note place="margin">Dan 9.20.21.22.</note> ſaying vnto vs for our returne vnto heauen, as vnto the people of Iſrael in Babylon, for their returne vnto Ieruſalem</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now me thinkes I heare two obiections made againſt me by two ſorts of people:</head>
               <p>The one ſaying, This doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the generality of death, needed not; it might haue bene ſpared, and the ſpeech ſpent vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> matter that we know not. For by the vſe of reaſon, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon experience, and by manifold ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, men are induced to beleeue all this that you haue ſaid to be true, and long ſince generally allowed. This is now a harſh kind of doctrine to wiſe men, and it is very diſtaſtfull to all men; for it is a melancholy kind of teaching, and of no ſuch neceſſity. Ye might ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in ſteed thereof ſtirre vp men to be merrie, and to endure their miſeries patiently. Preachers do nothing more then fright and aſtoniſh men: in the name of God let vs be merrie whiles we may, ſorrow comes faſt inough.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:6245:21"/>
               <p>The other ſort reaſoning, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulating with fleſh and bloud, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not determine vpon the generality of death. They ſee not, they ſay, how it may be, nor how it can ſtand to be true, becauſe then it is queſtionable, ſay they, who ſhall haue the dominion ouer other creatures in the world, which are innumerable, and moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.1. 1.3.4.</note> Saint Peter ſaith, theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue not that the world ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed with fire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An anſwer to the firſt concerning the generalitie of death.</head>
               <p>Interrogatiuely, do you know this to be true by any ſentence or exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of holy Scripture? No, no, you do not. For if you did ſo know it, the hearing of the ſame againe and againe, would rather haue bene comfortable the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tedious vnto you. That knowledge which is not grounded vpon the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of truth is nought worth, &amp; meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnperfect. True it is, that men may know and be induced to beleeue, that they which are a dying, will die; and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6245:21"/>that they which are in eminent dangers and perils preſent, ſhall die. But truly to beleeue, and certainly to know that all men ſhall die, or who, or how many ſhall die, fleſh and bloud cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale vnto men. For the ſenſe of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and ſeeing, by the which men are brought to know and to beleeue, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth no further then vnto things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; becauſe light, which is the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of ſeeing, and the aire which is the obiect of hearing, vpon diuers oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions are ſometimes giuen, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times taken away. Therefore to ſee and to know certainly, as an article of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, that all men ſhall die, which is my generall doctrine, no man can appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend nor yet comprehend, but by the knowledge of the holy Scriptures, and by the holy influence of Gods diuine ſpirit; becauſe in verie truth, the ſame reacheth vnto the apprehenſion of things in time to come, and vnto that which is cleane out of ſight and out of hearing. Saint Paul ſpeaketh directly of two ſorts of ſeeing,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.18.</note> the one proper to the ſpirituall eyes, or eyes of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6245:22"/>in theſe words: We looke not on the things which are ſeene, but on the things which are not ſeene. As if he had ſaid, We who are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, do not eſteeme of that which we may apprehend with our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural eyes, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon: but we eſteeme and allow, ſpecially, of that which we may comprehend and apprehend by faith. And in that verie place he verifies the ſame, calling the one, in a ſort, an obiect temporall; the other an obiect eternall. The ſame Apoſtle ſaith to the like purpoſe: We walke not by ſight, but by faith:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.7.</note> to wit, We iudge not ſo highly, nor ſo truly of that which the light or the aire doth manifeſt vnto our ſenſes, as of thoſe things which the word of faith doth manifeſt vnto our ſoules. The effects and fruites of the one and the other ſhewes the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. As the vertue attractiue was not in Noahs Arke,<note place="margin">Gen. 7.7.9.10.</note> that drew famous and moſt worthy creatures and of all ſorts into it; nor the vertue attractiue was not in Elias cloke that drew Eliſha fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his plowing,<note place="margin">1. King. 19.19.</note> but both in the effectuall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6245:22"/>vſe of Gods word. Euen ſo the vertue of hearing, ſeeing, and beleeuing the general doctrine of death and life, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth not from any matter in nature, nor from worldly reaſon, nor yet from the wiſeſt humane narration, but from the holy Spirit of the liuing God, who worketh in vs by faith, which is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the written word of God. As for example briefly;<note place="margin">2. King 6.18.19.</note> Eliſha his man, as he was a naturall man, ſaw onely an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of the Aramites who were come to take his maiſter: but when the eyes of his vnderſtanding were opened vpon the prayers of his maiſter, he ſaw a farre greater army of Angels that were come to protect them. This made S. Paule to pray,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.</note> That the eies of the Epheſians vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding might be opened: which was in effect, that God would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to inflame &amp; to kindle their hearts and their affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with the ſplendor of his word and Spirit. As the ſame hoſt of the Aramites was led with blindneſſe,<note place="margin">1. King. 6.18.19.</note> vnto their mortall enemie the king of Iſrael, at Samaria, the eyes of their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding being ſhut vp: and as the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6245:23"/>Sodomites did ſtrike at Lots doore with blindneſſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.10.11.</note> when their naturall eyes were open; or as Saule and his company,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 26.12.</note> being in the iuſtice of God, ſtriken into a dead ſleepe: euen ſo all ſuch as haue not their ſight, and their knowledge for ſpirituall things out of Scripture, they weare out themſelues with weariſomneſſe, and in the end do bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, as through ignorance, into that ineuitable gulfe of perdition. Labour you therefore, ye ſeruants of the Lord, labour ye the Scriptures, and know you for certaine, that ye know nothing as ye ought to know, vnleſſe ye know it by the Scriptures, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it by the ſame Spirit that wrote the Scriptures. As the light of the body is the eye,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.34.</note> ſo the light of the inner man is the word of God; and conſider I pray you, conſider in due time I aduiſe you. If I be to be blamed for this long diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concerning the generalitie of death, why then did the holy Ghoſt ſo largely diſcourſe thereof? Why did his holy Maieſtie ſo often particulate one and the ſame matter, ſo variably and in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6245:23"/>ſo many places of Scripture? How can this be anſwered? If you ſay, fewer pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces would haue ſuffiſed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you do di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly blaſpheme; which God forbid. Then you charge the holy Ghoſt with ſuperfluities and tediouſneſſe, where as through Gods mercies, with ſuch, and ſo many iterations he doth importune you to remember your mortalitie and to make prouiſion for the ſame accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. If you ſay this doctrine was not ſo needfull, becauſe you knew it long ſince; out of your owne words you proue this doctrine, of all others, to be moſt needfull, and my ſelfe of you moſt carefull. And whereas you know alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, as you ſay, that you ſhall die: neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, it is queſtionable, whether you be readie prepared to die euerie houre for the teſtimonie of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as his Maieſtie hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, yea or no. And it is queſtionable, whether you be willing and deſirous to die. You wil ſay peraduenture, you are of that mind, &amp; you truſt euer to be ſo, that there is nothing vainly ſpoken in Gods word: and you will count them
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6245:24"/>vaine and friuolous that ſhall ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing out of this word, that doth not in ſome ſort humour and applaud you. Here I end this matter, deſiring God to enlarge your affections more &amp; more vnto the obedience of his word.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An anſwer to the <hi>2.</hi> obiection concerning the generalitie of death.</head>
               <p>Herein I will be briefe, becauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, this ſort of people are leſſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of further inſtruction, who hold that this ſo goodly a frame of the world, ſhould not, or cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. Of whom Saint Peter ſpeaketh thus:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.3.</note> There ſhall come in the laſt dayes mockers who will walke after their owne luſts, and ſhall ſay, Where is the promiſe of his coming for ſince the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers died, all things continue alike vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this day. There needeth no other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for them then that which S. Peter maketh them in the verſes following, let them looke to it vpon their perill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:6245:24"/>
               <head>This doctrine concerning the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of death, ſerueth to reproue three ſorts of people.</head>
               <p>The firſt are thoſe who wholly, or for the moſt part, do ſet their loue and liking vpon the things of this world, as if they were to tarrie in it for euer: or as if they were to chuſe, they would not change this world, no not for the kingdome of heauen; ioying and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing, as Amos the Prophet ſaid,<note place="margin">Amos. 6.13.</note> in a thing of nought: &amp; like vnto the tribes of Ruben and Gad, and halfe the tribe of Manaſſes,<note place="margin">Num. 32.1.2.</note> who choſe the towns and lands on this ſide Iordan, becauſe there were goodly habitations, and fertile ſoyle, rather then the townes and lands in Canaan, which for the fertilitie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, was ſaid to flow with milke and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: and for the innumerable pleaſures thereof, like vnto the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Saint Paul blaming ſuch, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to draw them vnto better choiſe, exhorteth, ſaying: Seeke ye the things which are aboue,<note place="margin">Col. 3.1.</note> where Chriſt ſits at the right hand of God, and ſet your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6245:25"/>on heauenly things and not on earthly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſecond ſort who are to be reproued by the generall doctrine of death,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Are they who murmure much, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do mourne too much for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſſe of their neare friends, as though God had not done well to take one, and not another, to take this and not that: or as if death had ſurpriſed them before their time, and for euer; or elſe that death had caſually lighted on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more then others. Saint Paule comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelfe and others concerning this complaint,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.1.</note> ſayd: We haue a buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding giuen of God, that is, an houſe whoſe builder and maker is God. The children of God die but one:<note place="margin">Luk. 20.36.</note> they taſte not of that ſecond death in hell, as the reprobates do. This once to die, is but a ſhort interiection betweene two eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, to wit, election and glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with a kingly and a kindly paſſage as it were, by calling and iuſtification vnto eternall ſaluation.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.9.</note> Chriſt died once, but in that he liueth, he liueth for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6245:25"/>euer. So ye likewiſe, ſaith the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, are dead to ſinne,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.9.</note> but aliue to God through Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The third ſort who are to be reproued by this generall doctrine of death,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Are thoſe, who not minding their mortalitie, nor accompts which they muſt make, do treaſure vp ſinne vpon ſinne, being driuen, as it were, with the ſwinge of their nature, &amp; ſet on fire of hell, defile their bodies, and the whole courſe of nature: reſolued with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to vndergo any ſinne, ſo as it may bring them either pleaſure or profite. Alwayes ſaying in their hearts, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times with their tongues, If we muſt die for ſinne, as Preachers ſay, and that as well for one ſinne as for a thouſand; why then let vs eate and drinke, and be merrie while we may. Salomon out of his owne experience, and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally from the holy Spirit of inſpiration, faith of ſuch one a after this maner:<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.9.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce ô thou yong man in thy youth,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6245:26"/>let thine heart cheare thee, walke in the wayes of thine owne heart, and in the ſight of thine eyes. But what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth? God will bring thee to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Although his Maieſtie be incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to mercie, yet when he is moued to iuſtice, it is ineuitable, it is innarrable, &amp; it is intollerable. To that effect ſaid Dauid, as if it were in the proper per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of almightie God, vnto all ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate and graceleſſe wretches, that do abuſe his holy patience:<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.17.</note> I will ſet thy ſinnes in order: to wit, thy ſins in the night, thy ſinnes in the day, thy ſins in thy youth, and thy ſins in thine age, thy ſins againſt me, and thy ſinnes againſt thy brethren. I will ſo muſter and ſo ranke them together, &amp; ſo place them by rowes, and in euerie ranke and row, ſuch, and ſo many, as ſhall ſeeme to be more odious, ſhamefull, and deteſtable euen vnto thine owne ſelfe. And what ſhall follow? I will teare thee in peeces, that is, thy torments ſhall be more ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, and farre more horrible to nature then as if thou wert racked &amp; tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted peece-meale. Theſe are they who
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6245:26"/>although in deed ſinne is too too ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, yet they rifle, and runne raging<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after it, in a more particular manner, not minding their mortalitie, or at leaſt, not regarding the accompts that they muſt make; do maligne, enuie, vtterly hate, yea and ſeeke the whole ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of vs the Preachers of his holy word, and others the deare children of God, who runne not into the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of riot and damnable behauiour: but with zeale do frequent the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his word, with reuerence do keepe his Sabbaths, &amp; with all care do keepe themſelues vnſported of the world. Therefore they eſteeme them not worth their ſocietie, nor worthie to liue vpon the earth.<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.19.</note> We are not of the world, therfore the world hatethvs, ſaith S. Iohn. The manifold plagues to the Egyptians, the fierie Serpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to the Iſraelites, and the Emerods to the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims, were not ſo troubleſome and tedious, as theſe heatheniſh Atheiſts, &amp; prophane Iewes are to vs. We liue not as enemies in an hoſtile manner among them, but modeſtly, and mildly, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6245:27"/>benignly, as Chriſtian co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forters, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging peace, &amp; offering reconciliation. The words of our commiſſion are of 3. emphaticall and publicke narrations. The firſt is, <hi>Benedicite,</hi> bleſſe ye; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is, <hi>Benefacite,</hi> do ye good; and the third is, <hi>Orate,</hi> pray ye. Thus are we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned to behaue our ſelues, amongſt many other religious duties, towards God and good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea &amp; towards our enemies. Where in ſo euer we do faile through frailtie, it is not indifferent, nor iuſtice for them, being our enemies to iudge what we ſhould do, but rather out of charity to iudge what we would do. Neither is it for them to reuenge themſelues vpon vs, it is his holy Maic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to whom we muſt anſwer vpon our accompt. We are (whatſoeuer they ſay) bringers of peace, and we are peaceable.<note place="margin">2. King. 10.17.</note> Come &amp; ſee, ſaid Iehu to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honadab: ſo it were to be wiſhed, that theſe men would zealouſly and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly come and ſee before they would condemne vs, and heare quietly what we haue to ſay, before they do with their tongues ſo iniuriouſly execute vs.<note place="margin">Ier. 18.8.</note>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:6245:27"/>As the ſoule of Ionatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was knit to the ſoule of Dauid,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 18.1</note> ſo our ſoules are knit as in one to them. We can truly ſay, our hearts are vpright towards them, as the heart of Iehu was towards Ichonadab.<note place="margin">2. King. 10.15.</note> And yet for all that me thinkes I heare them ſay, as Iehu ſaid to Iehoram,<note place="margin">2. King. 9.19</note> what haſt thou to do with peace? turne thou behind vs. And to be briefe, we ſhal not need to inſinuate for feare, to haue their fauour: euery one of vs may with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian magnanimitie ſay vnto them, as Nehemiah ſaid to his aduerſaries,<note place="margin">Neh. 6.11.</note> Shall ſuch a man as I flie? who is he being as I am that will do it? For we may ſay as Eliſha ſaid to his man,<note place="margin">2. Kin. 6.16.</note> There are more with vs then be with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And with the Prophet Dauid, If God be with vs, who can be againſt vs? Although they haue dealt with vs ſhamefully and deſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, as the Ammonites dealt with the kind meſſengers of king Dauid,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 10.1. to 17.</note> ſhauing halfe their beards, and cutting off their skirts euen to their buttockes, yet we will neither do nor ſay,<note place="margin">Iudg. 9.</note> but as Iotham ſaid to the Sichemites, If ye haue dealt truly and purely with vs, then reioyce
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6245:28"/>ye with vs, and we will reioyce with you: but if not, we will retort vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their own tearms, What haue we to do with your peace? turne you behind vs. Theſe are they, who long ſince, as they ſay, do know right well that they ſhall die, and they doubt not but they ſhall die ſo faithfully and ſo godly, as the pureſt and moſt perfect Chriſtian of vs all.</p>
               <p>That this their error and groſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion may appeare vnto them, and vnto all others, I will yet for their ſakes, &amp; for the better patient abiding of the godly, deliuer in ſorne particular man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, by the Scriptures of truth, who they be indeed, out of this generall nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that ſhall die well, and ſo liue euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly in the glorious kingdome of heauen.</p>
               <p>The generalitie of death is not now in queſtion. It is generally agreed vpon, and withall, we find it is of neceſſitie: it is forcible and violent vpon the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table decree of the moſt Higheſt. But the queſtion is, who frames himſelfe to die willingly, and with contentment.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6245:28"/>All ſhall die of force: but none ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the kingdome of heauen, but ſuch as in ſome meaſure do die willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and with contentment. Saint Paule ſaith, Although I preach the Goſpel,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.16.17.</note> I haue nothing to reioyce of, for neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie is laid vpon me: if I do it willingly I haue a reward, but if I do it againſt my wil, what is my reward? As if he had ſaid, what religious dutie ſoeuer is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in reſpect of commandement and feare, is not to any man ſo much as thanke worthie: but that which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by man voluntarily and freely, as from a liberal heart, without reſpect of law, or conſtraint, that man ſhal haue his reward. Euen ſo is it with euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is of force ſurpriſed by death, but almightie God highly accepteth of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie man that diſpoſeth of himſelfe, with a willing heart to die. Therefore the Lord ſaid vnto the people of Iſrael: My heart is among them that are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. As if he had ſaid,<note place="margin">Iudg. 5 9.</note> Though you faile to do ſuch things as I command you, yet I will accept of your will. This wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe is a kind of ſtrong affection
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6245:29"/>and a forcible facultie of the ſoule: and yet for all that, it is led captiue vnto ſin. Such is the corruption of mans nature, being inuegled with the manifold for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and aſſaults of Satan, that it preuails againſt the will of the inner man: as S. Paul complains of himelſe verſe large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and particularly, and which makes him to ſay plainly,<note place="margin">Ro. 7.15. to the end.</note> I allow not of that which I do; for what I would that do I not, but what I hate, that do I. As if he had ſaid, Howſoeuer it be, that I offend God through corruption and frailtie, yet my heart, my mind and my will is with God. When I do any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the will of God, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it is not I that do it, but finne that dwels in me.<note place="margin">Phil. 1.23.</note> Saint Paul did deſire to die, and yet in a ſtronger appetite and affection he would not. So was it with Chriſt Ieſus.<note place="margin">Luk. 22.42.</note> So long as a man can finde in himſelfe a will to do well, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be properly the gift of God, it ſhall be accounted vnto him a deede, as it was vnto Abraham,<note place="margin">Gen. 22.12.</note> when as his will led him to ſacrifice his ſonne, and yet did it not from his naturall affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6245:29"/>He that will die willingly and wel, muſt liue willingly and well accordingly. There muſt be a continuall combat, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the ſpirit of man, and his fleſhly members.<note place="margin">Col. 3.5. Ephe. 4.21. to the end 5.8 to 22.6.10. to 19.</note> The earthly members muſt be mortified, and ſubdued by little and little, with the will and deſire of man; to wit, man muſt carrie a loathing in his mind and will of that which is euil, by a cleane contrarie affection, lifted vp to heauen. Our ſauiour Chriſt referres vs vnto the ſerpent, for two ſpeciall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, concerning this buſineſſe, in theſe words; Be wiſe as ſerpents.<note place="margin">Mat. 10.16.</note> The ſerpent being fiercely purſued, &amp; in da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of her life, not able to ſhift any longer, ſhe with her teeth, wings and clawes, will earneſtly labour in the ground, to hide her head, being then ſure enough from the purſuers, as not caring for her body, becauſe her life lies in her head: euen ſo they that make a good preparation to die willingly and well, muſt not regard their goods,<note place="margin">Ionah 1.5.</note> when their bodies are in queſtion, nor regard their bodyes, when their ſoules are in queſtion; becauſe indeede the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6245:30"/>life of their body and ſoule lies in their head Chriſt Ieſus, who hath ſo enioyned them. The other qualitie of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent is, to rouſe and rub herſelfe very vehemently when ſhe is old, againſt the ground, vntill ſhe hath gotten off all her old skinne; and then hauing new vnder it, ſhe flieth vp on high with ſuch agilitie and nimbleneſſe, as when ſhe was young: euen ſo if we will die well and willingly, ſo as our ſoules may mount vp to heauen, we muſt in our youth, and in our age rub off, and ſhake away the old man which is ſinne and wickedneſſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.6.</note> and be renewed in the ſpirit of our mindes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Three diuine cauſes mouing willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to die.</head>
               <p>The 1. is drawne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the generall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God, who in reſpect of death, deales indifferently with all the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of mankind: all men muſt die, the noble and the ignoble, the King as the begger; why then ſhould any man mourne or murmure at the death of his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6245:30"/>deareſt friends? and why ſhould he not be moued to yeld himſelfe, with al wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe &amp; contentment to die? Why ſhould any one man thinke himſelfe worthy of that prerogatiue, and priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as not to die, yea rather wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, then of conſtraint? Ioſua the Lord Generall of Iſrael, at his death tooke this as a ſtrong forcible argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to perſwade with his people, to liue well, and that they might die willingly; therefore emphatically, he ſaid,<note place="margin">Ioſua. 23.14.</note> This is the way of all the world: to wit, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I be a man as ye know, in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary acceptation with God, yet I muſt die; ſo muſt you, and ſo muſt all mankinde that liue, and are yet to be borne, looke not you to be exempted from this ſentence: but prouide ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. A voyce ſaid vnto Eſai, Crie;<note place="margin">Eſai. 40.6.</note> What, ſaid he? That all fleſh is graſſe, &amp; the grace thereof as the flower of the field. This holy Prophet being ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted and inſtigated by the Spirit of God, to prepare the way of Chriſt in the hearts of the people, he receiues as from the Lord alſo, the manner how
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6245:31"/>to moue them effectually thereunto, euen by telling them that they were all ſubiect to death, and that the moſt wiſe and moſt excellent amongſt them was ſubiect to the ſame end.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond cauſe mouing willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to die.</head>
               <p>It is drawne from a threefold ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that we make with the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: <hi>the firſt is the exchange</hi> that we make of our bodies;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.25.54. Phili. 3.21. Eſai. 49.10.25.8.</note> for this corruptible bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which is ſubiect to manifold miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and to fall from God, we ſhall haue incorruptible and immortall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. For theſe our bodies ſubiect to hunger, to thirſt, to cold, to heate, to manifold diſeaſes, to ſundrie paſſions, and other ſuch like calamities, we ſhall haue celeſtiall and glorified bodies, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie way freed of all thoſe perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The Lambe which is in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the throne,<note place="margin">Reue. 7.15.16.17.</note> ſhall gouerne his people, and ſhall leade them vnto the liuely fountaines of waters, and God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes.<note place="margin">21.3.4.</note> The tabernacle of God is with
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6245:31"/>men, and he will dwell with them, and they ſhall be his people, and God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhall be their God with them. There ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrow, neither crying, neither paine. Euery Chriſtian is alwaies longing, and deſiring this exchange, yea ſenſeleſſe creatures, do alway ſtraine with a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent deſire to be vnburthened, &amp; to be diſcharged of this life; how much more euery good man? As he that is in priſon deſires and longs to go abroad, or as Hagar in her bondage, ſo miſerable is man liuing in the fleſh, as a liuing ſoule in a body ſubiect to death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſecond exchange</hi> that we make is of our goods, as when we change earthly riches for heauenly, momentanie and tranſitorie treaſures for euerlaſting, and that which neuer fadeth. To which purpoſe the holy Ghoſt ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.19.20.</note> Lay not vp treaſures where moath or canker corrupteth, and where theeues breake through and ſteale: but lay vp treaſures for your ſelues in heauen. As if it were to ſay, The beſt things of this life, are ſubiect to corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; to manifold ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualties:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6245:32"/>but the treaſures which are in heauen, are not ſubiect either to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tability, or yet to decay. And our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt ſaith by way of a parable,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.15.10.22.</note> that the abundance of worldly wealth auailes nothing for the time prefent, which is but momentanie, neither doth it any way miniſter comfort vnto the diſtreſſed ſoule. Thus he ſaith, take heed of couetouſneſſe; for though a man haue abundance, yet his life ſtandeth not in his riches. Saint Paul ſeeing and perceiuing the inordinate deſire of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which was in his time, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the like would be continued, he ſpeakes by way of compariſon, verie diſdainefully and contemptuouſly of worldly riches,<note place="margin">1 Timo 6.17.18.19.</note> and charges men to prouide for better things, and to build vpon a better foundation. In heauen is all kinde of plentie, maturitie, and ſatietie.<note place="margin">Iudg. 18.9.10.</note> As the Spies ſaid vnto the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Dan their brethren concerning Laiſh, Ariſe and let vs go vp, we haue ſeene the land, and ſurely it is verie good, it is a place lacking nothing that is in the world; be not ſlothfull to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6245:32"/>poſſeſſe it, for God hath giuen it into your hands: euen ſo do innumerable ſentences and examples of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſay and aſſure vs as touching the kingdome &amp; immortall ioyes of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The third exchange</hi> that we make by dying willingly and well, is of our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, &amp; of our companie; as when we change the ſocietie, fellowſhip, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of men, for the company and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie of Angels;<note place="margin">Heb. 12.22.23.24. Reuel. 14.1. to 6.</note> the company of whoremongers, drunkards, liers, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, oppreſſors, and ſuch like, for the company of the Saints; the company of children on earth, for the company of children in heauen; the company of husband or wife, for the company of Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe. As a virgine that is affianced to a man thinkes it long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſolemnization thereof: ſo is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one that is affianced with Chriſt euermore deſiring his full fruition and holy fellowſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:6245:33"/>
               <head>The third cauſe mouing wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe to die.</head>
               <p>It is the mitigations, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts, &amp; helpes, that almightie God yeelds againſt the torments of death, to ſuch as do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate their mortality, with prayers and interceſſions vnto almightie God, that they may be faithfully prepared. Of which gracious qualifications of ſickneſſes, and diminiſhing of deaths torments, the holy Prophet Dauid ſpeakes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 41.3.</note> moſt plainely, The Lord will ſtrengthen him vpon his bed of ſorrow; thou Lord, ſaith the Prophet, haſt tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all his bed in his ſickneſſe as if it were to ſay, God wil enable a mercifull religious man, to endure all that he will lay on him, or elſe will diminiſh the qualitie or quantitie of the diſeaſe. To whom alſo Chriſt Ieſus ſaith, I am the phyſition: as if it were in effect to ſay, I am a preſent diſcharge for the ſoule that is ſurcharged with ſinne, and alſo a preſent qualification of bodily griefes, and naturall diſeaſes, as was manifoldly and plainely experimented by Chriſt,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6245:33"/>vpon diuers poore people, who were miſerably and mortally diſtreſſed with both.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond inſtruction.</head>
               <p>Concerning the <hi>manner, ſort, or kind</hi> of death, to wit, how diuerſly, and how many wayes, death ſeizeth on all the generation of mankind: I will diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh into foure ſorts. The which for aſſignations ſake, I muſt call by foure names, vnder the which the holy Ghoſt comprehends as in a cloſe narration di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed ouer the Bible, all maners, ſorts, and kinds of death whatſoeuer, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, and whereſoeuer: which are theſe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. the Penall death.</item>
                  <item>2. the Naturall death.</item>
                  <item>3. the Vnnaturall death.</item>
                  <item>4. the Politicall death.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe three are comprehended in that anſwer of Dauid, the ſelected man of God, to Abiſhai, concerning Saul the king, whom God deliuered into their hands, to do with him as they would: euen as Pontius Pilate deliuered Ieſus
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6245:34"/>into the hands of the Phariſes, to do with him as they would.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 26.8.9.10.</note> Let me ſmite him but once, ſaid Abiſhai to Dauid, &amp; I will ſmite him no more: intending by thoſe words, with one blow to kill Saule. Shall I lay mine hands vpon the Lords annointed, ſaid Dauid? <hi>No, I will not, God ſhall ſmite him.</hi> There he plainly related the penall death. <hi>Or his day ſhall come to die.</hi> There he plainly related the naturall death. <hi>Or he ſhall deſcend into battell.</hi> There he plainly related the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall death.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>the Penall</hi> death is that which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God did vſually inflict vpon thoſe, with whom he was wrathfully diſpleaſed; as appeared by the ineuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe thereof. It was moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miraculous, and publikely powerful, that it might be for an euerlaſting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance among all nations. Such was the puniſhment of Adam for the tranſgreſſion of Gods commandement,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.17.18.19.</note> as did appeare by many particular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntiations; and afterwards conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with his death, and with the death of all his poſterity irrecouerable in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6245:34"/>for euer. Iob to this purpoſe ſaid,<note place="margin">Iob. 34.14.15.</note> If God ſet his heart vpon man, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto himſelfe his ſpirit and his breath, all fleſh ſhall periſh together, and man ſhall returne to duſt. As if he had ſaid, If God be once wrathfully diſpleaſed with any man, how ſhall he liue? how can he or they endure the hand of him, who ſo penally &amp; power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully puniſheth vnpenitent ſinners?</p>
               <p>Druine motiues or reaſons, why God doth ſo penally, ſo miraculouſly, and ſo powerfully puniſh ſome, and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: <hi>with a ſixefold anſwer thereunto.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt Motiue why God puniſhed penally.</head>
               <p>Firſt, God puniſhed <hi>penally with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> when men were publikely and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally growne to be tirannous, cruell, and ſauagely diſpoſed, one towards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, as the people of the old world. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did the windows of heauen open,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.11.12.13. Gen. 7.4.10 11 to the end.</note> and the foundations of the great deepe breake vp, ſo that the waters preuailed exceedingly vpon the earth, and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all the hie mountains of the world.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:6245:35"/>
               <p>Likewiſe the Egyptians,<note place="margin">Exod. 1.11. to 16.5. to 14.7.8.9.10.11.14.</note> who dealt tirannouſly, &amp; cruelly with Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple this Maieſtie taking ſpeciall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof, did penally and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully puniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with manifold plagues in their own land, and afterwards with the inundations of waters, wherein their king, and many thouſands more were miraculouſly drowned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond Motiue why God puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed penally.</head>
               <p>Secondly, God puniſhed <hi>penally with fire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 19.5.15.16. to 17</note> when he ſaw that men were grown ſo generally and ſo publikely carnall, ſenſuall, fleſhly, &amp; vnnaturally defiling their owne bodies, taking the louing admonitions, and godly perſwaſions of his Saints, but as ieſts and mockes: as he did the Sodomites.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third Motiue why God puniſhed penally.</head>
               <p>Thirdly, by changing <hi>the nature and qualitie of the earth:</hi> when as particular perſons being in place of prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, did offer indignity &amp; diſloyaltie
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6245:35"/>to ſuch as were in authoritie, as did Corah Dathan,<note place="margin">Num. 16.29.36.</note> and Abiram with their companions; whom God did penally, powerfully, and miraculouſly deſtroy, by opening the earth to ſwallow them vp aliue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth Motiue why God puniſhed penally.</head>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>with ſauage beaſts,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as his holy and welbeloued people are diſdai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, mocked, and ſcorned;<note place="margin">2. King. 2.23.24.</note> as two and fortie that mocked Eliſha the Prophet of the Lord, and were penally deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Beares.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fifth Motiue why God puniſhed penally.</head>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>with Angels,</hi> when as men in authoritie do publikely and incorrigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly offend his holy Maieſtie, as did Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid in numbring his men of warre,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 24.1.15.</note> and truſting in them: whom God did penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and publikely puniſh with the death of ſeuenty thouſand of his choſen men, by the ſtroke of an Angell.<note place="margin">Act. 12.23.</note> Likewiſe Herod the king was ſtriken vnto death
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6245:36"/>publikely by an Angel, becauſe he took that glory to himſelfe, which was due to God.<note place="margin">1. King. 13.1.2.3.2. King 23.17.</note> So was Iehoram moſt penally and miraculouſly deſtroyed for his i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie, according to the ſaying of the man of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſixth Motiue why God puniſhed penally.</head>
               <p>Sixthly, where it may be demanded why God doth puniſh ſome ſo <hi>penally and ſo miraculouſly,</hi> and not others, it is drawne from his eſtabliſhed rule, and generall order of gouerning kingdoms and nations, holding it ſufficient in his godly wiſedome, to puniſh publikely ſome, in ſtead of many, that one exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſo publike and ſo penally powerful, ſhould ſerue for many hundred yeares in a whole nation or kingdome. When the Church began to ſpread through Gods mercies, there were many mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, ſignes and wonders; as that in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, as that in their iourney through the wilderneſſe, and as that their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering of Canaan, and ſo vntill the temple of Ieruſalem was built, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6245:36"/>eſtabliſhed. But afterwards as it drew nearer and nearer vnto Chriſt, they grew to be fewer and fewer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt vſe of this doctrine concerning the penall death,</head>
               <p>Serueth to forewarne <hi>Landlords and Patrons,</hi> who moſt tyrannouſly liue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſpoile of the poore: the one flee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Church, the other fleecing the commonweale, and both robbing God of his honour ſo much as they may, or as it doth bring them either pleaſure or profite. As in the old world, wherein crueltie did ouerrun the whole earth: ſo it is now in the glorious Sun-ſhine of the Goſpell. If the examples of thoſe whom God ſo powerfully &amp; ſo penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſhed, will not ſerue, it may well fall out euen in the iuſtice of God, that for the ſame crueltie, their oppreſſion and grinding of the poore, and ſelling them for old ſhooes, that they ſhall be made examples for ſuch as do come after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:6245:37"/>
               <head>The ſecond vſe of this doctrine concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning penall death.</head>
               <p>It may well ſerue to forewarne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and looſe liuers, yea all ſuch as liue according to their own luſt, giuing themſelues ouer, according to the ſwing of their own nature; leſt they alſo neglecting the vſe of Gods holy word, and the vſe of theſe fearefull examples, do, in a time when they thinke not, fall into ſome ineuitable and damnable iudgements of God in a miraculous manner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third vſe of this doctrine concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning penall death.</head>
               <p>Forewarneth all ſuch as are ſubiects, to ſubmit themſelues vnto ſuch as are in authoritie ouer them, as vnto the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ordinance of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth vſe of this doctrine concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning penall death.</head>
               <p>It may ſerue to admoniſh all ſorts of people to demeane themſelues reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, and conſcionably, towards all
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6245:37"/>the zealous profeſſors of the Goſpell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fifth vſe of this doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the penall death.</head>
               <p>It admoniſheth all thoſe that are in auctoritie, to ſubmit themſelues duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and euery way religiouſly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, as they wold their ſubiects ſhould do vnto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond manner, ſort and kind of death, to wit,</head>
               <p>The <hi>naturall death</hi> is more moderate, more milde, and more alluding to the fauour of God, then the penall death; becauſe indeede it hath reference to the promiſes of God, in Chriſt Ieſus: by whom the guilt of ſinne, and the condemnation of the law together, with the ſting of death, is qualified and in a ſort done away; leauing indeed no more to do, nor to ſay, againſt ſuch as can take hold of his promiſes, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the periſhing and deſtroying of that body, ſo naturally ſubiect to ſinne. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as Paule proclaimed, in a moſt comfortable manner, in theſe words.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6245:38"/>Death went ouer all men:<note place="margin">Rom. 5.11.</note> in as much as all men haue ſinned, as if he had ſaid, Such was the infinite mercie of God, and yet mingled with his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, that he would lay no more to the charge of his choſen, then he muſt needes by the open rules of religion, &amp; reuealed word. Moſes in his defence to the people of Iſrael concerning that open rebellion of Corah and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, ſpeakes moſt diuinely, and moſt plainely, of this kinde of death in theſe words,<note place="margin">Numb. 16.29. to 36.</note> If theſe men die the common death of all men, or if theſe be viſited with the generall viſitation of all men, then the Lord hath not ſent me. As if he had ſaid, There is a ſort or kind of death, which is naturall, which is vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and which is rightly appertayning vnto the nature of mankinde; and that which moſt commonly falles out vpon good and reaſonable deliberation, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> orderly diſpoſing of worldly affaires, &amp; vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> due bequeathing of the body to be buried. This naturall death which he calles the common death, and the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral viſitation of all men, Iob ſaith it
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6245:38"/>is as a ricke of corne,<note place="margin">Iob. 5.26.</note> which comes into the barne in due time. As if he had ſaid, This is the death indeede that is full of maturitie, and ſeaſonableneſſe; lo, thus we haue inquired of it, and ſo it is. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine he ſaith to the ſame effect:<note place="margin">Iob. 34.14.15.</note> As a ruſh cannot grow without mire, and as graſſe without water can grow no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but withereth, though it be not cut: euen ſo man by nature liueth vntill nature be quite worne, and wholly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, and then dieth though he were not touched nor medled withall in any ſort; which death is nothing ſo, nor ſo as the penall. The man of God intimating ſuch a kinde of death, ſaid to Hezckiah King of Iudah,<note place="margin">Eſai. 38.1.</note> Thou ſhalt not die with the ſword, but thou ſhalt die in peace. To wit, thou ſhalt not die the penall death, which is terrible and painefull; nor an vnwonted death, but the common death, the generall viſitation of all men, to wit the naturall death.</p>
               <p>This <hi>naturall death</hi> which is alſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the common death, and the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall viſitation of all men, hath by the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:6245:39"/>reuealed word of God foure other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior ſorts or kinds of death, whereof I muſt diſpoſe for methods ſake after this manner.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Some do die In their old age.</item>
                  <item>2. Some do die In their nonage.</item>
                  <item>3. Some do die Languiſhingly.</item>
                  <item>4. Some do die Suddenly.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt reaſon why ſome liue long.</head>
               <p>Is drawne from the ſingular fauor of almightie God, in granting vnto ſome one amongſt many, that which in his heart he ſpecially deſireth. For amongſt all things that man ſpecially deſireth, there are principally theſe two, to wit, health and wealth. For wealth a man will beſtow all his wits, all his indeuor, all his labour, all his friends, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer elſe he poſſibly can deuiſe: but for health, and that he may liue long, he will beſtow all his wealth that was ſo induſtriouſly, &amp; ſo laboriouſly got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and be contented to be counted a foole, yea a forlorne wretch, and to be indeede a begger at euerie mans
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:6245:39"/>doore, all the dayes of his life. To be breefe, as chaſtity is a ſingular gift of God, to one amongſt ten thouſand, ſo long life is a ſingular guift of God, to one amongſt ten thouſand. Salomon therefore ſaid,<note place="margin">Pro. 16.31.</note> Old age is a crowne of glorie, wherein are two goodly and godly reſpects; one is, that a man may the better &amp; the more abundantly ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther riches, by looking more reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuely into the workes of God, and the end of his creation. For the longer a man lines in a reaſonable kind of huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie, the more his gaine and get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting muſt needes be. Although his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes be but ſmall, yet if he get and ſpare, here a litle and there a litle, in continuance of time according to the old prouerbe, Many a little makes a mickle: following the example of that little poore piſmire, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to her ſmall ſtrength, and yet being diligent,<note place="margin">Pro. 6.6.</note> hath againſt winter a great heape of prouiſion; and being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo prouidident, ſhe painefully nibleth the heads of euery graine, leſt they ſhould grow, and ſo her labor loſt. The
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:6245:40"/>Maieſtie of God to ſet forth his renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed loue towards Iudah, and Ieruſalem, ſaid thus:<note place="margin">Zach. 8.4.</note> Their men ſhall liue ſo long as that they ſhall go by a ſtaffe. As there is no commandement that hath any promiſe, but the honouring of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: ſo there is no ſuch reward plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to any man as to liue long: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God made promiſe thereof to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that keepe his commandement. What temporal bleſſing did the Lord beſtow on Dauid,<note place="margin">1 King. 3.14.</note> for a reward, who was a man according to his owne heart, but long life? as the holy Ghoſt teſtifieth, he liued ſo long that he could liue no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,<note place="margin">1 King. 1.1.</note> nature was quite extinguiſhed in him. This was alſo a reward ſpecially, beſtowed vpon the ten holy Fathers,<note place="margin">Gen. 5.1. to the end.</note> before the floud. Thus ſhall men be enabled with their hands, to performe the deſire of their hearts, in contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnto the neceſſitie of the Saints. Abraham alſo had for his temporarie bleſſing,<note place="margin">Deut. 31.2.</note> an hundred and twenty yeares life, euen in his old age he was care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to fulfill the worke of the Lord ſo long, as he ſaid that he could go no
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6245:40"/>more out, and in. Length of life,<note place="margin">Deut. 11.9.</note> ſaith Moſes, is a reward for keeping of Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements: they then that keepe not Gods commandements, ſhall be guilty of Gods iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for the ſame, and alſo for the time, which they haue miſ-ſpent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The other ſpeciall and moſt principall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of long life,</hi> is that ſuch men might alſo gather ſpirituall riches. For as by little and little, men come to be ſtored with the things of this world, ſpecially if it be long continued: euen ſo by the continuall keeping of the Sabboth, by the often reading and hearing of Gods word, by vſual praiers, by often reitera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with thankefulnes the mercies of God, &amp; ſuch like, men may grow &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe moſt richly and abundantly, in the things that concernes a better life. If the increaſe be but as Eſai the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith, here a line, and there a line,<note place="margin">Eſai. 28.10.</note> to wit, a little at one time, and a little at another, either gotten or ſaued. To which purpoſe Iob ſaith,<note place="margin">Iob. 12.12.</note> In length of dayes there is wiſdome, and amongſt the ancient there is vnderſtanding.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:6245:41"/>Therefore the holy man Dauid all his life long followed the counſell and directions of the ancient, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by proſpered. It is a matter ordinarily expected from old men, that they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſuch an extraordinarie fauor at Gods hand, ſhould not onely be able well and wiſely to gouerne themſelues, but alſo well and wiſely to gouerne others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond reaſon, why ſome do die in their minoritie and non-age.</head>
               <head type="sub">The anſwer is fourefold.</head>
               <p>The firſt is drawne from Gods ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great mercy in Chriſt towards ſome to whom he imputeth nor ſinne, for their good euen in this world, that they ſhould not ſee, nor heare of thoſe lamentable calamities, &amp; wofull iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that ſhould fall vpon them, with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſometimes liued. His Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie duly te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dering the good diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the mild affection, &amp; tender inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all ſuch people, takes them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore before hand into his glorious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6245:41"/>that they ſhould not be gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with the ſight nor hearing of thoſe matters. Accordingly ſaith Eſai the Prophet, The righteous ſhall be taken away from the euill to come:<note place="margin">Eſa. 57.1.</note> that is as much to ſay, Some of Gods deare chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhall not liue to ſee and heare the miſeries which ſhall come vpon thoſe whom they do ſo highly loue. Marke the vpright man, &amp; behold the iuſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.37.</note> the end of that man is peace. So it is ſaid of Ieroboams ſonne,<note place="margin">1. King. 14.13.17.</note> he only of Ieroboam ſhall come to the graue, becauſe in him there is found ſome goodnes towards the Lord God of Iſrael. As if it had bin ſaid, He onely of that houſe ſhall go to his graue in peace, becauſe he ſhall not ſee the deſolation that ſhall come vpon the land. So alſo was it ſaid of Ioſias, as if it were in the proper perſon of God, in theſe words;<note place="margin">2. King. 22.20.</note> I will gather thee to thy fathers houſe, thou ſhalt be put in thy graue in peace, and thine eyes ſhall not ſee the euill that I will bring vpon this place.<note place="margin">Wiſd. 1.13.14.</note> Though they were ſoone dead. yet fulfilled they much time: as if he had ſaid, They did much
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6245:42"/>glorie to God, and much comfort to his Saints in that litle time wherin they liued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond anſwer, why ſome do die in their non-age or minoritie.</head>
               <p>It is drawn from the mercifull good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God in Chriſt Ieſus, in brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them more ſpeedily out of this world into their heauenly inheritance. For by how much the ſooner he taketh them out of this world, by ſo much the ſooner he bringeth them into their wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed poſſeſſion,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.14.</note> God prouiding better things for them. In the prayer which Chriſt our aduocate hath framed for vs, we are taught ſpecially to deſire the ſpeedie entrance into this our heauenly inheritance, in theſe words, Thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome come. And with all for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enabling, propping, &amp; comforting of his people with patience, to abide the time, he ſaith in a figuratiue ſpeech, Behold,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.8. to 14.</note> he cometh leaping vpon the mountaines, and skipping vpon the hils like a young Roe, or as a young
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6245:42"/>Hart. Iob ſpeaking of the beſt eſtate of man liuing in this world, ſaith thus; While his fleſh is vpon him,<note place="margin">Iob. 14.22.</note> he ſhall be ſorrowfull; and whiles his ſoule is in him, he ſhall mourne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third anſwer why ſome do die in their minoritie.</head>
               <p>It is the ſinne of the parents, or beſt affected friend of him that dieth, whoſe death is to him a puniſhment. For as generally amongſt parents, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more grieuous, nothing more irkeſome, then the death of their yong children; ſpecially ſuch as are tractable: ſo is there no puniſhment ſo counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailable as the death of ſuch children. Naomi, when her husband &amp; her two ſonnes were dead, ſaid vnto her daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in law:<note place="margin">Ruth. 1.13. to 21.</note> The hand of the Lord is gone out againſt me, the almighty hath giuen me much bitternes. The widdow of Sarepta, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her yong ſon was dead cried, &amp; ſaid to Eliah;<note place="margin">1. King. 17.18.19 20.</note> Art thou come to call my ſinnes to remembrance, and to ſlay my ſonne? As if ſhe had ſaid, I ſee the greatnes of my ſinnes againſt God,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6245:43"/>by the greatneſſe of my puniſhment, which, by taking away my ſonne, his Maieſtie hath inflicted vpon me. The ſame Prophet in his interceſſion farther ſaid; O Lord God, haſt thou puniſhed this widdow by killing her ſonne? As if he had ſaid, O Lord do not ſo: the world was not worthy of them,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.38.</note> the ſins of worldly men deſcrue them not. Lord do not lay her ſinnes ſo heauily to her charge. Saint Paul ſaid, that the recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of Epaphroditus out of his mortall ſickeneſſe,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.25.26.27.</note> imparted the mercie of God towards him, leſt he ſhould haue had ſorrow vpon ſorrow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth reaſon why ſome do die in their minoritie.</head>
               <p>It is the extreme wickedneſſe and outrage that ſome would grow into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and his Saints, if they were ſuffered to liue. To which purpoſe his holy Maieſtie ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſa. 101.8.</note> I wil deſtroy all the wicked of the land, that I may cut off al the workers of iniquitie from the citie of the Lord. As if he had ſaid, I will preuent by death the vngodly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6245:43"/>of graceleſſe men, they ſhall not liue ſo long as to do villany againſt my people.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third queſtion why ſome do die languiſhingly.</head>
               <head type="sub">It is anſwered threefold.</head>
               <p>Firſt, to declare that the vſe of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, Chirurgerie and ſuch like meanes are nought worth, and to no purpoſe, when as God denieth the vertue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. To make men know that the beſt meanes, and the effects thereof, are two diſtinct things, Almightie God in his irefull ſpeech to the Egyptians, ſaith thus, Take balme,<note place="margin">Ier. 46.11.</note> ô virgine daughter of Egypt, and in vaine ſhalt thou vſe many medicines, for thou ſhalt haue no health. He ſpeakes againe by the ſame Prophet after this manner, Thy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings are incurable,<note place="margin">30.12.13.</note> and thy wounds dolorous, there are no plaiſters, nor medicines, nor helpe for thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:6245:44"/>
               <head>The ſecond anſwer why ſome do die languiſhingly,</head>
               <p>Is drawne from the fatherly care of Almightie God, who knowing whereunto ſome of his children are inclined, and naturally addicted, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly he keepes them vnder, he ſtill diſables them from the performance of that they wold, euen in matters hurtful to their owne ſoules. As a naturall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tenderly affecting the good of his ſonne, whom he ſeeth to take head, &amp; make way to ſpend all, ſometimes he threatens him ſore, ſometimes he beats him ſharply, at other times he feeds him with hard fare, now &amp; then he cloathes him with ragged apparrell, and alway keepes him without mony. Or as a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intending to weane her child from the breaſt, lets him crie much; if that wil not do, ſhe annoints it with worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood or ſuch like, euen ſo God deales with ſome ſuch as are ſtubborne or like to grow diſobedient, he keepes them vnder with many ſtrange deuices, and doth diſable them euerie where, &amp; at al
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:6245:44"/>times from doing that they would, to the hurt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. The peregrination of the people of Iſrael fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Egypt to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, was through the moſt vaſte, deep, and dangerous places of all the world; and ſometimes through goodly val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leyes, by pleaſant riuers, and ſuch like places of contentment: ſometimes in great penurie &amp; ſcarceneſſe of all good things, and ſometimes in great plentie of euerie thing; &amp; thus with vncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, mutabilities, liking &amp; diſliking 40.<note place="margin">Num. 33.1</note> yeares together before they came into the promiſed land, not reſting in any one good place one whole yeare, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingling one with another. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo is it with gods people, ſpecially ſuch of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as his Maieſty knoweth will not trauel rightly the right way. Moſes ſaid, God led them 40 yeares in the wildernes,<note place="margin">Deut. 8.2.3</note> to trie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to humble them, to know what was in their hearts. God ſaid by the mouth of his Prophet thus,<note place="margin">Ier. 30.11.</note> Although I haue ſtriken thee with the wound of an enemie, and with a ſharpe chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe thy ſins were increaſed, I will correct thee, but not vtterly cut
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:6245:45"/>thee off. So God ſaid to Dauid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Salomon his ſonne,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 7.13.</note> If he ſin I will chaſtiſe him with the roddes of the children of men, but my mercy will I not vtterly take from him. Whom the Lord loueth,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.6.</note> ſaith the holy Author to the Hebrues, he chaſtiſeth, &amp; he ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth euery ſonne that he receiueth. We haue a famous example in Dauid, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if God had not humbled with continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all perſecution, it is certaine he would haue driuen Saul violently out of his kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third reaſon why ſome do die languiſhingly.</head>
               <p>As the former proceeded from the mercie of God towards thoſe whom he would reforme: ſo in this we ſhall finde the ineuitable iuſtice of God vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wicked, euery way diſabling and putting them downe from their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and enterpriſes, keeping them at a low rate, and as it were at a ſcantling. He deales with them, as with the houſe of Ioab the murtherer;<note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.23.</note> neuer without running iſſues, neuer without
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6245:45"/>the leproſie, or one that leaneth on a ſtaffe, or doth fall on the ſword, or lack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth bread. So God ſaid he would deale with the people Iſrael, if they would not keepe his commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, in theſe words: The Lord wil make thy plagues wonderfull, and of long continuance,<note place="margin">Deut. 28.59.</note> ſore diſeaſes, and of long durance. Such a writing was brought to Iehoram King of Iudah, from the Lord, becauſe of his Idolatrie, contayning this effect; Thou ſhalt be in great diſeaſes,<note place="margin">2 Chro 21.12 to 16. 2 King. 15.5.</note> in thy boweles day by day. Ahaziah King of Iudah was diſabled with a leproſie for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth reaſon why ſome do die ſuddenly or inſtantly, hath theſe two reſpects.</head>
               <p>The firſt reſpect is the matter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they die. Some die with old age as did Dauid; ſome with long endured ſickneſſe; ſome with the eminency of the place which miniſtreth preſent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and death, as a ſhip againſt the rocks, a wilderneſſe of wilde beaſts, a ſtorehouſe of gunpouder. Sometimes
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:6245:46"/>in reſpect of Gods ſudden decree, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lords breath is in his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrels.</p>
               <p>Sometimes being occaſioned from a naturall cauſe, which learned Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſay, doth ariſe <hi>ab apoplexia,</hi> a ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page in the head, or <hi>à vomida pulmonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> a ſuffocation in the lungs, or elſe <hi>à ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cope vel cardiaogmo,</hi> from the ſtomacke or heart. All which is common both to good and bad men, to the iuſt and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt: and that which neuer giues war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nor knowledge, any manner of way formerly to be preuented by phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, and therefore rightly called <hi>Mors repentina,</hi> a ſudden and an vnprouided death.</p>
               <p>The ſecond reſpect is the manner or difference betwixt both. The bad and vniuſt man dieth ſuddenly, how long ſoeuer he liueth, and what warning ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he hath,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.3.</note> becauſe of his vnprepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redneſſe, like the fooliſh virgins: or like the vniuſt and careleſſe ſteward.</p>
               <p>The good and vpright man who feares the Lord, and rules himſelfe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his lawes, is alwaies vpon
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:6245:46"/>his guard, like the good houſeholder, who knowes on a night ſuddenly his houſe ſhall be broken vp: and like thoſe wiſe virgins alwaies in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, euer looking for death. This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blance of both was in the old world; Noah was well prepared, the reſt were nothing at all.</p>
               <p>The <hi>eight vſes</hi> that we are to make of this doctrine, concerning the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall death, which is the common death, and the generall viſitation of all men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt vſe concerning the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall death.</head>
               <p>It ſerueth to reproue old men, who either idlely or riotouſly ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonies, and their parents portions. The holy Prophet Hoſea ſaith,<note place="margin">Hoſe 7.9.</note> Gray haires are here and there, vpon him, and he knowes it not: to wit, the aged man conſiders not, the old man whoſe life is almoſt ended remembers not, he thinkes vpon time enough to be get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and ſparing, which is yet left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde; he deuiſeth vpon many more yeares, &amp; ſo goeth on vntill his ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:6245:47"/>faileth him, and he purpoſeth to bring many matters vnto good effect, euen by his wits, when as indeede with his ſtrength, his ſenſes will faile him. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Ieremy the Prophet ſaid,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.27.</note> It is good for a man to beare the yoke in his youth. It is expedient that he do take paines in his profeſſion while he may, leſt when he ſhould giue, he be enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to take. Salomon not onely for matters of ſaluation, but alſo for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this life, doth exhort very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, particularly &amp; plainly,<note place="margin">Eccle. 12.1.2. to 8.</note> thus: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber thy maker in thy youth, whiles the euil dayes come not, nor the yeares approch wherein thou ſhalt ſay. I haue no pleaſure in them. To conclude with that patheticall ſaying of Saint Paul,<note place="margin">1 Timo. 5.8.</note> If there be any man that proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not for his owne, namely for them of his houſehold, he denieth the faith, and is worſe then an infidell; the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable age is not that which is meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by time, neither that which is mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the number of yeares: but wiſdome is the gray haire,<note place="margin">Wiſd 4.7.8.</note> &amp; an vndefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led life is the old age. As if he had ſaid,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:6245:47"/>It is not the age of any man, how old ſoeuer, that deſerues reuerence and ſpeciall account amongſt men: but it is the knowledg of God, and an vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueable life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond vſe concerning the naturall death.</head>
               <p>It ſerueth to reproue thoſe who by their ouer much care, and exceſſiue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, haue gotten much wealth, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way getting, euer ſparing, neuer ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, accounting from ten to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and from the hundred to the thouſands, for euery of their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; yea and many times (hauing nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſonne nor daughter) they know not for whom: and yet in all this time and amongſt all this wealth, hauing nothing at all for themſelues againſt the day of the Lord, hauing indeede neither oyle nor lampes. Much like the glutto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that fared deliciouſly euery day,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.19.</note> &amp; gorgeouſly apparelled: but inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for his ſoule he was more miſerable then any, and as the poore begger at his doore outwardly. So commonly at
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:6245:48"/>deathes doore the wicked parteth with all ioyes: and there the godly receiues it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third vſe concerning the naturall death.</head>
               <p>It ſerueth to reproue all ſuch parents, who hauing a ſonne or a daughter ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from them by death in his minori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they do not take to heart nor thinke the extraordinary care, the greedy gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, the intollerable ſhiftes, and the manifold deuices which they vſed to get worldly wealth and preferments for him. So that they euer kept from their heart, or for the moſt part, all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable care of trayning him vp in the feare and nurtour of the Lord, ſo as he might be a neceſſary member in Church or comon wealth. They conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not, neither can they be made to thinke, much leſſe to beleeue, that God tooke him away for their puniſhment. And for this cauſe alſo God takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way another, and ſo another of their beſt and deareſt children, leauing ſuch parents, either none at all, or elſe ſuch
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:6245:48"/>as are graceleſſe, and without hope to be any comfort vnto them. If parents out of their naturall affection, or out of Gods word, would but imagine what a dolefull day, what a ſorrowfull ſight, and a galling griefe it would be vnto them, to ſee one child after another ſuffer the bitter paines and pangs of death, &amp; then being dead to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of their ſaluation: ſuch parents might the better and the ſooner ſee, &amp; take knowledg of their ſinnes towards their poore children, and ſo by true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance be turned vnto the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth vſe concerning the naturall death.</head>
               <p>It ſerueth to reproue thoſe who out of their ouer abounding naturall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection towards their children, are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer prepared to part with their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, no not though they be to change their company, for the company of God himſelfe, and the company of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers their brothers and ſiſters, for the company of the holy Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in heauen. And their worldly ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:6245:49"/>for the true treaſures purchaſt by the precious bloud of Ieſus Chriſt. And this becauſe that either they want knowledge, or faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fift vſe concerning the naturall death.</head>
               <p>It ſerueth to reproue thoſe who liue ſo ſecurely and ſo careleſly, as if they had made a couenant with death, vntill an appointed day: or as if they could keepe death away ſo long as they would, or at leaſt giue themſelues law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full warning. Vpon theſe comes the day of the Lord ſuddenly, not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of God, but in reſpect of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, being vnprouided. By how much they want of that they ſhould haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his coming, or by how little they feare death, by ſo much the more terrible and fearefull death is vnto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſixth vſe concerning the naturall death.</head>
               <p>It ſerueth to reproue thoſe who arrogate to much vnto the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:6245:49"/>of the meanes, attributing that vertue vnto them, which indeede is due vnto God; as in the time of ſickneſſe, to phyſicke, ſurgery and ſuch like. No maruell though they languiſh in their diſeaſes, and no man able to helpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. What was the ouerthrow of ſo many thouſands of the Iſraelits, &amp; the taking away of the Arke of God by the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines?<note place="margin">1. Sam. 4.5.</note> was it not becauſe they relied to much vpon the arke? as appeared by their ſhooting and loud reioycing, as though heauen and earth rang toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Ieremie ſpeaketh of them at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, how they vanted and boaſted of their temple, ſaying,<note place="margin">Ier. 7.4.</note> The temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord: therefore the Lord gaue their Temple to be ranſacked and ruinated by Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar king of Babylon.<note place="margin">Dan. 1.1.2.</note> Ieremie likewiſe ſpeaking of the pride and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuſneſſe of the Egyptians, who in their ſtrength and multitude of their men, concluded moſt infallibly the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ouerthrow of the people of Iſrael:<note place="margin">Ier. 46 7.</note> They come, ſaith he like floods and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, with raging horſes, ſwift chariots,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:6245:50"/>Blackemores and Libians to ſhoote and to beare ſhields, yet all in vaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſeuenth vſe concerning the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall kind of death.</head>
               <p>It ſerueth to reproue thoſe who do derogate from the worthineſſe of the meanes, which God in his mercie hath ordained in his Church and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, to be in him, and for him, or as in his ſtead, helpers &amp; comforters vnto his people: as in the time of ſickneſſe, not to ſeek to the Phyſitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they rather ſcoffe and ſcorne them, and they deride their profeſſion. Theſe indeed, as the former, are acceſſarie to their owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall diſeaſes, languiſhing maladies, and in the end, to their owne death: not becauſe that they thereby do di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly ſhorten their liues, but becauſe that they do fruſtrate, ſo much as in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lieth, the holy ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of God, which are ioyned with his decree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The eight vſe concerning the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall death.</head>
               <p>It ſerueth to reproue thoſe who run
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:6245:50"/>into eminent dangers &amp; places of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion; they auoid not when they may conuemently, outragious elements, as fire, water, and ſuch like: or enterpriſe to performe actions, which ſtand not either with their wits, or with their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>3.</hi> generall ſort, manner, or kind of death, to wit, the vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall death.</head>
               <p>The <hi>vnnatur all death,</hi> is that which is more violent, more abhorring nature, more croſſe and contrarie to the lawes &amp; ordinances of God. A kind of death which proceedeth from mans ſelfe, or rather a death inſtigated by the diuell: meerely derogatiue to the Maieſtie of Gods gouernment, diſhonourable to his name, &amp; by the reuealed word, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachfull to the ſaluation of the ſoules of ſuch. An vntimely and an vnſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder this kind of death there are <hi>4.</hi> other inferior ſorts.</head>
               <p>Firſt when a man <hi>killeth himſelfe vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:6245:51"/>or againſt his will,</hi> as Ahaziah king of Iſrael did with a fall.<note place="margin">2. King. 1.6</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, when a man <hi>kils himſelfe wittingly and willingly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 31.4 2. Sam. 17.23. 1. King. 16.18.</note> as Saul did with his owne ſword; as Achitophel hanged himſelfe; and as Zimry did, that burnt himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, when a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>is killed by another vnwittingly and vnwillingly,</hi> not hauing hated him before;<note place="margin">Nu. 35.22. Ioſ. 20.1.2.3</note> for whoſe ſaftetie God appointed cities of refuge.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, when a man <hi>is wittingly and willingly killed by another,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Sam. 3.27 2. Sam. 20.10.</note> as Abner was by Ioab, and as Amaſa was.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt queſtion concerning the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the vnnaturall death.</head>
               <p>Why it is, or how it comes to paſſe, that ſome vnwittingly and vnwillingly do kil and deſtroy themſelues, yea with their act and deed, ſome hang them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, ſome burne themſelues, ſome drowne themſelues, and ſuch like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of vnnaturall death?</p>
               <p>This kind of vnnaturall executions happeneth many times on the iuſt, as well as on the vniuſt, vpon the wiſe, as
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:6245:51"/>vpon the fooliſh; vpon the rich as vpon the poore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The anſwer therefore is twofold, one concerning the vngodly, the other concerning the godly.</head>
               <p>That which concernes the vngodly, is, when any ſuch man or woman vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wittingly puts or brings himſelfe into perillous places, puts himſelfe to death by his owne act and deed. It pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the vpright iuſtice of God, ruling and ouer-ruling man how puiſſant, and how outragious ſoeuer he be, making him in deſpite of his heart, &amp; wholly againſt his will, to do that to himſelfe which ſhal be to his owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and againſt nature. To which purpoſe God ſpeakes by his Prophet, vnto the wicked, in theſe words;<note place="margin">Ier. 20.21.</note> I will make thee to be a terror vnto thy ſelfe, and to thy friends. And by a phraſe of ſpeech, as from him who hath ſuffered great indignitie, ſaying to the wrong doer, I will make thee vndo that again which thou haſt don vnto me, although thou diddeſt it by another: I will make
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:6245:52"/>thee vndo it thy ſelfe, and with thine owne hands. After this manner it is ſaid, that God doth ſurcharge the wicked, who ſometimes haue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled and ſurcharged his people. As for example, Paul and Silas hauing bene wrongfully impriſoned, and ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whipped by the gouernors of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippi, a famous citie in Macedonia, they ſent their Sergeants,<note place="margin">Act. 16.35.36.</note> ſaying, Let theſe men go. Nay verily ſaid they, we haue bene beaten openly vncondem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and now would they put vs away priuily? but let them come and bring vs out. So they came and brought them out, and prayed them and deſired them to depart. Likewiſe he ſaith by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Ieremie to the people of Iſrael,<note place="margin">Ier. 5.9.</note> As ye haue worſhipped ſtrange gods in your owne land, ſo ſhall ye worſhip ſtrange gods in another land. As if he had ſaid, Whereas in your owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try you would worſhip idols whether I would or not, now I will make you do the like in another la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d whether you wil or not; how hurtfull and loathſome ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it be vnto you, yet I will enforce
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:6245:52"/>you. Abſolon,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 18.9.10.</note> who was a publike ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to the crowne of Iudah &amp; a deadly enemie to the king his father, by his owne act and deed vnwillingly, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his heart and mind hung himſelf. King Pharaoh hauing drowned many of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s people in Egypt, by the iuſtice of God vpon him, vnwittingly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly drowned himſelfe and his hoſt euen by his own act and deed.<note place="margin">Exo. 14.26.</note> The Moabites miſtaking the element of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for bloud, became ſecure and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,<note place="margin">2. King. 3.22.23.16.17.</note> and therfore vnwittingly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly, and yet by their owne act &amp; deed, they fell vpon the ſword of their enemies. Wherin God ſhewed that eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ſelfe ſame matter wherwith the Iſraelites were comforted and relieued, their enemies were confounded and diſcomfited: where with a man ſinneth,<note place="margin">Wiſ. 11.13.</note> euen by the ſame God vſually puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. And as Samuel ſaid vnto Agag the king of Amalek, As thy ſword hath made many women childleſſe,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.33.</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo ſhall thy mother be childleſſe of thee amongſt other women.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:6245:53"/>
               <head>The ſecond anſwer concerning the godly, who vnwittingly and vnwillingly do by their owne act and deed kill and deſtroy themſelues, is threefold.</head>
               <p>The firſt ſort are thoſe, who being ſurpriſed <hi>with ſorrowes and anguiſh of heart:</hi> as Eli, who hauing hauing heard that both his ſonnes were ſlaine by the Philiſtims,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 4.19.20.21.</note> and ſpecially that the Arke was taken, he fell back out of his chaire and brake his necke. Likewiſe Phineas wife, when ſhe heard ſuch newes of the Arke, pained &amp; died. So Nabal hauing heard by his wife what Dauid had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.37.</note> with ſorrow his hart died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him, and he was like a ſtone.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſort <hi>miſtaking the vſe of the good creatures of God,</hi> and their owne ſtrength, do vnwittingly &amp; vnwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues:<note place="margin">2. King. 4.18.39.40. 2 King. 3.</note> ſo did the Shuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits ſonne with ouermuch heate in his head. So did the children of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, who in ſtead of pothearbs gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red wilde gourds, and therewith had poyſoned themſelues, had not the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:6245:53"/>miraculouſly and ſpeedily holpen them.</p>
               <p>The third ſort being ouercome <hi>with drowſineſſe and ſtupiditie of nature</hi> do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wittingly &amp; vnwillingly, euen by their owne act and deed kill the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues: ſo did Eutychus,<note place="margin">Act. 20.9.</note> who ſleeping at Saint Pauls ſermon fell out of an high window, ſo that he was dead.</p>
               <p>The ſecond queſtion, Why ſome kill and deſtroy themſelues, ſo diuerſly and ſo many wayes, and that wittingly and willingly, as by their owne act and deede.</p>
               <p>The anſwer is of foure ſorts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt ſort who kill and deſtroy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues wittingly and willingly,</head>
               <p>Are thoſe who, <hi>through the ignorance of God</hi> that is in them, do not know whether there be an hell or a heauen. Of which ignorance, Saint Paul ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth thus:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14.</note> The naturall man perceiueth not the things that be of God; they are ſpirituall, but he is carnall. It may be ſaid vnto them, as Chriſt ſaid vnto Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">Mar. 8.33.</note> Thou ſauoreſt not the things that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:6245:54"/>be of God, but the things that be of men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond ſort who killand deſtroy themſelues wittingly and willingly,</head>
               <p>Are thoſe who in the iuſtice of God for <hi>their vnpenitencie and reprobate man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of behautour,</hi> hauing the eyes of their vnderſtanding ſhut vp, their ſenſes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away for the time, their wittes not their owne, their memory gone. Of which kind of benumming Saint Paul ſpeakes to the Romans;<note place="margin">Rom. 1.24. to the end. Ephe. 1.18.</note> and prayeth for the reſtoring of the Epheſians, to wit: that the eyes of their vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding might be opened. The Aramites being in this reprobate ſenſe, hauing their eyes of vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding ſhut vp,<note place="margin">2 King. 6.18.19.</note> we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t into Samaria where was their mortall enemie the King of Iſrael; when as they thought to haue gone home vnto their maſter and King. In like manner, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bucadnezer the King of Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Dani. 4.30.31.</note> being alſo in this te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per by the vpright iuſtice of God, went out of his pallace from amongſt his Nobility, vpon his hands
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:6245:54"/>and feete, into the fields amongſt his beaſts, where he continued as a beaſt 7. yeares. Saul, as he thought, was ſafe,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.11.12. to 18.</note> hauing his ſpeare at his head, with Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Lord Generall, and the people guarding him round about; but God ſent a dead ſleepe vpon them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Dauid went in, and brought forth the Kings ſpeare, &amp; might haue ſlaine him. No man ſaw it nor marked it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did any awake, ſo bewitched they were of their ſenſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third ſort who kill and deſtroy themſelues wittingly and willingly,</head>
               <p>Are thoſe who from an exceeding diſtruſt of Gods mercies, hauing long lauiſhed in an abominable life, &amp; neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected al the meanes of their faith, they conclude deſperately with themſelues. Much like the foure leprous men,<note place="margin">2. King. 7.3.4.5.</note> at the gates of Samaria, who ſaid one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, If we tarie here we ſhall die; if we go into the citie we ſhall die come, let vs go into the the tents of the Aramits; if they ſaue our liues, we ſhall liue; and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:6245:55"/>if they kill vs we are but dead: and as the King of Iſrael ſhamefully ſaid, This euill comes from the Lord,<note place="margin">2 King. 6.33.</note> ſhall I at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend vpon the Lord any longer? To them and to all ſuch it may be ſaid, as Elias ſaid to Ahab King of Iſrael, Thou haſt ſold thy ſelfe to worke wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe.<note place="margin">1 King. 21.20.</note> Thus theſe men betraying all ſuccors that reaſon offers, they ſet euery member or members againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother,<note place="margin">Iudg. 7.22.</note> like the ſword of the Midianits ruſhed into the bowels one of another: the ſoule againſt the body, &amp; the body againſt the ſole, althings vpſide downe like the chariots of Pharo,<note place="margin">Exo. 14.25.26.</note> the wheeles vpward, and the bodies downeward; greatly afraid where no feare was, like a lion who maſtering al other beaſts in the forreſt, quakes and trembles at the crowing of a cocke. Or rather like the damned indede,<note place="margin">Pro. 28.1.</note> flying when none purſueth; they are ſtriken with faintnes of heart,<note place="margin">Leui. 26.17.36. Deut. 28.28. 1. Sam. 13.6.</note> with the ſound or ſhaking of a leafe, and with cowardlineſſe to hide themſelues in caues, in pits, and in dens, from a ſword. All theſe being former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowne vnto God, for the manner
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:6245:55"/>of their behauiour, his Maieſtie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed vpon the manner of their death, not as it was in him, but as it would be in them. As the diuell did put into the heart of Iudas to betray Chriſt his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, ſo the diuell puteth into the hearts of thoſe to betray themſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth ſort who kill and deſtroy themſelues wittingly and willingly,</head>
               <p>Are thoſe who do not onely neglect all good meanes, and opportunities thereunto: but alſo voluntarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne it treade it vnder feete, and with fierce affection following their owne wayes: of whom Ieremy ſpeakes repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſiuely after this maner, as it were in the proper perſon of the almightie God.<note place="margin">Iere. 2.12.13.</note> My people haue committed two euils, they haue forſaken me the well of life, and haue diged vp puddles of their owne. As Pontius Pilate deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Ieſus vnto the common people,<note place="margin">Luke. 21.24.</note> to do with him what they would: euen ſo theſe in a ſort do deliuer vp moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturally their bodies and their ſoules
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:6245:56"/>vnto the diuell, to do with them what he will.<note place="margin">Luk. 21.14.</note> They fall vpon the edge of the ſword, to wit, into eminent and ineui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table dangers.<note place="margin">Iudg. 9.54.</note> As Abimelech being brayned by a woman, called haſtily vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his page, Draw thy ſword and ſlay me, that it be not ſaid, that a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſlue me: euen ſo do they that in their diſtreſſes do not relie vpon Gods directions. As the waters preuailed &amp; increaſed ouer all high mountaines, ſo doth the diuell increaſe and multiply ſinne vpon ſinne in the vnpenitent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, making him vnrecouerable to god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third queſtion concerning thoſe that do wittingly and willingly kill and deſtroy one another.</head>
               <p>The Prophet Malachi wondering at ſuch vnnaturalneſſe, queſtioneth after this maner:<note place="margin">Mal. 2.</note> Haue we not all one father? hath not one God made vs? Why do we euerie one tranſgreſſe againſt his brother, &amp; breake the couenant of our fathers? The anſwer to this queſtion is drawne firſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the killer, ſecondly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:6245:56"/>the killed. The killer is drawne therunto ſometimes by an euill ſpirit, executing therein vpon the killed, the ruſtice of God, for ſome former murther, as vpon Abimelech,<note place="margin">Iudg. 9.23.55.56.57.</note> who killed his ſeuenty bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. To which effect the Prophet Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy ſaith, They that deuoure ſhall be deuoured they that ſpoile thee ô Iſrael,<note place="margin">Iere 30.16.</note> ſhall be ſpoiled, &amp; they that rob thee, I will giue to be robbed. So he ſaith by his Prophet Ezekiell,<note place="margin">Ezek. 35.6.</note> Except thou hate bloud, bloud ſhall purſue thee. Ioaſh the King of Iudah hauing cauſed the ſon of Iehoiada the prieſt to be ſlaine innocently,<note place="margin">2 Chro. 24.25.</note> he deſired God to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber it, and therefore God according to iuſtice remembring it indeede, his owne ſeruants murthered him as he lay in his bed.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 14.20.</note> So it is ſaid that the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtians ſlew one another; alſo when the euill ſpirit was vpon Saul,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 19.10.</note> he ſtill ſought to kill Dauid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond motiue in the killer.</head>
               <p>The killer is drawne thereunto by malice &amp; enuie,<note place="margin">Gene. 4.4.</note> as Caine ſlue his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Abell. Which made Dauid to ſay
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:6245:57"/>vnto Saul,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 26.19.</note> If the Lord do thus ſtirre thee vp, let him receiue a ſacrifice at my hands: but if it be the children of men that haue done it, curſed be they before the Lord. To which effect the Lord ſpeakes by his Prophet Ezechiel vnto the Seirians concerning his people Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,<note place="margin">Ere. 35.5.</note> Thou haſt a perpetuall hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my people, and haſt put them to flight with the ſword, when their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie had an end. As if he had ſaid, O Seir, thou moſt malicious and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious wretch, thou perſecuteſt my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, not as an inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Gods iuſtice, but out of thy owne extreme malice &amp; enuie, euen when I was at peace with them. Againe, he ſaith vnto all ſuch by the mouth of his Prophet Zacharie, I am wrath with theſe careleſſe heathen,<note place="margin">Zach. 1.15.</note> who when I was angrie but a litle with my people, they helped forward the affliction. Wherein he ſheweth that they were very malicious, and very en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiouſly diſpoſed. After that manner Caine ſlue his brother.<note place="margin">Gen. 4.8.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:6245:57"/>
               <head>The third motiue in the killer.</head>
               <p>One killeth another out of his owne malicious &amp; diuelliſh quarrels, with an vnſatiable deſire of reuenging. As Ioab ſlue Abner for the bloud of Haſael,<note place="margin">2 Sa. 3.27.</note> which he had ſhed.<note place="margin">2. Sa. 13.27.</note> So Abſolon ſlue Ammon. The holy Ghoſt ſaith of a graceleſſe man,<note place="margin">Wiſ. 10.13.</note> In his wrath he killeth his brother, &amp; in his furie he periſheth. As if he had thereby pointed out by two ſpeciall notes, a reprobate and a moſt vile man, ſhedding his brothers bloud, to wit, by ſurie and by anger. As Sampſon being moued with an intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable paſſion,<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.28</note> deſired nothing of God but that he might haue ſtrength to be auenged for his two eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth motiue in the killers.</head>
               <p>Some kill one another being drawne thereunto through couetouſneſſe, as Ieſabel ſlue Naboth.<note place="margin">1. King. 21.12.</note> This kind of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie is in ſuch, for lukers ſake, as he of whom Nahum the Prophet ſpeaketh, likening him to a Lion, in theſe words; He did teare in peeces for his whelpes,<note place="margin">Nah. 2.12.</note>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:6245:58"/>and woried for his Lioneſſe, and filled the holes with prey, and his dens with ſpoyle. Euen ſo theſe graceleſſe grigs to haue worldly wealth for their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, will ſpare neither old nor yong.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fifth motiue in the killer is,</head>
               <p>When a man doth kill another in the quarrell of God and his people, as did Ehud,<note place="margin">Iudg. 3.21. Iudg. 4.21.</note> who ſlue Eglon: and as Iael who ſlue Siſera.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſixth motiue in the killer</head>
               <p>Is to kill and deſtroy, being drawne thereunto with a damnable rage, for the offence of ſome other. As that moſt execrable example of Saul, who killed the prieſts of Nob,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 22.18.19.22.</note> through the offence that was committed by Dauid, as he himſelfe confeſſed to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biathar: I am guiltie, ſaid he, of their bloud, they were innocent. Murther hath bene held among barbarian hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens an intollerable and a reuengefull ſinne, as appeared by their words, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the viper fell vpon Pauls hand,<note place="margin">Act. 28.1.2.3. &amp;c.</note> Sure ſaid they, this man is a murtherer, who
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:6245:58"/>although he hath eſcaped the ſeas, yet vengeance hath not ſuffered him to liue.<note place="margin">Gen. 4.10.11.</note> The bloud of Abel cried for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. And to conclude; Murther is ſo deteſtable in Gods ſight, and ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring nature, as for what cauſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer one man ſhal or doth wittingly &amp; willingly kill another, if it be ſecretly done,<note place="margin">Deut. 21.1. to 10.</note> as doth appeare by diligent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition made for the finding out of the murtherer, the hainouſneſſe of the ſinne alſo appears by the greeuouſneſſe of the puniſhments, which are no leſſe then death.<note place="margin">Leui. 24.17.21. Deu. 21.8.9.</note> It endangereth the whole congregation with the plagues of God how guiltleſſe ſoeuer they be of that fact.<note place="margin">Gen. 4.10. Re. 6.9.10.11.</note> It calleth and crieth out from earth to heauen for vengeance, &amp; the ſoules of the Saints in heauen do call and crie vnto God for inſtice. The holy man Dauid, who by his regall authoritie, &amp; alſo in his martiall affaires, was to ſhed the bloud of many: yet he prayed that God would deliuer him from bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiltineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:6245:59"/>
               <head>Now concerning the killed, to wit, why God doth ſuffer innocent blood to be ſhed wilfully, or to be ſubiect to the will of the wicked.</head>
               <head type="sub">The anſwer is twofold.</head>
               <p>The firſt anſwer concerning the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, is to manifeſt Gods ſecret decree concerning the time of mans departure; and as for the manner how, it is all one with God, and ſo is it with a righteous man. The manner of death maketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt the matter of ſaluation. Chriſts Ieſus ſpeakes comfortably and verie directly to this purpoſe, vnto his Apoſtles and diſciples, and ſo vnto all true Chriſtians: You ſhall be betraid of your brethren,<note place="margin">Luk. 21.16.17.18.19.</note> and kinſmen, &amp; friends: &amp; ſome of you they ſhall put to death; ye ſhall be hated of all men, yet there ſhal not one haire of your heads periſh; poſſeſſe your ſoules in patience.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond anſwer concerning the killed.</head>
               <p>It makes the iuſtice of God the more manifeſt vpon the killer. As Salomon ſaid concerning Ioab who had murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:6245:59"/>Abner and Amaſa:<note place="margin">1. King. 2.32.33.</note> The Lord ſhall bring his bloud vpon his owne pate, for he ſlue two men cauſleſſe, and more righteous then he: their bloud ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vpon the head of Ioab. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Habacuck queſtions to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe with God, concerning the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent that were ſlain ſo vniuſtly: O God,<note place="margin">Hab. 1.13.14.15.16.17.</note> ſaith he, thou art of pure eyes and canſt not ſee euill, wherefore doſt thou looke vpon the tranſgreſſours and holdſt thy tongue, when the wicked deuoureth the man that is more righteous the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he? Shal they therfore ſpred forth their net &amp; not ſpare continually to ſlay the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? This is anſwered by the ſame Prophet in the ſame chapter, after this manner: Art not thou ô Lord my God,<note place="margin">12.</note> my holy one? we ſhall not die. O Lord thou haſt ordained them for iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ô God thou haſt eſtabliſhed them for correction. As if he had ſaid, Thou wilt not ſuffer theſe lewd and graceleſſe ones any longer, then vntill thou haſt accompliſhed thy will in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vpon vs, then thy heauy wrath ſhall conſume them. Saint Luke affirmes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatiuely
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:6245:60"/>the ſame after this maner: Shall not God auenge his elect which crie day and night vnto him?<note place="margin">Luk. 18.7.8.</note> though he ſuffer long, I tell you he will auenge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quickly. As Chriſt ſaid concerning the man that was borne blind,<note place="margin">Ioh. 9.1.2.</note> It was not his ſinne, nor his parents, but that the worke of God might be ſeene: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo theſe whom the monſters of the world do kill and deſtroy, is not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of that which they pertinently or properly haue deſerued, but that the iuſtice and vengeance of God might be ſeene iuſt vpon ſuch as kill them. There are many wayes and diuers manners by the which the deare children of God do depart this life, but no way nor manner can preuent their preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to die well, how ſudden and how vnuſuall ſoeuer it ſeemes to be vnto others. And ſeeing the caſe ſo ſtandeth, let all men beware of raſh iudgement, and vncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable cenſuring of ſuch as are ſlaine. Let the manner of death be rather an occaſion to forewarn others to be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die alſo, as not knowing the time, nor the manner of death. It is commonly
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:6245:60"/>alike, both to the iuſt and to the vniuſt for the outward manner of death, but the inward is nothing ſo nor ſo. As we may reade of the two theeues, the one vpon the right hand,<note place="margin">Mat. 27.38</note> the other vpon the left hand of Chriſt: the outward maner of their death was alike, but the inward was not ſo; for the one died faithfull, and therfore Chriſt ſaid, This day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe: the other being vnpenitent inwardly went vnto the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned. Againe, the ſuffering or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of God is alway the meanes of his ſecret decree: no man can kill ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, no not iniure his brother in the leaſt meaſure, but by the will of God; becauſe no ſinne can be committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will: nor any otherwiſe will God permit and ſuffer a ſinner to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, then in that maner, &amp; ſo far forth as may ſtand well with his diuine pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: &amp; yet for all that, ſuch a will, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and permiſſion of his, cannot be ſaid to be the immediate cauſe of ſuch an outrage or iniurie done howſoeuer; but rather out of mans will, who for his owne part reſpects not the fulfilling of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:6245:61"/>Gods will ſo much as his owne, which proceedeth from his corrupt nature being inuegled by the diuel. And when as almightie God doth withdraw his helpes, his gifts and graces, (which he may, becauſe properly they are his owne,<note place="margin">Ezod 7.4.</note>) thence it is ſaid, that God har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened the heart of Pharaoh; &amp; that Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hon king of Heſhbon would not let Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael paſſe by,<note place="margin">Deut. 2.30.</note> for the Lord had hardned his ſpirit and his heart. Further, it muſt be granted, that almighty God might verie well, and moſt fitly, if he would, haue reſtrained and withholden that murther and ſhedding of innocent bloud, and ſo the wrong and killing of other his Saints; but it was not his wil, it pleaſed him not ſo to do, he foreſees it not to be for his honor, and a further good. As may plainly be euidenced by a ſpeciall difference betweene the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of God, and Gods election: for it is certaine that election was before the purpoſe of God to ſaluation or damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe in election there is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will of God, without regard either of good or euill to be found in man, or
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:6245:61"/>before he had done either good or euil. The concurrence and the proſecution whereof ſtands in theſe three moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſeuerations of the Almightie, the firſt being vocation, the ſecond iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and the third glorification. To which effect and purpoſe the holy man Dauid being preuented of his murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring mind, ſaid with all holy conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; gladſomneſſe:<note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.33.</note> Bleſſed art thou which haſt kept me this day from ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding innocent blond.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth manner, ſort or kind of death, to wit, politicall.</head>
               <p>In the diſcourſe wherof there will ariſe many dolefull queſtions, with croſſe and contrarie obiections, made by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which are perplexed, ſome for their ſonnes, ſome for their daughters, ſome for their deare &amp; familiar friends, ſome for their wiues, and ſome for their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, who before their faces were cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly executed vnto death; which pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of theirs, do attribute the ſame vnto the rigour of law, or vnto the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt proceedings of law, or at leaſt vnto
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:6245:62"/>the cruell executioners of law. For the remouing of all which vniuſt imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as alſo for the comforting of all ſuch ſorowfull ſoules, I will deliuer ſo particularly, ſo plainely, and ſo directly, my mind &amp; my knowledge therein, as I hope through Gods mercy ſhall ſtand them in good ſtead for perſwaſion and ſatisfaction in this manner and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt, what the lawes ought to be in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall in a well gouerned kingdome.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly, what the lawes now are in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall inthis our glorious and ſo ſelected a kingdome.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thirdly, what the law politick in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar is in this kingdome for the complainants inſtanced.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Firſt concerning the lawes in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall how they ought to be.</head>
               <p>The lawes of all well gouerned king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes ought to be grounded vpon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine intentions, and peaceable ends, conſiſting of iuriſdiction, regall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out partiality, and of a ciuill policy without corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the nouriſhing
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:6245:62"/>and vpholding of ſpiritual iuriſdiction, tending to the religious worſhip of God, and the mutuall ſociety amongſt brethren, which is indeede rightly rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned to be the ſumme of the morall law of Moſes, and the chiefeſt reſpect of our common lawes. The princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of all which lawes alſo are to haue their fit, their conuenient &amp; their war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable application, and denommati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, firſt to the glorie of the bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, ſecondly to the honor of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Maieſtie of the King; thirdly to the reuerent regard of his or their ſubſtitutes: and fourthly to the good of the people in publicke, according as times, places &amp; perſons ſhall vrge their importunities; ſtill inferring and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending rules of iuſtice and equitie, thereby making an euident difference betwixt the plaintiffe &amp; the defendant, and betwixt the iuſt and vniuſt, becauſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarieties being layd together, makes iuſtice to appeare the more iuſt, and the ſame law to be the more commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and vnrepealable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:6245:63"/>
               <head>Secondly, concerning the common lawes as they are now in England.</head>
               <p>This little Iſle of England, and Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne ſide of the world, of which the great Prophet Ezechiel ſpeakes in ſome particular,<note place="margin">Chap. 38.2.3.4.5.6.15.</note> hath bene more anciently endued with Gods particular fauors, then any other part elſe of the whole world, for matter of his Maieſties reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſeruice, and for matter of ciuill gouernement, in this land now moſt graciouſly eſtabliſhed. All which law is full of profound maturitie, full of needfull iuſtice, and full of druine well ordered policies. And wheras other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions round about this realme through their owne homebread mutinies, and forren deuaſtations, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not preſcribe by any record, cuſtome, or memorie of man, by what law, iuſtice or equitie, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then by the law of nature, which is common amongſt heathens, that they do execute any malefactor, or inflict a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pecuniarie puniſhment, almightie God out of his infinite prouidence and mercie, although that many times reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:6245:63"/>through the corrupt iudgement of Kings and Queenes of this land, &amp; the manifold ſinnes of the people there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, were ſometimes altered, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times quite ouerthrowne: yet our common lawes were ſtill maintained, and extolled euen vnto this day. All which lawes had they not excelled the lawes of other nations, they could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue continued without extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhment, without impeachment, or at leaſt, without ſome anullity, &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like indignity by the Kings of the Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, or by the Kings of the Saxons, or by the Kings of the Danes, or by the Kings of the Normans; euery of which men were verie wiſe, verie politicke, verie religious, and moſt admirably va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous: which Kings immediatly ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded one another, euer ſince this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land was firſt found habitable. In all whoſe times theſe our ſaid lawes ſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, and by many neceſſarie additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were publickly enlarged. Againe, had not theſe our common lawes bene euerie way beſitting the maintenance of Gods ſacred and true religion, and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:6245:64"/>for the preſeruation of peace; as alſo by all former ages, ſince the confuſion of tongues, left vnto our dayes and times vncontrollable, &amp; vnrepealable; then without all queſtion, ſome one or other of our godly Kings or Queenes would haue eſtabliſhed other lawes, or elſe would haue in ſome ſort reformed them. But by reaſon of the great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplication of this nation, and through ſome diſorders likely to accrue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſo many, who would in time croſſe and contrarie the true meaning of thoſe lawes, our renowned Princes haue onely repealed ſome few ſtatutes, and in ſtead thereof haue enacted o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to better purpoſe, as neceſſarily was required: alway with this prudent prouiſo, that no law nor ſtatute ſhould be in ſence and intendement but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rules and former pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns, which they had receiued from former ages, tending to the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and the peace of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. So did Alfred a famous King of the Saxons, in the yeare of our Lord 880. adde vnto theſe lawes, holy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:6245:64"/>and ſtatutes, namely againſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge, againſt the violating of the Sabboth, againſt treaſon, &amp; againſt the immodeſt and vnchaſt touching of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother mans wife or daughter: all which facts were euen then held to be moſt vile, moſt odious, and moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable; and yet for all that euen then were they moſt likely to haue bin com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by many irreligious perſons. So in like manner Caeſar the Emperor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the incarnation of Chriſt, by an eſtabliſhed law brought that wife with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of petty treaſon, which was found guilty for betraying the life of her husband, and to be burned for the ſame. So likewiſe the ſonne that did betray his father, and the ſeruant that betrayed his maſter, ſhould be hanged for the ſame as petty traytors: all which well contriued lawes are in force vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this day, bleſſed be the Maieſtie of God for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:6245:65"/>
               <head>Thirdly concerning the politicall law, which is a chiefe part of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law: whence indeede ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the matter inſtanced.</head>
               <p>The politicall law is that by vertue whereof malefactors are iudicially ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted vnto death, vpon publicke tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als and arraignment, by witneſſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, and then by the verdict of 12. ſubſtantiall honeſt ſworne men. The common law, whereof I haue ſpoken, doth conſiſt of a law Regall, and a law politicall, both which were in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt many yeares before Chriſt was borne. This law Regall is ſaid to be grounded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuers ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cuſtomes, rules and orders, drawne out of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall law, or as it may be ſaid, out of the will of the King, be it good or euil, which is effected by his auctoritie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſubiects. The political law is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a branch principall, and a meanes ſpeciall of that by the which the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall policie of the Church is royally maintained and ſupported, and which is in very deed the life of the regall law.
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:6245:65"/>As the iudiciall law of Moſes was the coniunct and the inſeparable compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the morall law amongſt the people of Iſrael: ſo in like manner the politicall law may be ſaid to be arteries and ligaments of the common lawes amongſt vs here in England. As if it were to ſay, Where there is no political law wiſely and mercifully contriued, there is no regall law that can be vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden and maintained; take away the one, take away the other. A king I grant may gouerne regally, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his will may enforce his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects vnto obedience, or patience: yet without Chriſtian policie no king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome can continue. For the order and frame of ciuill gouernment is broken, if men may not poſſeſſe their owne in peace after a peculiar propertie: ſo is it if men may nor be in their owne houſes ſafely: ſo is it if men me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may not trauel without danger of robberie: ſo is it if men may not haue the free vſe of the Sabboths by an ingreſſe and egreſſe for the ſeruice of God, according to an vniform order throughout the Realm.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:6245:66"/>This I conclude: We being defended by the kings lawes from all iniuries, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate and publike throughout his domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and alſo hauing vnder his prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the peaceble profeſſion of Ieſus Chriſt, in effect then, Let vs ſubiect our ſelues vnto him as vnto the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Vicar or Deputie of the King of heauen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The politicall law hath in it ſelfe theſe foure ſorts or kinds of executions.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Beheadding.</item>
                  <item>2. Hanging.</item>
                  <item>3. Burning.</item>
                  <item>4. Preſſing.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Firſt, the reaſon of this politicall law in generall, or the cauſe why it hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bene held requiſite and neceſſarie in euerie wel-gouerned kingdome; it is occaſioned or drawne from the foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and moſt outragiouſneſſe of ſome mens nature, breaking forth into an hatefull kind of demeanour towards their equals, and a treacherous manner of behauiour againſt their ſuperiours; euermore and in all places, preferring
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:6245:66"/>contentions and warres, before quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and peace, liking and allowing in their corrupt iudgment, deceit, and rapine, before truth and plain-dealing: ſtill preſſing themſelues vnto the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonour of God, and vnto treaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the king; if it may carry any hope of profite, or likelihood of pleaſure. And therefore haue need of ſuch law as may reſtraine all ſuch, or if they will not be ſo reſtrained, then without all partialitie to execute them. The morall law of God, &amp; the common law of this land, do onely manifeſt and perſwade with men what things ought to be done. But the politicall law, as the law judiciall, doth enforce and violently preſſe men to the performance of that which ought to be done. Of which ſort of people Saint Paul ſpeaketh, as of the Romans,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.31.</note> Though they knew the law of God, that they which do ſuch things are worthie of death, yet not onely do the ſame, but fauour them that do it. This kind of law may be truly ſaid to be the law of nature, to wit, a law com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all people; where yet the law of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:6245:67"/>God is not in force, and duly executed, they are a law vnto themſelues. To be briefe, the politicall law is an execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner of the common law, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a cauſe principall and neceſſarie to haue it, and to keepe it in vſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Secondly, the reaſon of ſuch ſundrie ſorts and ſeuerall manners of execution, which are vſed by vertue of the politicall law.</head>
               <p>The manner, ſort, or kind of execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting malefactors worthily deſeruing the ſame, is not to be found in the grounds of the common law, nor in any branch thereof; but alway hath bin held as a matter indifferent, and to be publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and maintained according to the pleaſure of the Prince for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſpecially as the manners of their ſubiects did enduce him thereunto by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of the hainouſneſſe of the fact either more or leſſe: as we find by the order and maner of Moſes in his gouernment, which muſt needs be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood to be figuratiuely related to all other kings and people, as well as to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:6245:67"/>the people of Iſrael; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they ſhould deriue the ſubſtance of their politicke lawes to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſting of iuſtice &amp; equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: and alway vſing the maner, the ſort, and kind thereof, as being a matter of circumſtance, according to their owne wils, as time, place, and perſons require. As for example briefly, The iudiciall law for him that ſtole an oxe was,<note place="margin">Exo. 22.1.2</note> that he ſhould recompence it to the owner with fiue oxen. Some kings puniſh ſuch an offence with ſtocking &amp; whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, ſome do puniſh it with baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and our kings for many hundred yeares together haue puniſhed it with hanging. As for murther, it was euer &amp; in all places puniſhed with death, and yet the manner of the death ſtill remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the will of the king, according as the maner of the murther was found to be either more or leſſe hainous. The Iudiciall lawes of Iſrael were ſaid to be appertaining vnto them, and therefore can they not be ſaid to be broken by vs when as indeed they were neuer giuen vnto vs, neither yet made for vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:6245:68"/>
               <head>This doctrine ſerueth to reproue foure ſorts of people. The</head>
               <p>Firſt are thoſe, whoſe nature is ſo fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and ſo rebellious, that they are no way to be gouerned and guided but by force and violence: yeelding rather their obedience and loyaltie to man &amp; that onely for feare of puniſhment, then vnto almightie God for the loue of his fauour.</p>
               <p>Secondly, thoſe who do moſt vniuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and moſt maliciouſly maligne the reuerend and commendable ſtudents of the law, and generally all the learned and graue profeſſors thereof; being drawne thereunto out of their extreme folly and palpable ignorance: or elſe being conuicted vniuſtly in the triall of ſome caſe, through their owne wrong information, or want of meanes iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to follow it: or otherwiſe, hauing had the ouerthrow and conuiction, as iuſtly they deſerued, by reaſon of the vnlawfulneſſe and vniuſtneſſe of their caſe, being plaintiffe or defendant.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, thoſe who do vtterly ſcorne
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:6245:68"/>and altogether diſdaine the verie law it ſelfe. And no maruell, for commonly they are ſuch as do mocke and ſcorne the maieſtie of Gods holy Scriptures, and all the ſincere Preachers thereof; drawne thereunto, as may be thought, by a turne ſicke ſpirit of giddineſſe, or rather from the ſtirring of the diuell, who can away with nothing which is better then himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, thoſe who moſt vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably, and without all Chriſtian reaſon or good conſideration, do make que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion and doubt of their ſaluation, who are iudicially executed for their vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full actes. As though the manner of death did any thing at all derogate from the matter and ſubſtance of faith, which is required of euerie one that dieth howſoeuer. Or as though he that ſtealeth, or he that murthereth, or he that is a traitor, were a greater ſinner then Chriſt would or could forgiue; or elſe as though that they which die na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally in their beds, or they themſelues which liue in the good appearance of the world, were not as guiltie of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:6245:69"/>for euery ſmall ſinne which they commit, without faith in Ieſus Chriſt, as they who are hanged, burned, beheadded or preſſed, or as thoſe vpon whom the tower of Siloam fell.</p>
               <p>Here I conclude, asking pardon of the learned, wherein ſoeuer I haue er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or haue wanted in the diſconiſe of the common lawes of this land. Knew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the profunditie thereof to be paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the reach of all men: and withall, acknowledging it to be a meere ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect out of my element; and therefore as a man hauing ſpoken nothing in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of that which it deferueth, I am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned without replica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a <hi>nihil dicit,</hi> if reaſon require it</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third inſtruction concerning the timelineſſe of death.</head>
               <p>Not withſtanding there are ſuch va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable and ſundry ſorts or manners of death, as hath bene formerly enlarged; and howſoeuer almightie God hath bene occaſioned in his iuſtice to puniſh ſinne: yet none of the generation of mankinde departs this life before his
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:6245:69"/>appointed day, ſo that no man by dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence can lengthen his life, nor any man by negligence ſhorten his life. The holy Prophet Dauid hauing Saul his enemie in his hand, would not be perſwaded to lay his hands on him, but ſaid, His day ſhall come to die,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.8.9.</note> I will not ſmite him. As if he had ſpoken more plainely, It is not for me to kill him, for God hath appointed him his time, in which he ſhall die. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſaid the iuſt man Iob by way of two interrogations,<note place="margin">Iob. 7.1.</note> Is there not an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time for man vpon the earth? And are not his dayes determined?<note place="margin">Iob. 14.5.</note> The number of his moneths are with thee, thou haſt appointed him his bounds o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer which he ſhall not paſſe. As if it were to ſay, Certainely there is an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time for mans departure out of this world, euen by the diuine ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance &amp; ſacred decree of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which cannot be ſhortened nor lengthned, no not ſo much time more as to go ouer a meere or baulke, nor ſo much time leſſe as to come vnto it. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine he ſaith verie emphatically and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:6245:70"/>affirmatiuely, beleeuing in the promiſe of God therin, after this manner, I will waite my appointed time: as though he had ſaid,<note place="margin">Iob. 14.14.</note> My God hath determined and ſet downe the day, and houre of my diſſolution: it is hid from me, I will therefore attend, I will be looking for it from day to day. Salomon after his conuerſion, amongſt many excellent &amp; moſt diuine inſtructions, he particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth this ſecret decree of God moſt plainly after this manner:<note place="margin">Eccl. 3.12.</note> To all things there is an appointed time. And from this generall he deſcendeth into a more particular, thus: There is a time to be borne, and a time to die; to wit, as there is a moſt certaine time incloſed in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry womans wombe, in which ſhe ſhall bring forth into the world: euen ſo there is a certaine and an appointed time, in which he that is borne of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhall go out of the world. Saint Paul ſaid to the Athenians,<note place="margin">Act. 17.26.</note> God hath aſſigned the times that were ordained before, and the bounds of their habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. By that ſaying the time of mans departure is decreed, and vnreapeable:
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:6245:70"/>why? becauſe there is no alteration nor change in Gods diuine Maieſtie; that which he is, he was, &amp; the ſame he will be for euer. Iehoida ſaid,<note place="margin">2 King. 11.15.</note> He that comes within the ranges, let him die the death: euen ſo it may be ſaid, Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer comes within the compaſſe of the time which God hath decreed, let him die without delay; there is no hope nor helpe for him, there will be no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality or fauourable reſpects. The liues of the 10.<note place="margin">Gen. 5.3. to the end.</note> Fathers were twiſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly reckoned, and their death once, for diuers cauſes, but ſpecially that thereby euerie man thenceforth might be able to know the age of the old world before the floud. The ages of theſe holy men being computated and layd together, do amount iuſtly to 1656. yeares. In which obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance or ſure rule for numeration, and multiplication, the holy Ghoſt deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth plainely, that God doth ſtrictly &amp; ſeuerely recken the liues of all men, yea from their verie beginning to the verie day of their death. Saint Iohn and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſts affirme out of their
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:6245:71"/>owne knowledge, that the Iewes vſed all cunning meanes, &amp; practiſed diuers wayes to apprehend our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour; but all was in vaine, ſomething or other went betweene: and why? his houre was not yet come,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.30.</note> the time which his holy Father had decreed was not when they would. To this effect Moſes by a large meaſure of inſpiration ſpake of an holy woman, the wife of the Patriarch Abraham, who had a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and gracious reſpect before God, ſpecially for the time of her life, &amp; the time of her death.<note place="margin">Gen. 23.1.2</note> When Sarah, ſaith he, was 127. yeares old, ſo long liued ſhee, then Sarah died. That is as much to ſay, Shee liued iuſt ſo long in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede and no whit longer; when her appointed time was come, then ſhe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and not before. Likewiſe Moſes doth computate the age of Abraham her husband and ſaith,<note place="margin">Gen. 25.7.</note> This is the age of Abrahams life which he liued, 175. yeares. Then Abraham yeelded the ſpirit, &amp; died in a good age. As if he had ſaid, This 175. yeares was the full time in which God had appointed him to
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:6245:71"/>liue. When as Moſes himſelfe was to depart this life, almightie God called him ſaying, Thy dayes are come,<note place="margin">Deu. 31.14.</note> thou muſt die: to wit, my decree is certaine towards thee my louing and my faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruant, as towards all the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of mankinde. As in an hoaſt of men furiouſly in fight, ſo in the world ſome ſhall die now, becauſe God hath ſo appointed; and ſome ſhall not die then, becauſe God hath not ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. To which effect he ſpake by the mouth of his Prophet,<note place="margin">Eze. 9.4.5.6.</note> Set a marke vpon the foreheads of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that mourne. And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning others he ſaid vnto him, Go and ſmite, deſtroy vtterly the old and the young.<note place="margin">Gen. 4.15.</note> (So likewiſe God was ſaid to ſet a marke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Caine) but touch no man, vpon whom the marke is ſet: ſhewing therein that euen amongſt fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and outragious men, in martiall affaires, and in the determinations of malicious men, life and death, is euen then particularly in Gods hands, and alſo the verie time thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here ariſe two neceſſary queſtions. One, why hath God ſo exactly determined the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:6245:72"/>time of death: the other, why God doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale the time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt whereof is: Why hath God ſo exactly determined the verie time of euery mans departure out of this world, ſo that no man can go beyond it, nor come ſhort of it? Why did he not rather reſolue vpon this, Let euery man ſhift for himſelfe, and liue ſo long as he can?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The anſwer or reaſon is fourefold.</head>
               <p>The firſt reaſon thereof is to declare, that he is the principall maiſter of times, and according to his diuine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce he is an exact performer of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes through all ages of the world. He obſerues the time when a man comes into the world, and when he goeth out of the world. The Maieſtie of this eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall God conſiderately and renowned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beginneth ſamous actions, and ends them memorably by periods &amp; places full of weighty conſideration, accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the yeares of holy men.<note place="margin">Gen. 5. Gen. 1. to Gen. 7. Gen. 8 to Gen. 12. Gen. 12. to Exod. 19. Exo. 12. to Ioſ. 1. Ioſ. 1. to Iudg. 1. Iudg. 1. to 1 Sam. 1. 1 Sam. 1. to Nehe. 1. Nehe. Eſra. Heſter. Daniel.</note> As by the liues and deathes of the firſt ten ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fathers, how many yeares there was
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:6245:72"/>from the creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the floud: viz. 1656 yeares. From the floud to the promiſe made to Abraham, 427. yeares. From the promiſe to the giuing of the law, 430 yeares. From their going out of Egypt to their entrance into Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, 40. yeares. From their entrance into Canaan to their quiet poſſeſſion, 7. yeares. From thence to Saul the firſt King, 450. yeares. Thence to their cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity in Babylon, 490 yeares. From their captiuity to their reſtoring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, to build the Temple at Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, 70. yeares. From thence to their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall libertie by Chriſt Ieſus, 490 yeares. Almighty God is ſo ſeuere and ſo ſoueraigne an obſeruer of time for the beginning &amp; ending of all famous actions, and ſpecially the coming of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the world, and his going out, that he ſtandeth vpon the performance of his word and promiſe euen to a day. Moſes ſpeaking of the Egyptian capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity ſaid,<note place="margin">Exo. 12.41.</note> that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 430. yeares were expired, euen the ſelfeſame day depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all the hoaſt of the Lord out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt. Yea and farther his Maieſtie ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:6245:73"/>the verie name of the day, in which he doth performe his word and promiſe, as he ſpeaketh plainely by his Prophet.<note place="margin">Eze. 14.1.2.</note> Sonne of man, ſaith he, write the name of the day, euen of this ſame day, for the King of Babell ſet himſelfe againſt Ieruſalem the ſelfeſame day. So God ordereth all things in meaſure,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 11.17.</note> in mumber, and weight.</p>
               <p>The ſecond tenne holy Fathers in whom it pleaſed God to multiplie a new Church after the floud,<note place="margin">Gen. 11.10. to the end.</note> are exactly accounted by euerie full yeare in which they liued, according to the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate will of God, and that for diuers cauſes, but ſpecially to declare that the life of man is not at randome nor at ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. And here alſo obſerue, that at the floud the ages of men were halfed, as may appeare by the ages of thoſe holy men, who liued not aboue halfe ſo long as they liued before the floud. Againe the fame age was halfed at the building of Babel; againe it was halfed vpon the going of Iſrael out of Egypt. And at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of theſe ages his holy Maieſty had a ſpeciall hand, that neither the one
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:6245:73"/>nor the other, good nor bad, ſhould haue either more or leſſe then was in his will. As of theſe holy men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and immediatly after the flood, ſo withall God computates the ages verie directly of all and euerie of the twelue Patriarchs:<note place="margin">Gen. 49.50.</note> alſo how long euery Iudge of Iſrael hued, and how long euerie oppreſſor was to liue. He alſo kept a regiſter and did diumely chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolize the age of euerie king, and how long he did reigne in Iſrael and in Iuda, as may be ſound in euerie of their ſtories.<note place="margin">Dan. 1.2.3.4.5.</note> The ſeuentie yeares captiuitie was ended exactly vpon the particular death of three kings, to wit, Nebucad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar who liued 45. yeares, Euilmero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech who liued 22. yeares, and Balta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhar who liued three yeares, neither one day more, nor one day leſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond anſwer or reaſon concerning the timelineſſe of death, to wit, why God hath ſo exactly determined it.</head>
               <p>It is to ſet foorth the incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibleneſſe of Gods wiſedome and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:6245:74"/>in that he doth gouerne all the generation of mankind through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the world, as one common weale, or as one priuate family, or as if it were one particular perſon, regiſtring and chronolizing euerie man by his name, by the place of his habitation, by the manner of his conuerſation, and by the time ſpecially of his departure out of this life, as a wiſe maiſter of a familie, taking in ſome, &amp; letting others forth. So did Ahaſhuerus the king of Perſia put forth Vaſthi,<note place="margin">Heſt. 1.19.</note> and tooke in Heſter: ſo doth the Maieſtie of God in due time take in ſome into the world, and lets others depart.<note place="margin">1. King. 10. 1. to 11.</note> The Queene of Sheba hearing of the maruellous wiſedome of Salomon for the ordering and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his houſe and kingdome, came from farre to ſee and to heare more therof: after the which ſhe ſaid, Happy are theſe thy ſeruants which ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee to heare thy wiſedome. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold here, faith the holy Ghoſt, a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then Salomon, to wit, a God more admirable then Salomon for his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment in Church and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale.
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:6245:74"/>The holy Prophet Dauid entring into ſome conſideration of his maruellous Maieſtie, concludes moſt admirably of it, ſaying; O Lord our gouernour, how wonderfull art thou in all thy workes! thy knowledg is too wonderful for me,<note place="margin">Pſal. 139.1.</note> I cannot attaine vnto it. Ezra ſaid, that God numbred all the veſſels that were to be returned from Babylon to Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem euen vnto the meaneſt ſort.<note place="margin">Ezra, 1.7.8.</note> And he doth account the people euen by their names, and by the names of their fathers: intimating thereby,<note place="margin">Ezech. 9.7.</note> that none went to Babylon, but ſuch, and ſo many as had receiued his expreſſe name; nor any that were to returne, but ſuch as he had reſerued to build the Temple, and to reedifie the wals of the citie, and to plant the religion of their fathers. Gods wiſedome and prouidence is innarra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and infinite, euen to a ſparrow.<note place="margin">Luk. 12.6.</note> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas and Paul ſaid,<note place="margin">Act. 15.18.</note> From the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world God knew his workes. Moſes, to the end he might fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten the ſure knowledge, and the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance therof in the harts of the people of Iſrael, ſaid; Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:6245:75"/>the dayes of old,<note place="margin">Deu. 32.7.8</note> aske thy father, and he will ſhew thee, thine elders, and they will tel thee. When the moſt high God deuided the nations their inheritance, when he ſeparated the ſons of Adam, he appointed the borders of the people according to their number.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third anſwer or reaſon concerning the timelineſſe of death, why God hath ſo exactly determined vpon the ſame.</head>
               <p>It is to manifeſt the prerogatiue, the priuiledge, and ſupremacy that his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mareſty hath, and holdeth ouer all principahties and powers, captiuating and ſubduing them, and all the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man, to the obedience of his will, that neither the one nor the other can poſſibly lengthen or ſhorten his own life, much leſſe the life of another. As a king that is to gouern a kingdom, muſt be powerful and ſeuere in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of inſtice againſt the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and readie to miniſter mercie to the needie and diſtreſſed: euen ſo the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of this eternall King, hauing the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:6245:75"/>whole world to guide and to gouerne, muſt be powerful and ſeuere. To which effect he faith by his Prophet Ier emie, Feare ye not him, faith he,<note place="margin">Ier. 5.22.</note> who hath placed the ſand for the bounds of the ſea by a perpetuall decree that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not paſſe? Againe he ſaid, Cannot I do with you ò Iſrael, as this Potter?<note place="margin">Ier. 18.6.</note> The holy Prophet Ezekiel ſpeaking of his predomina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t power ouer the wicked faith after this manner;<note place="margin">Ezech. 6.7.</note> I will take the bloud out of his mouth, &amp; his abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt his teeth. The ſame prerogatiue our Sauiour Chriſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſteth himſelfe to haue in his ſpeech to his Diſciples: If any man, ſaith he,<note place="margin">Mar. 11.3.</note> do ſay vnto you, Why looſe ye the Colt? ſay ye vnto them, The Lord hath need, and they will ſtraight way let it go. As if he had ſaid, Do but tell them of me, vſe but my name, and they ſhall haue no power to withſtand you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond queſtion, why God doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale the time of mans departure out of this life?</head>
               <p>Why doth he keepe it ſecret to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe?
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:6245:76"/>This ſeemes to be hard iuſtice, that a matter of ſo great importance ſhould be hid:<note place="margin">Eccl. 9.12.</note> No man knoweth his time, ſaith Salomon, but is ſuddenly taken, as a fiſh or as a bird.<note place="margin">Dan. 12.4.</note> It is ſhut vp and ſealed vnto theend of the time appointed, ſaid Daniel.<note place="margin">Gen. 27.2.</note> I know not the day of my death, ſaid the holy Patriarch Iſaac. And as Saint Luke ſaid to the diſciples con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the reſtoring of Chriſts king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: It is not for you to know the times &amp; ſeaſons which God hath reſcr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in his owne power:<note place="margin">Act. 17.</note> euen ſo is it not for any man to know the time and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his departure out of this life. I conclude this queſtion with the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warning of Saint Paul to Timothie, in theſe words; Put away fooliſh and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned queſtions, knowing that they ingender ſtrife.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>There are three speciall and diuine reaſons why the time of death is concealed.</head>
               <head type="sub">The firſt reaſon is,</head>
               <p>That euerie man ſhould ſtand vpon his guard, leſt the enemie come ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly.
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:6245:76"/>Watch and pray therefore, ſaid our Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus. Saint Luke knowing the manner of death, exhorts to watchfulneſſe in theſe words,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.35.36.37.38.</note> Let your loynes be girded about, and your lights burning, and ye your ſelues like vnto men that wait for their maiſters. God told Moſes where he ſhould die: but he told him not the time: and why? becauſe he, as all other men, ſhould ſtand vpon his watch or guard.<note place="margin">Deu. 28.66</note> Thy life ſaith the Lord ſhall hang before thee, and thou ſhalt feare both day and night, and ſhalt haue none aſſurance of thy life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond reaſon why the time of death is concealed.</head>
               <p>It is for the continuall good of all ſucceeding ages, that the one ought to prouide for the other. Therefore ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally it is ſaid by Salomon,<note place="margin">Eccl. 1.4.</note> One genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion paſſeth, and another cometh: as of heauenly, ſo in ſome proportion of earthly, which made Chriſt to ſay, One ſoweth, and another reapeth.<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.37.</note> Were it that ſome might know the time of
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:6245:77"/>their departure, they would not renue any thing that might be for them that ſhould come after, partly through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and enuie, and partly through extreme idleneſſe, or ſuperfluous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third reaſon why the time of death is concealed.</head>
               <p>That all men ſhould carefully &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently vſe the meanes for life which God hath appointed in his Church. Whereas if they knew the exact time of their departure, they wold hold it fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous to vſe any of thoſe good means which his holy Maieſty hath inſerted &amp; annexed to the decree for the time of mans departure. So ſhould the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God concerning the vſe of his creatures be made fruſtrate, and thoſe his exceeding good creatures ſtand of none effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth reaſon why the time of death is concealed.</head>
               <p>If the time of death were knowne to ſome, they would liue very deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:6245:77"/>and damnably for many yeares: and the more neare to the time of their death, they would grow the more ſad, ſorowfull, and heauy, and into ſuch intollerable paſſions, as would driue them into deſperation, or at leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an vnwilling and a moſt graceleſſe ſtriuing with death, &amp; in a ſort againſt God himſelfe. Therefore Moſes ſaid,<note place="margin">Deu. 29.29</note> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret things belong to the Lord our God, but the thing reuealed belong vnto vs and to our children for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beſides theſe two queſtions which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly you haue heard, there ariſe out of this doctrine concerning the timelineſſe of death, three obiections.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, if God haue ſo reſolutely decreed vpon the verie day and houre of euery mans departure: To what end ſhall a man vſe indeuor or any of the beſt meanes for the preſeruation of life?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt anſwer for the vſe of meanes to preſerue life.</head>
               <p>As almightie God hath decreed the time of death: ſo withall he hath an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, and commanded religious and
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:6245:78"/>pertinent meanes for the preſeruation of life, vntill the time come. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, The people vnder Moſes and Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might haue periſhed in a naturall contagion of the leproſie; therefore God comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that the whole might be ſingled and ſeuered from the ſicke and infected.<note place="margin">Leuit. 13.1.2.3.4.</note> The ſame people might haue bene deſtroyed in the iudgment which God had prepared for others; therefore God commanded ſome, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Separate your ſelues from the tents of Corah,<note place="margin">Numb. 16.1.2. 2 King. 10.23.</note> Dathan and Abiram. Iehu the King ſaid, Search &amp; ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be any of the Lords ſeruants amongſt the ſeruants of Baall, leſt they be alſo deſtroyed with them. Good men may periſh in the outrage of the wicked,<note place="margin">Mat. 2.12.13.</note> therefore God forewarned the wiſe men to depart home another way. And Saul ſaid to the Kenites,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.6.</note> Depart from amongſt the Amalekits, leſt I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy you with them.</p>
               <p>That vertuous woman ſo highly in the fauor of God, might haue bene fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed in that ſeuen yeares of dearth,<note place="margin">2 Kings 10.23.</note> had not God forewarned her by his
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:6245:78"/>Prophet, that ſhe ſhould ſhift for her ſelfe and her houſhold in due time.</p>
               <p>All men, by the iuſtice of God for their ſinne, might lawfully be deſtroyed together in this or that plague or ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance: yet he hath in his mercie fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned ſome, and ſo doth, to ſaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the vſe of meanes which he hath commended and commanded in his Church. And withall in the vſe of the ſame meanes, or the like, to preſerue very reprobates fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the plagues which falle vpon their fellowes, to the end they may liue vnto the time which he hath decreed for their death, in which their ſinnes will be full ripe. As may appeare in the foure recited examples.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond anſwer for the vſe of means to preſerue life,</head>
               <p>Is the practiſe of holy men who were moued by the Spirit of inſpiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as of Dauid the King and Prophet, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had the word and promiſe of Almightie God, for victorie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Philiſtins; yet he knowing the right rule of Gods will in his word,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:6245:79"/>and promiſe, determined with himſelfe to vſe warlike meanes, and therefore came vpon them valiantly with an ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum from the mulberrie trees.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 5.25.24.</note> So did Gedeon politickly and valiantly come vpon the Midianites with his 300. men only,<note place="margin">Iudg 7.16.17.18.</note> hauing in ſted of ſwords &amp; ſtaues, pitchers and lamps. Ichoiada the prieſt though he did know that his cauſe and his butines was the Lords, yet he gaue commandement vnto the Captaines to vſe ſpeares and ſhields which he gaue them.<note place="margin">2 King 11.10.11.</note> As the ſeruants of Benadab the King ſaid to their maiſter, when they were ouercome by the King of Iſrael, We haue heard that the Kings of Iſrael are mercifull,<note place="margin">1 King. 20.31.</note> we pray thee let vs put on ſackcloth about our loynes, and ropes about our necks, and let vs go to the King of Iſrael, it may be he will ſaue thy life: So likewiſe, we muſt all conclude and agree for the vſe of all kind, ſorts &amp; manners of good meanes; who can tell whether the Lord our King and our God will ſaue vs in the vſe of meanes or not? As Daniel ſaid to his keeper,<note place="margin">Da. 1.12.</note> Proue vs ten dayes, let vs
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:6245:79"/>haue pulſe to eate, &amp; water to drinke: ſo in like maner let vs ſay to our ſelues, and to whom elſe ſoeuer, Proue the meanes, trie what God vouchſaſeth to do thereby. Although Saint Paul knew that neither he nor any one of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ſhould periſh in that dangerous voiage, yet he ſaid vnto the mariners, Except theſe tarie in the ſhip,<note place="margin">Act. 27.23. to 52.</note> they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaued; as if he had ſaid, We and they haue one meanes of life, let vs vſe it, and God will giue good iſſue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Saint Paul alſo knew by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of inſpiration and by the reueiled word of God, that no man ſhould die before his day, yet he commanded Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motheus to vſe wine for his ſtomacke ſake, and his often infirmities.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.23.</note> As the Gibeonites being leaft-handed vſed to ſling ſtones, whereby they became ſo skilfull that they could ſling at an haire and not faile:<note place="margin">Iud. 20.16.</note> euen ſo Gods people are to be ſo skilfull in the vſe of meanes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the leaſt to the greateſt, that they may preſerue life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:6245:80"/>
               <head>The third anſwer for the vſe and meanes to preſerue life,</head>
               <p>Is proued by the practiſe alſo of holy women, as that vertuous woman of Tekoha,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 14.14.</note> who importunately intreated King Dauid for the life of Abſalon his ſonne. The Shunamitiſh woman being of great eſtimation, and hauing her onely ſonne dead,<note place="margin">2 King. 18.19.20.</note> moſt labouriouſly vſed the helpe of Eliſha the Prophet, if it were poſſible, to haue him reſtored to life. As the inhabitants of Gibea, though they were leaft-handed,<note place="margin">Iudg. 20.16.</note> could ſling a ſtone at an haires breadth, and faile not: euen ſo muſt Gods children, labor to be skilfull in the vſe of al good meanes for the preſeruation of life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth anſwer for the vſe of meanes to preſerue life,</head>
               <p>Is the practiſe of almightie God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who vſually doth annexe the vſe of meanes with his decree concerning the time, as well for the deſtroying of life, as for the preſeruing of life: whereby the one be not ſhorter, nor the other
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:6245:80"/>longer. Sometimes he vſeth weake or ſmall meanes to bring mightie things to paſſe, and that for the manifeſtation of his mercy, and readineſſe, for the chearing vp of ſuch as were weake, and miſerable:<note place="margin">2 Cro. 14.11.</note> as Aſa the King of Iudah ſaid in his prayers vnto God. being mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably diſtreſſed, It is nothing with thee to helpe with many or with no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. Likewiſe Gedeon with his 300 me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſumed vpon the promiſe of God,<note place="margin">Iudg. 7.16.12.18.</note> to giue the onſet to many royall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies at one time of the Midianites. If<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael had victory againſt the Philiſtims,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 13.19.</note> without ſpeare or ſhield. Sometimes God vſeth baſe, or, as it may be ſaid by a phraſe of ſpeech, fooliſh meanes, that thereby he might confound the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the wiſe. So did he command Ioſua to compaſſe the great and inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible citie Ierico ſeuen times,<note place="margin">Ioſua. 16.11. to 8.</note> ſounding out their rams hornes, and with the ſame to throw downe the wals, and to open their gates of iron &amp; braſſe. Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he vſeth miraculous means.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 14.15.</note> There was feare in the hoaſt of the Philiſtims amongſt all the peope, the garriſon alſo
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:6245:81"/>and they that went out to ſpoyle were afraid themſelues: the earth trembled, for it was ſtinken with feare by God He vſeth miraculous meanes for the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of his inexpugnable power, as at the winning of that royall citie of Gibeon,<note place="margin">Ioſua 10.11.12.</note> whereat fine Kings and their armies were diſcomfited in one day. Ioſua being the Lord Generall of Iſrael; whereof ſome with the ſword, ſome with ſtones from heauen. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times his Maieſty vſeth phyſical means, as that plaiſter of figs which Hezechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,<note place="margin">2 King. 20.7.</note> was commanded to take for his plague ſore. Sometimes he worketh the good of his people, euen by no means, as he himſelfe ſaid by the Prophet Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſea: I will not ſaue them by bow,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 1.7.</note> not by ſword, nor by battell, nor by horſes, nor by horſemen; but I will ſaue them by the Lord their God. As if he had ſaid, Naturall &amp; worldly men ſhall not impute the deliuerance of my people vnto poſſible meanes on earth but it ſhall be done beyond all expectation, cleane contrarie to the vſe of reaſon, &amp; beſides the capacity of the moſt wiſe in
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:6245:81"/>the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fifth anſwer for the vſe of meanes to preſerue life.</head>
               <p>There is in euerie man both good &amp; bad by the inſtinct of nature, an intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable affected proneneſſe to vſe all ſorts and all kinds of meanes for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of life, drawne originally from a naturall manner of feare, ſuch as was in Adam, who hauing in his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience deſerued death,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.8.9.10.</note> fled and hid himſelfe. So Caine hauing murthered his brother, durſt not for feare of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment acknowledge his offence, and when ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was pronounced againſt him,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.13.14.</note> he feared death exceedingly which made him to expoſtulate with God in a moſt deſperate manner.<note place="margin">Act. 27.1. to 21.</note> Saint Paul his company in that moſt dangerous voyage, were maruellous fearefull, which made them to labour, and to vſe all meanes poſſibles for their liues. The heathen ſailers with Ionas to Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhis in that great outragious tempeſt,<note place="margin">Ion. 1.1. to 8.</note> ſpared not their beſt commodities, but threw them into the ſea to lighten the ſhip, and laboured innarrably, and all
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:6245:82"/>with the feare of death.</p>
               <p>So in like manner, holy men, ſuch as were indeed the true and ſincere ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God, were touched with this naturall feare, and therewith drawne to vſe all meanes poſſible for helpe and ſafegard of their liues. Ieremie the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet did importune the king after this manner for his life, being drawne into an extraordinarie feare;<note place="margin">Ier 37.20.</note> Now I pray thee ô my Lord the king, let my prayer be accepted before thee, that thou cauſe me not to returne vnto the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, leſt I die there. Likewiſe, Ieſus Chriſt himſelf, knowing that the houre of his death was at hand, did excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly deſire his Father, that if it were poſſible he might eſcape it.<note place="margin">Mat. 26.39</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, we are to obſerue that there is in mans corrupt nature an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable kind of deuouring or eating and drinking, which made the Maieſtie of God to reſtrain man &amp; his generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by way of exceptions,<note place="margin">Leuit. 11. to the end. Gen. 3.3.4.</note> from diuers ſorts of creatures whereof they ſhould not cate. Adam was to eate of euery tree in the garden of God, which was a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:6245:82"/>allowance, but out of his vnſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe he tooke alſo of that which was excepted: of which corrupted na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it cometh that men generally haue a continuall renued deſire of eating and drinking. Which God in his mercy doth tollerate, and allow their proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſo farre, as they are not excepted nor forbidden.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, from the nakedneſſe of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, which was Gods particular iuſtice for his wilfulneſſe, it cometh to paſſe that his poſteritie do vſe all ſorts of clothing, ſome to auoyde heat, ſome to auoyd cold, the which alſo God doth like and allow ſo farre ſtill as is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted.</p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe, he that is moued to vſe meanes for the preſeruation of his life by the inſtinct of nature onely, and not for imitation and example ſake, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to faith in the promiſes of God &amp; obedience to his commandements, he is ſtill a moſt miſerable naturall man, &amp; farre from the way of his ſaluation.</p>
               <p>To conclude this doctrine for the vſe of meanes, as notwithſtanding the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:6245:83"/>vſe thereof, men muſt die when the time of Gods decree is come, in things pertaining to God: euen ſo not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the negligent vſe of the meanes, men muſt liue vntill their time doth come, in things pertaining to men. Both which are to be found in the conſideration of the difference that is betweene the preſeruing of life, &amp; the lengthning of life. Men may by means preſerue life vntill the time of Gods decree come: but men by no means can lengthen life, when the time of Gods decree for death is come. As for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, two me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are ſtriken with the plague both at one time, the one a begger, the other a king; both of equal yeares, both of one complexion, both of one diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, both of one climate, both of one houſe, both in one bed, both vnder one Phyſition, and both applied with one ſelfe ſame ſalue or medicine; yet the begger liueth, and the king dieth. And why? the one was ſtriken (his time being come) by an Angel, either good or bad, &amp; that ſupernaturally, as ſome in euery houſe from Dan to Berſheba:<note place="margin">2. Sa. 24.15.</note> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:6245:83"/>incurably: the other naturally, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued from ſome corrupt and poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full matter in himſelfe, and therfore cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. And becauſe the Angels ſtroke is not eſſentially to be knowne from that ſtroke which cometh by naturall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, becauſe elements reſolue into putrifaction; it were ouer deſperate, &amp; vnchriſtian preſumption, to neglect the vſe of medicine; and no folly, but faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God giues the matter faithed,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.1.</note> to wait carefully vpon that ſeruice, and to ſtand with Chriſtian magnanimitie to performe holy religious duties one towards another in ſuch a caſe, as in a time of the greateſt weight in all the world, and in the iudgment of many, is an holy kind of martyrdome. As it was ſaid by the ſpies to Rahab Whoſoeuer ſhall go out of his doore,<note place="margin">Ioſua. 2.19.</note> his bloud ſhal be vpon his owne head, and we will be guiltleſſe: but whoſoeuer ſhall be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the houſe, his bloud ſhall be on our heads: euen ſo, he that neglecteth the meanes of life, ſhall be guilty of eternal death; but he that vſeth the means ſhal be innocent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:6245:84"/>
               <head>The ſecond obiection.</head>
               <p>If meanes are to be vſed, as formerly you ſeemed to proue, and that of neceſſitie: then it followeth by a neceſſarie conſequent, that he who doth contemn them or neglect them, doth ſhorten his life, and therein is gultie of his owne deſtruction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſame is anſwered <hi>6.</hi> maner of waies.</head>
               <head type="sub">The firſt anſwer concerning him that doth contemne or neglect the meanes, is</head>
               <p>From the generalitie and timelineſſe of death, where alreadie it was proued, that the time of euery mans departure is according to Almighty Gods former decree &amp; vnchangeable counſel; which maketh alſo, that neither the diligent vſe of the meanes can lengthen life, nor the neglect thereof can ſhorten the time of life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>2.</hi> anſwer concerning him that doth contemne or neglect the meanes.</head>
               <p>Where you heard that it was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:6245:84"/>commanded that meanes ſhould be vſed for the preſeruation of life, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe, nor other places do ſay, that the vſe of the meanes doth lengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> life, nor the neglect thereof ſhorten life; that were to croſſe and contrary o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy Scripture. But thoſe places do abſolutely command the vſe of all good meanes, as men will auoyd Gods high diſpleaſure, and not be found guiltie of their own euerlaſting death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third anſwer concerning him that doth contemne or neglect the meanes.</head>
               <p>There is no ſentence nor example of Scripture that doth conclude the neglect of the meanes to be the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of life, nor the diligent vſe thereof the lengthning of life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth anſwer concerning him that doth contemne or neglect the meanes.</head>
               <p>If the neglect or contempt of the meanes were the ſhortning of life, then that were to proue iniuſtice in
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:6245:85"/>God by puniſhing one mans ſinne for another. As if the father neglect or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the meanes of helping the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of his child, ſhall that be the childs death? No, God forbid. So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in Baptiſme; if the parent do neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect &amp; delay the baptiſing of his child, and the child in the meane time dieth, ſhall that neglect be to the condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the child? No no. Againe, if the neglect of the meanes be a ſhortning of life, and the diligent vſe thereof be a lengthning of life: then it muſt needs follow, and neceſſarily be granted, that it is in man by his diligent or negligent vſe of the meanes, to croſſe or to alter the decree of God, concerning the time of mans deceaſſe; which by no way can be granted: and be it far from any man ſo to thinke, much leſſe to ſay, leaſt of all ſo to teach.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fifth anſwer concerning him that doth contemne or neglect the meanes.</head>
               <p>By an vſual phraſe of ſpeech (it is ſaid) that man ſhortneth his life, when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:6245:85"/>the meanes, or doth runne head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into eminent dangers: yet by the proprietie of the Scripture, that phraſe cannot be ſo generally maintained, no more then it may be truly ſaid, that a man performing the will of God in ſome ſpeciall matter, is a meane there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to lengthen his life, but onely by a phraſe of ſpeech. So it was ſaid to Ebed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech the Blackmore, Thy life ſhal be a prey vnto thee,<note place="margin">Iere. 39.16.17.</note> becauſe of the fauor thou didſt ſhew to Ieremy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſixth anſwer concerning him that doth neglect or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne meanes.</head>
               <p>If the diligent vſe of the meanes be a prolonging of life, and the neglect thereof be a ſhortning of life; then of neceſſity it muſt be granted, that there is an inſeparable vertue, and an inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent qualitie of ſauing life in the means: and that were no leſſe ſinne then ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidg, arrogating to the creature by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating from the creator, or as abſurd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſay,<note place="margin">2 King. 6.6. Gen. 7.7.</note> that Eliſha his bough cauſed iton to ſwim: or that Noahs arke cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:6245:86"/>ſome of all ſorts of creatures to come into it. Thus did that proud and prophane Philiſtine,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.45.</note> preſumptuouſly challenging all Iſrael, cruſting in his greatneſſe, in his ſpeare &amp; in his ſhield; but Dauid manfully met him with his ſling and his ſhepheards crooke, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in the vertue and power of God whom he did ſerue. The Lord ſpeakes vnto wicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truſting to the means, by the mouth of his Prophet Dauid; I ſaid,<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.43.</note> I will turne backe the edge of the ſword: as if he had ſaid, When the wicked thinke with their inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of death to deſtroy my people, I will take away their force, they ſhall not cut nor hurt.<note place="margin">Iere. 6.22.</note> So he ſaith to the ſame purpoſe, I wil turne backe the weapons of warre that are in their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds. The Lord makes queſtion by his Prophet Ieremie thus: Is there no balme in Gilead?<note place="margin">Iere. 9.</note> is there no phyſicke there? why then is not the health of my people recouered? As if he had ſaid, That pretious medicina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble balme, and thoſe people skilfull in Gilead, of all others in the world, ſhall do no good on them, to whom I deny
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:6245:86"/>the vertue therof; theſe licors, oyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; ſuch like, &amp; the moſt exquiſite phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions ſhall not preuaile. Againe he ſaith by his Prophet Ezechiel,<note place="margin">Eze. 5.16.</note> I will breake the ſtaffe of bread: to wit, I will take away the vertue and efficacy, euen of their daintieſt foode. To which purpoſe Hoſea the Prophet ſaid, They ſhall eate and not haue enough: to wit,<note place="margin">Hoſe. 4.10.</note> thoſe which do relie wholly vpon the meanes, ſhall faile of their expectation. Likewiſe ſaid Micha the Prophet, All hands ſhall be weake,<note place="margin">Mich. 6.14.</note> and all knees ſhal be weake as water: to wit, thoſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant and mightie men that do depend vpon their ſtrength, when they come to the puſh ſhall faile of their purpoſe; for they ſhall not be able to ſtand of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their feete, becauſe the Lord hath diſabled them. Againe the Lord ſaith vnto all ſuch by the mouth of his Prophet Ezechiel,<note place="margin">Ezech. 7.17.39.3.</note> I will ſtrike thy bow out of thy left hand, and thine arrowes out of thy right hand: as if he had ſaid, How ready ſoeuer the wicked be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared againſt the faces of the godly, yet they ſhall not do the leaſt harme. The
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:6245:87"/>ſame in effect he ſaith by the mouth of Haggai the Prophet:<note place="margin">Hagg. 1.6.</note> Ye haue ſowne much, and bring in little, ye eate but ye haue not enough, ye drinke, but ye are not filled; ye cloath you, but you be not warme, and he that earneth wages puts it in a bottomleſſe bagge.</p>
               <p>To conclude, as a man may vſe all lawfull meanes for an honeſt and a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous wife, and yet may haue a graceles and an irreligious wretch: euen ſo a man may vſe all meanes and all ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors for the preſeruation of life, and ſhall not be able to preuent death. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the vertue, the efficacy and power of the meanes is in the hands of God, and the vſe onely in the hands of men. As in Noah his oliue leafe which the doue brought into the arke,<note place="margin">Gen. 8.12.</note> there were actions of two ſundrie natures, to wit, peace and plenty; and as in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of Gods word there is an action of life and an action of death: euen ſo in this matter or meanes concerning life and death, there are actions of two ſundry natures, one concerning God, the other concerning man. That which
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:6245:87"/>pertaines to man, is the diligent vſe of the meanes, that which pertaines to God, is to giue vertue and efficacy vnto the meanes. As for example, God ſaid vnto the people of Iſrael,<note place="margin">Iere. 38.2.</note> He that remaineth in the citie ſhall die without the ſword, by the famine, and by the peſtilence, but he that goeth forth ſhall liue, he ſhal haue his life for a prey. Here life and death was in preſent queſtion, to flie out of the citie was the meanes of life, which was for the people to do, and to giue vertue vnto their flight, was in God to do. On the contrary ſide the neglect of that duty, made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> guilty of their owne death, and acceſſary by a phraſe of ſpeech to their own deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: &amp; yet in that very rebellious actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theirs, was the decree of God fulfilled concerning the time of their death.<note place="margin">Mat. 2.</note> Likewiſe in that Herodian perſecution the wiſe men tooke the forewarning of of God for the meanes of their preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and his Maieſtie gaue good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe and effect thereunto. I conclude againe, that he which vſeth meanes (how lawfull ſoeuer) with an vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:6245:88"/>and with a beleeuing, that the ſame of it ſelfe is effectuall for the lengthning of life, that man is an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell. But to vſe meanes which are not inhibited for the preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of health, wealth and libertie, and ſuch like, is very religious.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third obiection concerning addition, or conditionall life</head>
               <head type="sub">If the time of death be ſo exactly ſet downe and ſo reſolutely conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the counſell of God,</head>
               <p>Why then doth his holy Maieſtie promiſe to lengthen the life of the godly? as is in the firſt commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the ſecond table,<note place="margin">Exo. 20.12.</note> I will prolong thy dayes, if thou wilt walke in my wayes. The performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his promiſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning long life,<note place="margin">Gen. 5.5.8. to 32.</note> may be euidenced from the ten holy Fathers before the floud, who for keeping of his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments did liue many hundred yeares more then any other liued after them. And the ſame we haue in a ſort truly ſaid of Ezechias, whoſe ſinceritie was
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:6245:88"/>ſuch as God vouchſafed to adde fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene yeares vnto his life. And againe,<note place="margin">2 King. 20.5.6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Why is it ſaid by the Prophet,<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.23.</note> 
                  <hi>The bloud-thirſty man ſhall not liue halfe his dayes?</hi> Or he ſhall liue long co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditional<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? as God ſaid to Abimelech. <hi>Deliuer Abraham his wife that thou maiſt liue:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 20.7.</note> 
                  <hi>but if not, be ſure thou ſhalt die the death, thou and all that thou haſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The anſwer to this obiection is threefold.</head>
               <p>Firſt, as by a decree from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is ſet downe how long the godly and the wicked ſhall liue, ſo withall euen in the ſame decree was ſet downe before the giuing of the law, that long life ſhould be a reward for him that kept the law, and ſhortneſſe of life for him that did breake the law, when as yet he had done neither good nor euill. Almightie God foretelleth the ſinnes of Iſrael, many hundred yeares before they were, and their iudgements that ſhould be accordingly, in theſe words:<note place="margin">Deut. 31.16.17.</note> This people will go a whoring after o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gods, they will forſake me and my
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:6245:89"/>couenant; wherefore my wrath will wax hot againſt them that day, and I will forſake them: then ſhall they be confounded.</p>
               <p>Almightie God to the like purpoſe by the mouth of his Prophet Eſay ſpeaks thus concerning the ſame people:<note place="margin">Eſa 48.8.</note> I knew that thou wouldeſt tranſgreſſe, therefore haue I called thee a tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor from the wombe.</p>
               <p>Saint Peter ſpeaking of Chriſts death, &amp; therin of the death of his Saints, ſaith thus to the Iewes:<note place="margin">Act. 2.23.</note> Him haue ye take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of the wicked being deliuered by the determinate counſell, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge of God. As if he had ſaid, This could not haue bene, had it not bene ſo decreed before hand: this is not happened by chance nor by aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but as it was foreſeene good of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond anſwer concerning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall lengthning, and threats of ſhortning life.</head>
               <p>The anſwer concerning the Prophets praying for, and in the behalfe of Gods
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:6245:89"/>people, for long life, and ſometimes praying for the cutting off of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. They being ſo graciouſly and ſo ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully inſpired by the ſpirit of God, could not erre ſo groſly as to croſſe &amp; contrarie other holy men, who had written by the ſame Spirit. They knew well that God had exactly concluded the time of all men for their life, and time of death, and therefore they did but pray as other religious me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drawne thereunto vpon the performance of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther religious duties, in that behalfe towards their brethren. After this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Daniel doth pray for the people of Iſrael being in Babylon;<note place="margin">Dan. 9.2.3.</note> hauing found by bookes, when the number of yeares was ended wherof the Lord had ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Ieremie, that he would accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh 70 yeares in the deſolation of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. Therefore although he knew that God would deliuer his people out of bondage, according as he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed: yet out of his loue to them, and from his dutie to God, he betook him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe moſt importunately to pray for them, and ſo continued vntill the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:6245:90"/>Gabriel brought him a direct &amp; an immediate anſwer from the throne of the Almightie.<note place="margin">Gen. 18.23. to 33.</note> Abraham prayed for the Zodomites, and that verie importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, though he knew very well that God had moſt iuſtly determined their ouerthrow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third anſwer concerning condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall lengthning of life.</head>
               <p>Thirdly, concerning that addition of fifteene yeares to Hezekiahs life, it is not ſo to be vnderſtood, when he was ſo mortally ſick, that his day was come to die. But in ſuch a caſe alwayes, where ſuch a Scripture ſeemeth litterally to diſallow or croſſe another, as this doth; men muſt looke for another ſence, yea ſuch a ſence as may agree with the ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie of faith. It ſeemed indeed vnto Hezekiah as he was a mortall man, and as the caſe ſtood between him &amp; God at that time, that indeed fifteen yeares were added to his life.<note place="margin">Iob. 42.16.</note> The like place is in Iobe.</p>
               <p>Hauing exactly by many ſentences proued the timelineſſe of death: and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:6245:90"/>withall hauing anſwered ſome obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions that might be made in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe thereof:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Let vs now obſerue ſixe ſorts of people who are to be reproued by this obiection of lengthning and ſhortning of life.</head>
               <p>Firſt it ſerueth warrantably to reproue thoſe that do put off the time of their death, vſing the world as if they were to dwell therein for euer. Like the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple before the floud,<note place="margin">Gen. 7.11.</note> of whom Saint Luke ſpeaketh, who notwithſtanding 120. yeares repentance giuen vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in the which the arke was a preparing; yet neuertheleſſe they were careleſſe and vnconſcionable.<note place="margin">Luk. 17.26.27.</note> They did eate and drinke, maried wiues, and gaue in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, euen vnto the day that Noe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the arke, and the floud came. Likewiſe as it was in the dayes of Lot, and when as they tooke his holy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation for mockage, they eate,<note place="margin">Gen 19.24. Luk. 17.28.</note> they dranke, planted vineyards, and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; but in the day that Lot went out of Sodom it rained fire and brimſtone,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:6245:91"/>and deſtroyed them all. So the people in theſe dayes, notwithſtanding the manifold and variable warnings of the Amightie, ſometimes out of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement, ſometimes out of the earth, ſometimes out of the ſea, and ſpecially out of his holy Scripture: theſe I ſay, are not yet moued in heart to prouide for their departure, or at leaſt they haue no willingneſſe, or reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therunto. They ſtand, as it were, vpon terms with his Maieſty, vntill they be ouercome &amp; ſurpriſed ſodainly, as a bird in the ſnare of the fowler. Theſe are they whoſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections being alienated, do iudge bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of earthly things then of heauenly: of whom Saint Iohn ſaith, They loue darkeneſſe better then light.<note place="margin">Io. 3.19.31</note> And he that is of the earth, is of the earth, and ſpeaketh of the earth. And as God ſaid vnto the Iſraelites,<note place="margin">Iudg. 10.14 11.7. Deu. 32.29</note> Go and cry vnto the gods which you haue choſen, let them ſaue you in the time of your tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo will the Lord ſay vnto all ſuch as defer the time of their repentance and amendment: Seeke you help elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, &amp; find it if you can, for I will do
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:6245:91"/>nothing for you. Why come ye vnto me now in the time of your tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? did ye not thruſt me out? O that men were wiſe, then would they conſider their latter end.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it ſerueth to reproue thoſe who wilfully &amp; riotouſly waſte, ſpoile, and ſpend that which ſhould neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appertaine to their poſteritie. Euen in nature and qualitie like the wilde Boare,<note place="margin">Pſal. 80.13.</note> of which the Prophet Dauid ſpeaketh, who not onely eates and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoures all that is aboue ground: but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards roots vp all that ſhould ſerue another yeare. And in the ſame place alſo likened vnto wild ſauage beaſts, who hauing eaten their fill, do tread &amp; trample all the reſt vnder foote and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the dirt, that no other beaſt may, or can eate thereof. If they ſinne that do neglect the vſe of lawfull meanes: how much more then they, that vſe lawfull meanes vnlawfully, by ſurfetting, by drunkenneſſe, &amp; ſuch like? which God in his mercie hath ordained for the chearing and comforting of the godly.<note place="margin">Pro. 31.7.8</note> Euen as the people of Laiſh after the
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:6245:92"/>manner of the Sidonians,<note place="margin">Iudg. 18.7.</note> dwelt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly, and ſo were conquered.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it ſerueth to reproue thoſe who not knowing the Scriptures, and therein not knowing ſpecially the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute decree of almightie God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the verie certaine day &amp; houre of euerie mans departure; they fret, they furne, they weepe, they waile ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiuely for the deceaſſe of ſuch as are nearely appertaining vnto them; as if the want of meanes, or the neglect of ſome dutie, had directly ſhortned his or their liues: all which is a plaine eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of an vnbeleeuing heart.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, it ſerueth to reproue thoſe who to preuent death in the time of danger, do arrogate vnto the vſe of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull meanes, as forceries, witchcraft, and ſuch like, which God hath directly &amp; abſolutely forbidden: or elſe, do firſt vſe vnlawfull meanes, and afterwards do applie themſelues to the vſe of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes,<note place="margin">Da. 2.1.4.1.</note> as Nebucadnezzer did, who firſt ſought to his aſtrologers, ſoothſayers, and others of that kind: and afterwards ſought helpe of Daniel
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:6245:92"/>the ſeruant of the liuing God. For to attribute that vnto the meanes which is due to God, is euery where inhibited; as it was forbidden the people of Iſrael to ſay;<note place="margin">Deu. 8.17.18.</note> My power &amp; the ſtrength of my hands hath prepared me this abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance: but remember the Lord thy God, for it is he which giueth thee po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to get ſubſtance.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, it reproues thoſe who ſpend the time of their renowm, the time of their dwelling here, &amp; the time wherein they poſſeſſe their ſoules, ſo vainly. Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie point whereof is precious: although not riotouſly, nor wantonly, nor coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly, yet careleſly, &amp; vnconſcionably ſpent without deſire of the knowledge of God according to his word, without groweth in zeale to his holy ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in the ſtrength of faith, and in the power of his ſpirit, hauing all meanes therof brought euen home vnto them; but euen as a people that doth neither good nor harme, luke-warme, or hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting betweene two opinions. The time of this ignorance, want of zeale, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and ſuch like, God regardeth
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:6245:93"/>not in vs whiles we are without the meanes thereof, as in his mercie he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared himſelfe alſo towards the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. But now it is called to day. Chriſt ſaid, partly concerning himſelfe, and partly concerning others, I muſt work while it is called to day,<note place="margin">Ioh. 9.4.</note> the night com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth when a man cannot work. Let vs alſo take it as ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs, we are Gods children, and therfore may not be idle: let vs be doing in time, for time will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. A man not knowing by the word of God the timelineſſe of death, to wit, that death cannot take hold on him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till Gods appointed time, and that then he muſt needs depart, the ſame man dieth willingly &amp; comfortably: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as a man that is ignorant thereof, mournes, and murmurs, imputing the cauſe of his ſickeneſſe and death vnto caſuall meanes.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, it is ſharpely and warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to rebuke thoſe moſt ignorant and moſt prophane caluminators, who do derogate from the worthineſſe of the meanes which God hath ordained in his Church, whoſe detracting tongs do
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:6245:93"/>manifeſt their hearts in ſpeaking ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly, ſo vntruly, and euery way ſo indignely, not only of graue &amp; learned Phyſitions, but alſo eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and honourable vſe of Phyſicke it ſelfe, which was highly commended, &amp; carefully vſed amongſt the holy Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches, the Prophets and Apoſtles, and thence from age to age ſucceſſiuely, by all, and amongſt all godly men ruling themſelues by the former examples &amp; ſufficient grounds of Scripture. Some of which malicious, &amp; profane perſons wil neuertheleſſe in their depth of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger vſe the aduico and helpe of Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whom at other times, before and after, they vſe in a parable of reproch &amp; diſdaine, as they do the Miniſters and Paſtors of their ſoules, without whoſe miniſterie they cannot poſſibly be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: and as indeed they do vſe the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the graue, and moſt honeſt profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the law, who in their places do ſtand for the defence of their goods, their good names and their patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. Euerie of which ſtately and moſt honourable profeſſions, is ſo needfull
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:6245:94"/>and ſo neceſſarily required in Church and in commonweale, as that neither the one nor the other can be, nor in any good ſeaſonable ſort continue. And to be breefe, the ignorant and diſſolute man doth alway beare armor defenſiue to defend his owne euilles, and armes offenſiue to aſſaile the good maners of others; according to the old ſaying, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Prouerbe. Yet according to my humble duty, in Chriſt, and in Chriſt his ſteede, euen by the mercifulnes of God I do exhort all ſuch, as in an acceptable time, to make vſe of theſe honeſt and holy profeſſors, as of the meanes of his mercie towards them, and as of effectuall inſtruments for their bodies, and for their ſoules: and that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the directions of the Scriptures of truth, and examples of holy men in all ages. And as Abimelech ſaid vnto his folke,<note place="margin">Iudg 9.48.</note> What ye ſee me do, make haſt and do the like; looke on me and do likewiſe, euen as I do ſo do ye: euen ſo ſay I and more alſo vnto you my good chriſtian brethren, let all things be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and done in the feare of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:6245:94"/>to knowledge, and according to the good example of ſuch as guide themſelues by the word and Spirit.</p>
               <p>The fourth inſtruction concerning the memorability of death, hauing in it theſe 4. principall reſpects or chriſtian conſiderations; as the perſons are in place or in behauiour, ſo is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration either more or leſſe, after their deceaſe to be ſolemnized priuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or publickly, with mourning, faſting and praying.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt the perſon dead or dying.</item>
                  <item>Secondly whether priuate or publicke.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly whether ſpirituall or temporal.</item>
                  <item>Fourthly whether iuſt or vniuſt.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Firſt, whether the perſon <hi>dead or dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be priuate or publicke,</hi> we are inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated vnto this mournefull memento, for the terrors and torments of death, which he endured in our ſight and in our hearing; as did appeare by his wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full complaints to ſuch as were about him, who would and ſhould, but by no meanes could miniſter any helpe vnto him; as alſo by the galling griefes and griping grones he endured, who being
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:6245:95"/>yet aliue was ſo ſurpriſed of al his vigor and force of ſpirit, as made him blind, yea deafe and dumbe. O how deteſtable is ſinne, whence death and the intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable pangs thereof are originally deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued! Sinne being ſo odious, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable with God, his Maieſtie deuiſed an odious and deteſtable puniſhment and plague for it, which is death. A plague of all plagues, and the moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingeſt plague of all other, for any man to vndergo. There was neuer any puniſhment that God did inflict vpon man for the breach of his holy lawes, nor any torture which the Imps of the diuell could deuiſe for the Saints of God, but euerie man was more willing to endure it then death. Not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it did depriue man of the world and worldly things, but alſo, and more ſpecially, becauſe that man hath euen in nature a great loathing, &amp; an vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able feare of it: as may partly appeare by the ſtrange meanes, by the notable deuices, and by the deſperate attempts which men haue vſed and indeuored, onely to ſhunne and to auoide the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:6245:95"/>of death: and as alſo may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the examples of many in the Scriptures, and of others who are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories. The paines and pangs which the body doth endure before the ſoule be ſundred, may be likened vnto the paines and pangs of a woman in her trauell with child, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy Prophet ſpeakes: Her hands, ſaith he, on her loynes,<note place="margin">Iere. 30.6. Eſai. 13.7.8,</note> her face turned to paleneſſe, her heart wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened and melting with feare and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh. Yea the paines and pangs of death do well reſemble the paines and torments of hell, and therefore the firſt &amp; ſecond death, is but one &amp; ſelfeſame, with this difference onely; the one is naturall and temporarie, the other is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall and euerlaſting. The feare of this death made our bleſſed Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt as he was a man, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune the Maieſtie of his Father with teares that it might paſſe from him,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.39.40.41.42.43.</note> &amp; being brought vnto it through the agonie thereof he was enforced to call and to crie vnto God his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as if in part he had deſpaired: O my
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:6245:96"/>Father, why haſt thou forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me? The like obliuion and deſperate ſpeeches are heard &amp; ſeene in the time of deaths torments, euen from many of Gods deare children and canonized Saints. Saint Paul ſaith that death hath a ſting, thereby inferring that death is veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, as all creatures which haue ſtings are noyſome and hurtfull either more or leſſe: but death is like vnto the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell himſelfe, ſtinging and poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, &amp; therfore called a ſerpent, the moſt noiſome, and the moſt peſtiferous crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all others. Againe, Saint Paul calleth death an enemie, inferring thereby as out of the naturall diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a naturall enemie, the greateſt miſchiefe that poſſibly he can deuiſe to the poore body of man, ſpecially being godly. The torments of death muſt needes be held innarrable, if we do but conſider the combate and conflict that is betweene the ſoule and the body, the one affecting cleane contrarie to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in nature quite oppoſite. Which oppoſition and conflict may well be reſembled vnto that dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:6245:96"/>tempeſt on the ſea of Tarſhiſh, which was raiſed purpoſely by God himſelfe, for the arreſting of Ionas, who was as he thought ſecure. The winds were ſent into the ſeas, which being an element light, laboured veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the nature therof to aſcend, and the ſeas being an element heauy, laboured mightily according to the quality thereof to deſcend; ſo that the ſeas being violently kept vp by the winds, and the winds being violently kept downe by the ſeas, made ſuch a ſtorme &amp; ſuch an outragious tempeſt, as if heauen and earth had ratled and rang together, or as if the ſhippe had bene ſtill a ruſhing and a riuing in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vpon the rocks: euen ſo is the ſoule and body of him who is in the hands of death. The ſoule according to the nature and quality thereof, being a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, an heauenly and holy creature of the Almightie, vſeth and enforceth all meanes thither to aſcend: but the body being of a cleane contrary diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, maſſie, heauy and earthy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the qualitie thereof, in ſort
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:6245:97"/>and kind labors thither to deſcend. The one being of a cleane contrarie diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the other, they become hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drances to the paſſage one of another, &amp; meanes one againſt another of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enduring paſſions. And to conclude briefly, the torments of death are as the hewing of Agag in peeces,<note place="margin">1 Sam 15.33. Pſal. 50.22.</note> &amp; as the ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full execution of God, whereof Dauid ſpeaks. Although this torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting be the decree of the Almighty, for the ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of mans body, and for the depriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his life: yet it is euident, that the variety and ſundrie manners, ſorts and kinds of death, whereunto his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie hath left himſelfe at large, is the cauſe that many wicked men ſo well as the godly do depart this life with litle pangs or paines. And at other times out of his Maieſties roiall and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary fauor through Ieſus Chriſt, the paines and pangs of death in many of the godly are mitigated and dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, as may appeare out of manifold ſentences and examples of Scripture. For it is all one with him, in regard of his power and mercie to abate or to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilate
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:6245:97"/>the qualitie and the quantity of executing creatures: or things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for torments, as it is for him to increaſe and to multiply the ſame. As the ſauage and hungrie lions were ſo aſſwaged, &amp; in their natures ſo mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note place="margin">Dani. 6.20.21.22.3.20.21.22.</note> that they became as playfellowes vnto Daniel; the fierie fornace being ſeuen times hotter then ordinary, was vnto him and his companions but as a place of recreation: So no doubt were the fiery torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts vnto the Saints of God, who were cruelly executed in Queene Maries dayes. After another ſort moſt powerfully doth his Maieſtie multiplie or increaſe the qualitie of bread and water, for the good of the poore who otherwiſe could not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly liue: and abateth the extremitie of their cold in the winter. Remember the augmentation of the 7.<note place="margin">Mar. 8.8. Dan. 1.15.</note> loues and few fiſhes, ſo that more was taken vp then was layd downe: and remember Daniels pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. And albeit I ſhould ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely grant that there is no mitigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of paines in death for any, and that it muſt needes be concluded, that the
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:6245:98"/>verie Saints and ſeruants of God ſhall ſuffer the moſt grieuous torments of naturall death equally with the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates (which cannot be truly agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto, and which God forbid): yet conſidering that the guiltineſſe of ſin is cleane taken away in Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; that theſe torments of death are but as it were momentanie, or as the twinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an eye in compariſon of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting torments of the reprobates: what man or woman hauing any hope thereof, hauing any feeling of faith, or hauing any one motion of Gods ſpirit, but would moſt willingly endure the torments of bodily death, were they yet greater? yea before it come, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate, and withall to celebrate the remembrance of death, by which there is an end of all ſorrowes, and the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of all ioyes and immortall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>If the perſon dead or dying be an huſband,</head>
               <p>Then the matrimoniall aſſociation which by Gods ordinance was made,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:6245:98"/>ſingularly and plurally, two in one, and one in two, the better to be helpfull one vnto another, is now by death daſht, as it were into powder, and violently par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a ſunder, and ſeuered one from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother for euer into two diſtinct pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which deuiſion to the husband or wife is ſo naturally grieuous, as it is for one limbe being cut off from another, as Ruth doth impart out of her moſt ſingular affection to Nahomie her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in law in theſe words;<note place="margin">Ruth. 1.17.</note> The Lord do ſo to me and more alſo, if ought but death part thee &amp; me: euen ſo is the loue of a wife, fearing God, towards her husband, that ſhe concludeth in her heart, from the firſt houre vnto the laſt, that nothing ſhal infringe her faith towards him but death, which when it cometh exceedingly moueth her to mourne. This alſo appeares vpon the wofull and lamentable experience of Nahomie, who by death was violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rent from her husband, which made her as out of a ſorrowfull heart to crie out ſaying,<note place="margin">Ruth. 1.20.21</note> The Almightie hath giuen me much bitterneſſe, I went full, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:6245:99"/>empty, the Lord hath humbled me, and brought me to aduerſitie. By which words and by many daily exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, it is plaine, that the parting of an husband from a wife miniſtreth many occaſions of weeping, mourning, and calling vpon God. If ſhe be old, then is ſhe void of hope, and the farther from helpe in her greateſt neede; if ſhe be young, then is ſhe the more ſubiect to vtter vndoing, by her choiſe, which ſtandeth ſo in generall amongſt all men in the world. In the meane time ſhe is in danger by her ſingularity to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till temptations of the diuell, and ſo to the prouocations of diueliſh men, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the breaking vp of her houſhold, and the diſperſing of her fatherleſſe children. All which dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dangers ſhould be ſufficient matter to moue her to commemorate her husbands death, and by the diuine or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of her ſelfe in the ſame to ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize her owne.</p>
               <p>If the partie dead be priuate, and a wife, the husband in like manner is oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned to commemorate her death,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:6245:99"/>with much mourning. The more god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wiſe the husband is, the more is his griefe with the conſideration of that danger which is to come, in the choiſe of another, and in ſtep-daming, and mother-lawing his little young children, and when as ſpecially he ſhall endanger religious exerciſes, in his houſe amongſt his familie, and in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the decay of Gods ſeruice, by meanes of a wife who perhaps will croſſe and contrarie all. The conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe, and ſuch like diſturbances no doubt together with natural affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being powerfull in Abraham (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a man highly in the fauour of God) it wrought in him exceeding great paſſions, which made him to mourne much &amp; with heartie grife,<note place="margin">Gen 23. verſ. 3.</note> not able to abide the ſight of his corps.</p>
               <p>Here a complaint may well be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt husbands, who moſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly, and moſt vnconſcionably do paſſe ouer the deceaſſe of their wiues, and in like manner the wiues paſſing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the deceaſſe of their husbands; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing onely for the preſent time, the
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:6245:100"/>matter ſeeming irkeſome, they burſt out paſſionatly into ſome few funerall teares, ſaying with admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what is he dead? or is ſhe dead? what dead? alacke what dead? &amp; who would haue thought it! With clapping of hands, and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of thighes, as if death were vnwo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they ſtill for a few dayes ſpeake ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably, Such a man is dead, the onely honeſt husband is dead, or the onely honeſt wife that euer man had is dead; wel, this is the world, there is no reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, weeping will not ſerue, we ſhall all die; or elſe diſſemblingly they mourne on their backs, but ioy in their hearts, making an outward ſhew of that which is not inward.<note place="margin">Sam. 14.1. to 13.</note> Like the woman of Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koha, who with her mourning appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, with her heauy countenance, and with her lamentable cries made Dauid the King (though a great wife man) to beleeue that her husband &amp; her two ſonnes were dead in deede as ſhe ſaid, which was nothing ſo. Or elſe moſt vnnaturall of whom S. Paul ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.23.</note> who are nothing moued to mourne, being in ſort a people forſaken of God,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:6245:100"/>and branded with the marke of vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall affection. To yeeld no naturall affection, is ſo much abhorring nature, and ſo contrarie to pitie, and ſo voyd of pietie, as it is to denie the buriall of the dead; ſo that before God it is all one kinde of prophaneneſſe, and ſo much as that husband or that wife can do, to condemne them that are graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly dead in the Lord, to be in ſtate of damnation, and therefore not any way worthy of commemoration: whom the Prophet Ezechiel reproueth after this manner, Crueltie is riſen vp,<note place="margin">Eze. 7.11.</note> &amp; a rod of wickedneſſe, none of them ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, nor of their riches, nor any of theirs, neither ſhall there be lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for them. And Eſay ſaith,<note place="margin">Eſai. 57.1.</note> The righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous periſheth, and no man conſidereth it in heart, and mercifull men are taken away, and no man vnderſtandeth that the righteous is taken away from the euill to come.</p>
               <p>If the perſon dead or dying be pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, and a ſonne or daughter, the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent qualitie, and the vnanſwerable affections of parents towards their
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:6245:101"/>children whiles they are aliue, doth ſufficiently diſcouer their continuall mourning, their griefe and their hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſorrowes whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the children are dead. And now I call to minde out of my owne tormented heart, and fatherly afflicted ſoule, my ſorrow for many ſonnes, ſpecially forone. Parents can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be included within this account of reprooſe, but rather truly be reckoned amongſt thoſe who mourne too much and ouerlong, being drawne thereunto as out of their vnanſwerable affections, deriued no man knowes whence, nor how, ſauing that which is in reſpect of children begotten in mariage, to which the exceeding diuine affection of God the Father in Chriſt Ieſus hath relation and perfect reference.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the perſon dead or dying be priuate, and a father or mother,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What exceeding great cauſe haue the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> continually to commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and religiouſly to celebrate, his or her death, with mourning, with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and with calling heartily vpon
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:6245:101"/>God, for theſe two ſpeciall cauſes? One is, for their continuall care of parents, tending onely for their welfare in the world; the other, their Chriſtian conſcience for the ſaluation of their ſoules in the world to come: &amp; where parents faile in the one, they exceed in the other, according to the common prouerbe; Happie is the child whoſe father goes to the diuell. As if it were to ſay more particularly and more plainly, The father and the mother are ſo vnſatiable in their coueting, ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell-like pinching their backes &amp; their bellies, and ſo diuelliſhly oppreſſing the poore, yea many times ſo atheiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like hazarding their owne liues by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull getting, and ſo directly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelues againſt God, for to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich their children, as that indeed they make whole ſhipwrack of their ſoules. The truth whereof is ſo cleare, and the matter it ſelfe ſo probable, as if there were neither many millions of godly witneſſes, neither the wicked liues and waſtfull behauiour of their children: yet their owne conſcience to their own
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:6245:102"/>condemnation would manifeſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it. And haue not ſuch children great cauſe to mourne, yea alwayes to bewaile the deceaſſe of ſuch parents, ſpecially, becauſe of the helliſh tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the ineuitable paines which they do endure? Me thinks I heare and ſee the ſame or greater torments, which God in his vpright inſtice doth prepare for ſuch children, not onely becauſe of their vnnaturall and vndutifull beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uior towards their parents being dead, and whiles they were aliue; but alſo for that they do ſo ioy, and ſo reioyce in their goods, being ſo gathered, and ſo left vnto them, which is indeed, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the price of bloud; and I may ſay more plainly, the price of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ſoules and bodies.<note place="margin">Gen. 4.10.</note> As the bloud of Abel did call and crie from earth to heauen for vengeance againſt his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Caine,<note place="margin">2. Kin. 1.12.13. to 15.</note> and as Eliah called &amp; cried that fire might come from heauen to the earth vpon all the captaines of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haziah: euen ſo is there an interchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able entercourſe from heauen to earth, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth to heauen, of Gods irefull
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:6245:102"/>plagues to fall vpon ſuch children. The holy man Dauid, although he vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully longed to drinke of the water at Bethlehem, yet vpon better conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he wold none of it when the three Worthies brought it vnto him, but poured it for an oblation to the Lord; and ſaid, Let not my Lord God ſuffer me to do this.<note place="margin">2 Sam 23.15.16.</note> Be it farre from me that I do this, is not this the bloud of theſe men which went in ieopardie of their liues?<note place="margin">1. Chron. 11 17.18.19.</note> ſhall I drinke the bloud of theſe mens liues? So that by this it appeareth were there no other proofe, how dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly ill gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> goods are kept, how more dangerouſly they are to be ſpent, and how damnably ſuch children do liue in this world, indeed as it were without God: yea the very damned in hell ſhall riſe in iudgement againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Luk. 16.27</note> For the glutto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in torments was perple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed with griefe for the ſtate of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren which liued in ſin, &amp; would not haue them come to that place to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate his torments. Whereas theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracious children haue no remorſe or ſorrow for their diſtreſſed parents,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:6245:103"/>which died in ſinne, and liue in death. And what may not be ſaid of another ſort of graceleſſe children, who after the deceaſſe of their godly religious parents, are ſo far from mourning after them, or for them, as that they indeed do ioy and reioyce in their hearts at their departure? If they ſorrow any thing at all, it is for that they died not ſooner, according as many times they wiſhed, for their lands and goods ſake. Shall they eſcape for their wickednes? No: the Maieſtie of our eternall Father will ſhorten their dayes, diminiſh their ſtore; and from their graceleſſe ſtocke ſhall ſpring vngracious impes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſeuen fold into their boſomes.<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> For the meaſure, ſaith our Lord, which you mete to others ſhall be heaped vpon you againe. When good king Ioſiah was dead, we reade not that his ſonne Iehohaz mourned for him, or followed his good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, either in the continuance of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, adminiſtration of iuſtice, or god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conuerſation. Wherefore his dayes were ſhortned, his life miſerable, and
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:6245:103"/>his kingdome was left to the diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his enemie. His poſteritie was yet more miſerable; for his ſonne being dead, was not lamented,<note place="margin">Ier. 22.18.19.</note> neither did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mourne for him, ſaying; Ah Lord, or, ah his glory: he ſhall be buried as an aſſe, euen drawne and caſt forth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the gates of Ieruſalem.</p>
               <p>This ſerueth neceſſarily to inſtigate and to call vpon all ſuruiuors of their parents and friends, carefully to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate the heauy hand of God vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> themſelues, for that priuate depriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of friends if they were godly; with the acknowledgement of their owne ſinnes, chiefly in the omiſſion of many reuerent duties towards them, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in thankfulneſſe vnto God for thoſe helpes which they receiued from them. It ſerues for the accompliſhment of other holy duties towards the dead, in taking care, &amp; in making conſcience to do good vnto thoſe, whom their friends being dead, entirely loued whiles they liued. Whereof we haue a famous example in Dauid toward his faithful friend Ionathan who was dead:
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:6245:104"/>Is there any man,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 9.1. to 8.</note> ſaid he, of the houſe of Saul, that I may ſhew mercie vnto him for Ionathans ſake? to whom was brought Mephiboſeth, Ionathans ſon: Dauid ſaid vnto him; Feare not, for I will ſurely ſhew thee kindneſſe, for Ionathan thy fathers ſake, who is dead, and I will reſtore thee all the fields of Saul thy father, and thou ſhalt eate at my table continually. Againe he ſaid,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 10.1</note> I will ſhew kindneſſe vnto Hanun as his father ſhewed kindneſſe vno me. There was a ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne law in Iſrael, which was to be performed to the widow of him which was dead, if ſhe had no ſon to comfort her: which law &amp; Chriſtian commemoration for the dead was me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morably performed by Boaz towards Ruth.<note place="margin">Ruth. 4.10.21.</note> If the perſon dead were wicked in his life, and at his death; then there is more cauſe of mourning and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and calling earneſtly vnto God, by his kindred, and by his allied friends for the auoiding of Gods iudgements, which they moſt iuſtly haue deſerued, in that they did not more carefully and more conſcionably inſtruct ſuch a man
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:6245:104"/>or ſuch a woman vnto a better life, whereby he or ſhe might haue made a better death. According to which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Saint Iames ſpeaketh after this maner:<note place="margin">Iam. 5. v. 19.20.</note> If any of you haue erred fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the truth, and ſome man hath conuerted him, let him know that he which hath conuerted the ſinner from going aſtray out of his way, ſhall ſaue a ſoule from death, and ſhall hide a multitude of ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the partie dead or dying be publicke, ſpirituall, or temporall, and iuſt,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then conſider the preſent euill that hath happened to particular perſons, to priuate families, to publike congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and to whole kindomes, after the deceaſſe of ſuch a man, or ſuch a woman. Which is drawne from that good which almightie God vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth for the time preſent wherein they liued, who being dead, it incontinently ceaſſeth. As Salomon ſaith, By the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the righteous,<note place="margin">Pro. 11.11.</note> cities are exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: to wit, the whole inhabitants of that towne and countrie where a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:6245:105"/>perſon liueth, ſhall fare and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the better, and ſhall haue the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God which they haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued withholden from them. And it is certaine,<note place="margin">Ioſua. 7.1. to 6.</note> as for the ſinnes of one, many haue bene in the anger of God deſtroid and brought to nothing; ſo for the true godlineſſe of one or more,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 24.15.</note> many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds and thouſands haue bene moſt miraculouſly preſerued. God promiſed Abraham, that if in all Sodome and Gomorrah there were found but ten righteous perſons,<note place="margin">Gen. 18.24. to 33.19.18. to 26</note> he would ſpare all the reſt for their ſakes. The ſame was experimented in Zoar at Lots requeſt, for all the people therein were miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly preſerued from the fire which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly fell from heauen round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them. There was three yeares dearth in all the land of Iſrael for Sauls ſinnes onely in ſlaying the Gibeonits.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 21.1. to 11.</note> Dauid the King did therfore importune the Gibeonits, for their fauour vnto God in their behalfe, which being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned the plague ceaſſed. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie ſo long as Ioſeph liued, King Pharao and all his ſubiects proſpered:
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:6245:105"/>but when Ioſeph died,<note place="margin">Exo. 1.6.7.8. to the end. 9.1.33. Exo. 9.27.28. 2 King. 24.2. to the end. Dan. 11.1.2.</note> then their plagues reuiued and fell thicke in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt. When Moſes was intreated to pray for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thoſe plagues alſo ceaſſed. Moreouer after the death of King Ioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the citie of Ieruſalem was wonne, and the people caried captiue vnto Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon: God ſpared them and did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his wrath from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in all his dayes according to his promiſe. As the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is in his place of preheminence, in Church or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monweale, &amp; in his paines performing the worke of the Lord: ſo is the loſſe of him to the people whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he departs. And as the greatneſſe of the loſſe is, ſo ought the greatneſſe of the conſiderations to be had amongſt thoſe where he is miſſed, continually mourning, weeping and calling vpon God for his mercy, and that he will be pleaſed to withhold thoſe plagues which he hath ſo begun, hauing alwaies before them the remembrance of their ſinnes, and the iudgements of God for the ſame, which they haue many wayes and at ſundrie times deſerued, humbly proſtrating the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues before the throne
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:6245:106"/>of his mercies, in the name and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of Ieſus Chriſt. The children of Iſrael wept much and mourned ſore for Moſes thirty dayes together.<note place="margin">Deut. 34.8.</note> The Maieſtie of God taking particular knowledge of his death, ſaid vnto Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua, Moſes my ſeruant is dead.<note place="margin">Ioſua. 1.2.3.</note> As if he had ſaid more plainely, I ſee his want already amongſt the people, it is ſo great and ſo dangerous that there muſt be a preſent ſupply.</p>
               <p>If the perſon publike being dead were vngodly, an oppreſſor, and ſuch like ill diſpoſed, being in profeſſion ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpirituall, or temporall; who will not thinke it an happy day, a bleſſed time in which it pleaſed God to cut him off? for euery man where ſuch an one had to do, for his owne particular &amp; priuate good, hath cauſe to comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate the mercies of God in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. And by how much the more it may be ſaid that he was generally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to euill: by ſo much the more ought all that people amongſt whom he liued, be generally diſpoſed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate the mercies of God with all
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:6245:106"/>alacrity and cheerefulneſſe for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation: weeping and mourning for their former ſins, which was the cauſe why God did raiſe ſuch a graceleſſe man to haue rule ouer them ſo long, and continually praying to haue a more vertuous and a more religious man in his roome.</p>
               <p>This teacheth all true profeſſors of chriſtianity as formerly was ſaid, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to commemorate the deceaſſe of publike perſons, who had their places in Church and commonwealth; ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if they were profitable to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and religious towards God. We haue the example of Dauid the King, and all his honourable ſubiects; who mourned much after the deceaſſe of Abner,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.27. to 39.</note> becauſe he was a neceſſary man in the common wealth. So likewiſe it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Act. 8.2.</note> that there was great lamentation amongſt all the people which feared God, for Saint Steuen, who was a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary man in the Church. This reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious duty is not ſo much required, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their deceaſſes directly, as for our ſelues who were the cauſe thereof
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:6245:107"/>according to the foreknowledge of God, ſometimes arrogating too much worthineſſe vnto them, and therby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating from God; or ſometimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating from them that worthineſſe and deſert which was their due, and thereby do become ſpirituall ſpoilers and vnfaithfull vnto God that gaue them. And I may preſſe farther and iuſtifie out of mine owne lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble experience, that the comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of death paſt vpon others our deare friends, will worke in vs a hartie calling vpon God for mercy, and a kinde of preparation in our ſelues to die well, beſides the good example which we ſhall giue thereby vnto our poſterity to do the like for vs.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:6245:107"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
